<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A surreplication to the reioynder of a popish adversarie VVherein, the spirituall supremacy of Christ Iesus in his church; and the civill or temporall supremacie of emperours, kings, and princes within their owne dominions, over persons ecclesiastical, &amp; in causes also ecclesiasticall (as well as civill and temporall) be yet further declared defended and maintayned against him. By Christopher Sibthorp, knight, one of his majesties iustices of his court of Chiefe-place in Ireland.</title>
            <author>Sibthorp, Christopher, Sir, d. 1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102608</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838380</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838380</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12215)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1117:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A surreplication to the reioynder of a popish adversarie VVherein, the spirituall supremacy of Christ Iesus in his church; and the civill or temporall supremacie of emperours, kings, and princes within their owne dominions, over persons ecclesiastical, &amp; in causes also ecclesiasticall (as well as civill and temporall) be yet further declared defended and maintayned against him. By Christopher Sibthorp, knight, one of his majesties iustices of his court of Chiefe-place in Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Sibthorp, Christopher, Sir, d. 1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the Societie of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini M.DC.XXVII [1627]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2756:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2756:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SVRREPLICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION TO THE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IOYNDER OF A POPISH ADVERSARIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherein,</hi> THE SPIRITVALL SVPREMACY of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> in his <hi>Church;</hi> and the <hi>Civill</hi> or <hi>Temporall Supremacie</hi> of <hi>Emperours, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> within their owne <hi>Dominions,</hi> over <hi>Perſons Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> &amp; in cauſes alſo <hi>Eccleſiasticall</hi> (aſwell as <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Temporall</hi>) be yet further declared defended and maintayned againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> CHRISTOPHER SIBTHORP, <hi>Knight, one of his Majeſties Iuſtices of his Court of Chiefe-place in</hi> IRELAND.</p>
            <q>Give therefore unto Ceſar the things that bee Ceſars, and unto God the things that be Gods. <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 22.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>He that is not with mee <hi>(ſaith Chriſt)</hi> is againſt me: And he that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth not with me ſcattereth. <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke. 11.23;</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at DVBLIN by the Societie of Stationers. <hi>Anno Domini</hi> M.DC.XXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2756:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2756:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did expect (Courteous Reader) that before I had written any word in theſe matters, both my <hi>firſt Booke,</hi> and my <hi>ſecond</hi> alſo (which is my <hi>Reply</hi>) ſhould firſt have beene anſwered, and that in ſuch ſort as in the <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> annexed at the end of the ſame my <hi>Reply</hi> is declared: but therein I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive mine expectation is deceaved, and that my <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie</hi> without any regard had to that which I deſired, hath taken his owne courſe, and put forth a <hi>Rejoynder</hi> to that my <hi>Reply.</hi> In which his <hi>Rejoynder</hi> I am ſorry to ſee how much he, debating the point of <hi>Supremacie</hi> wrongeth not onely <hi>Me,</hi> and his <hi>Reader,</hi> and the auncient Chriſtian <hi>Emperours</hi> and auncient <hi>Fathers,</hi> but even <hi>CHRIST IESVS</hi> alſo himſelfe, and all <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> generally in reſpect of their ſeverall rights to them belonging. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I thought it not meete or ſeemely, for me in this caſe to be ſilent, or to deſiſt, but, (being thus provoked) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, and to make and publiſh a <hi>Surreplication</hi> to that <hi>Rejoynder.</hi> And this I doe the rather, that ſo a <hi>third book</hi> being added to my <hi>two former,</hi> they all three together might ſerve ſo much the more ſtrongly to perſwade him, and the reſt of the pretended <hi>Catholickes</hi> to the truth in this cauſe for <hi>vis unita fortior,</hi> &amp; a threefold corde is not eaſily broken. If by all or any of my labours, I ſhall bee a meane or helpe to worke their conformitie or reformation I ſhall be glad of it, for it is the maine thing I ſeeke after:
<pb facs="tcp:2756:3"/> but if they hate to be reformed and will in contempt and ſcorne of all admonitions live &amp; die in their errors (which were a caſe moſt fearefull, deſperate, and lamentable,) whom can they blame therein but themſelves, and their Popiſh teachers, by whom they are ſo much miſled and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. My <hi>Adverſarie</hi> when he tooke upon him to anſwer the two Chapters in my first Booke did not prefixe thoſe two Chapters of mine to his anſwer: neyther when hee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my <hi>Reply</hi> did he prefixe my <hi>Reply</hi> to his <hi>Rejoynder:</hi> And therefore alſo, neyther did I prefixe his anſwere to my <hi>Reply,</hi> nor his <hi>Rejoynder</hi> to this my <hi>Surreplication.</hi> Whereat, neyther he, nor any other for him hath cauſe to be offended, or to take exception, in aſmuch as I doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in but follow his owne preſident and example, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe firſt uſed, and wherein hee began unto mee. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, nevertheleſſe, marrow, pith, and ſtrength of all his Bookes, and of his reaſons and arguments therein contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I omit not but mention, and that uſually, or rather evermore in his owne words, and doe alſo make anſwere thereunto. But I am loth any longer to detaine you: and therefore, I here leave you to the reading of that which followeth: and that which followeth to your owne judicious juſt, and equall cenſure: Beſeeching God to guide us all unto his truth, &amp; to keepe &amp; eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh us therein continually, after that wee once ſee and know it. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2756:3"/>
            <head>A SVRREPLICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION TO THE REIOYNDER OF A POPISH ADVERSARIE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To my Adverſarie.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR: As you throughout your <hi>Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> addreſſed your ſpeech to me, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: ſo doe I in like ſort here direct my ſpeech unto you in this worke of mine. For although I neyther purpoſed nor promiſed it, nor others, (I ſuppoſe) expected it, yet that which you have of late publiſhed againſt my <hi>Reply</hi> hath provoked me once more to ſet penne to paper in defence of that cauſe which you ſo much ſtrive againſt in vaine In the beginning of that your <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> you ſay, that although wee bee different in religion, yet you deſire much, that wee be united in affection. This ſpeech of yours I diſlike not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſavoureth (as I conceive it) of that humanitie and charitie which is to be entertayned, and continued amongſt us, notwithſtanding theſe differences in points of religion: as alſo of ſome good affection, and inclination in you unto Gods trueth: wherein chiefely it is, that wee are to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For, as touching any other kindes of unitie, namely that which is in error and falſehood, I hope you deſire it not becauſe it is as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> rightly calleth it, <hi>Error is conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> a conſpiracie of error againſt the truth. The unitie, which is joyned with divine veritie, is it which <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth, <hi>The unitie of the ſpirit,</hi> and which hee would have all Chriſtians to be evermore verie carefull to obſerve, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.3</note> 
               <hi>Endevour to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2756:4"/> keepe the unitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace:</hi> and hee ſaith againe thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Let us follow the truth in love, and in all things grow up into him which is the head, that is, Chirist;</hi> This truth if we did all earneſtly ſeeke after and follow, and that in love, and in a charitable manner (as here we are required to doe) all our controverſies would the better, and the ſooner be ended and determined which have now ſo long diſquieted many mens mindes, and doe ſo much hinder that which is indeede moſt requiſite, namely, the good and due practiſe of true religion in the world. For how can any practiſe religion aright, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they know which is the right religion, which they are to practiſe, and to walke in? Or how can they know which is the right religion they are to walke in, ſo long as they be doubtfull of it, by reaſon of queſtions, and controverſies, that doe perplexe and diſtract them? The firſt thing then, which men deſirous to live good and godly lives are to ſeeke after, is, in the middeſt of all theſe controverſies to get &amp; obtain within themſelves <hi>a reſolution of a right religion:</hi> which reſolution they can never certainely have or attaine unto, but by meanes of the ſacred and Canonicall Scriptures, which be the onely infallible rule of all divine truth, as I have ſhewed in my firſt Booke: So that the purpoſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of that my firſt Booke, as likewiſe of the ſecond, which is my <hi>Reply,</hi> and of this alſo, was not, nor is, to have men to dwell continually and everlaſtingly in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, but cleane contrariwiſe to have them all ended and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and that as ſpeedily as might bee, in every mans conſcience by diligent ſearching of thoſe holy Scriptures, and finding out thereby what is the undoubted trueth in them: that men being once thus ſatisfied and reſolved of the truth and true religion, might afterward the better, and the more freely apply themſelves to the good and due pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of it in their affections, words, workes, lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, refuſing all other religions of humane invention whatſoever, and the wayes thereof. But now though the truth be never ſo manifeſt and apparant, yet ſome there be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2756:4"/> of that froward and perverſe diſpoſition, that they will not yeelde unto it, but as <hi>Iannes and Iambres withſtood Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſo doe theſe alſo reſist the truth,</hi> being men of corrupt mindes and reprobate concerning the faith, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of which ſort of men (if I could helpe it) I would not have you to be, though you be mine Adverſarie, yea though you were mine utter enemie. And therefore, as to the anſwere which you made to the two Chapters contayned in the firſt part of my firſt Booke, I replyed: ſo to your <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> I have here alſo thought it good to make <hi>a Surreplication;</hi> wherein I muſt not omit to tell you, that as touching the ſecond Chapter of my <hi>Reply,</hi> you have in your <hi>Rejoynder</hi> made no anſwere at all unto it, but it remaineth wholly and entirely unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and conſequently in his full force &amp; ſtrength againſt you. And as touching the firſt Chapter of my <hi>Reply,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Supremacie (upon which point it ſeemeth that all your thoughts were wholly fixed, &amp; imployed) although you make ſome kinde of anſwere in your <hi>Rejoynder</hi> unto it, and ſuch as perchance, you and your partakers may thinke to be ſomewhat ſtrong, yet it is indeede of that great debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, as that upon the matter, it is as good as no anſwere, as will appeare by the ſequele: and yet have you moreover left a great part, even of that firſt Chapter alſo unanſwered. Beſide that you have againe in your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> ſundry things which were before anſwered in my <hi>Reply,</hi> and much other idle, futile, and frivolous ſtuffe, which I ſuppoſe you would never have inſerted into your booke but fro want of better matter in your cauſe.</p>
            <p>For, firſt, what an idle exception is this, that you take to my <hi>Reply</hi> in that I dedicated it to the Right Honourable the Lord Deputie? Why might I not doe ſo? Was it not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? Or was there any inconvenience, or <hi>indecorum</hi> in it? You ſay that his Lordſhip hath taken the Oath of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, which maketh him a direct Partie, &amp; being a Partie, he may not alſo be a Iudge in the ſame cauſe. What? have you ſo ſoone forgotten what your ſelfe did? For when you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2756:5"/> made your anſwere to the two Chapters of my firſt Booke, you may remember that you dedicated it, <hi>To your deareſt countreymen, the Lawyers of Ireland.</hi> You then thought it lawfull and ſeemely enough for you ſo to dedicate it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that by their refuſall and utter diſlike to take the Oath of Supremacie, they manifeſtly ſhewed themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to be Parties. And was this lawfull for you to doe, and was not the other as lawfull at leaſt, or rather much more lawfull, and ſeemely (all things conſidered) for mee to doe? Howbeit, you know alſo, that Bookes be not alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to men to make them Iudges, but ſometimes, and uſually to the end, they ſhould be the Patrons thereof, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit therein alſo, they be not diſallowed but well allowed to paſſe their judgement and cenſure upon the ſame. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede no reaſon had you to diſlike of the dedication of that my Booke unto his Lordſhip, in whom your ſelfe doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that there is ſufficiencie to underſtand, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to diſcerne, and power to commaund. A like ſecond exception you take for that I call the Papiſts of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>Pretended Catholickes,</hi> which title (ſay you) they doe not acknowledge. But whether they acknowledge it or no, it muſt bee graunted, that whileſt they call themſelves <hi>Catholickes,</hi> when <hi>re vera</hi> they bee not ſo, (as I have ſhewed and prooved in my firſt Booke) they can bee no other but <hi>Pretended Catholickes:</hi> As likewiſe hee that calleth himſelfe an honeſt man, when <hi>revera</hi> he is not ſo, is at the moſt, but a pretended honeſt man. Yet another exception you take in this, that you ſay, I call you <hi>Canis feſtinans</hi> and <hi>Luſcus inter caecos:</hi> But you miſtake, in both. For, (in that my epiſtle dedicatorie, of my <hi>Reply</hi>) I did not ſay, that you were <hi>Cani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feſtinans,</hi> but that whileſt in your Anſwere, you ſtrived to make more haſt, then good ſpeede, you ſhewed your ſelfe to be, like <hi>Canis feſtinans, caecos edens catibos:</hi> which is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbiall ſpeech, tolerable enough in the judgment of ſuch, as be not over captious, and often and ordinarily vſed in that ſort and ſence, &amp; to that purpoſe that I uſed it. Neither
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2756:5"/> did I ſay definitely, &amp; expreſſely of you, that you were <hi>Luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus inter caecos,</hi> but my words be theſe: <hi>Regnat inter caecos Luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> which may be aſwell ſpoken of any other, as of you, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you will needs be the man, and ſo take and apply it, (as you doe,) to your ſelfe, particularly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After theſe exceptions, you come next to the the three requeſts, I made to him, that would take up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n him to anſwer my firſt booke: in the firſt whereof I deſired, that he would anſwere it, not by parts, or peaſemeals, but wholly and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, from the beginning of it unto the end: The ſecond was, that he would doe it, not ſuperficialie, and ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, but ſubſtantially, ſoundly, &amp; ſatisfactorily, if he could: Thirdly, I deſired him to doe it, as in love, and charity, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with an affection, only to follow Gods truth, and with all, to ſet his name unto it, as I had done to that booke of mine. But hereunto, you take divers exceptions, though now ſomewhat lately in your <hi>Reioynder.</hi> Firſt you ſay, that theſe being conditions, they ſhould have beene agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the mutuall conſent of parties: and that if any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage be given, it ſhould be in favour of the defendant, as in matter of challenge: for the defendant appoints the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, time, and place; But in this challenge of mine, contrary unto law and cuſtome, I have (ſay you) aſſumed unto my ſelfe, being the challenger, the propoſing of ſuch condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as doe diſadvantage the defendant. It is true, that in contracts, and bargaines betweene man and man, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions muſt be agreed upon by mutuall conſent of parties, before it be, or can be a perfect contract, or a perfect bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, howbeit conditions for all that, not onely may be, but alſo muſt be, firſt propounded before they can bee aſſented unto, or agreed upon. Againe there is aſwell a ſubſequent agreement, as a precedent: As if a man propound, or offer unto you a Leaſe for yeares of lands, upon certaine condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: you may chooſe, whether you will accept of it, or no, upon thoſe conditions; but if, though not at the firſt, yet afterward, you having the election, doe declare your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2756:6"/> and acceptance of it, by entring upon the lands, manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, taking the profits, is it not reaſon you ſhould performe the conditions thereunto annexed? You know how to make the application. And yet neyther was I, when I made that my Booke, contracting, or bargaining with you, or with any other man in particular: For, I then ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did, nor could poſsibly know before hand, who was to be the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> of it, with whom I might ſo contract, nor did I take upon me the perſon of a Challenger, as you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme: For I knew of no duell, that was in the caſe. And as for my defending of Proteſtancie againſt Poperie, it no more proveth me to be a challenger, then your defending of Poperie againſt Proteſtancie, proveth you to be the challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Yea in the concluſion of that my firſt booke <hi>Pag.</hi> 417. it appeareth, that I was ſo farre from taking upon me the perſon, or uſing the words of a challenger, that cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, I uſed onely the peaceable, and friendly words, of <hi>Deſiring,</hi> and <hi>Requeſting.</hi> For there I deſire of him, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hee were, that would take upon him to anſwere that booke of mine, that hee would, in that his anſwere, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obſerve, and performe thoſe three requeſts, or three conditions before mentioned, which I there propounded. All which were reaſonable conditions, and ſuch as (if you well conſider them) were not (as you ſay) diſadvantageable, but much advantageable rather to the cauſe of the anſwerer, if hee had performed them. But here, by the way, you tell me, of a verie compendious courſe, how that my whole firſt booke is anſwered and confuted: For you ſay, that he which fayleth in one point of faith, fayleth in all, and that a refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or diſproofe of any one particular in my booke, is a refutation and diſproofe of all. And for proofe hereof, you cite <hi>S. Iames cap.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10.</note> This you alſo cited, and alledged in your firſt booke. This is a verie ſpeedy courſe, and briefe manner of anſwering and confuting whole bookes, and volumes, if it might be allowed. Howbeit, touching that text of S. <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> which you ſomuch abuſe, and touching that your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2756:6"/> and ſtrange opinion, you have been before ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered in my <hi>Reply Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 110. 111. 112. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you in your <hi>Reioynder</hi> have ſaid nothing. But, admit your <hi>Maior</hi> propoſition were true (which is indeede utterly untrue) yet how doe you prove your <hi>Minor?</hi> that is to ſay, how doe you prove any one point or poſition of mine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in that booke to be falſe? Shew, or name that one, which you have diſproved, or confuted, if you can: but you are not able to doe it. From henceforth therefore bee not ſo prodigall of your words. But yet further to derogate from the credite of that my firſt booke, you ſay, that it is onely a collection out of Proteſtant authors: and that you can diſcover the Bookes, Chapters, and Pages, of <hi>Master Fulke, Maſter Whitakers, Maſter Downam,</hi> &amp; of others, whence I have borrowed, <hi>verbatim,</hi> whatſoever is expreſſed in it. This is too overlaviſh a ſpeech, and more then you will bee ever able to prove. Indeede, as touching the ſubſtance of the matter, and doctrine, contayned in that my firſt booke, and in my ſecond, and in this alſo, I thinke it no ſhame, but contrarywiſe I thinke it honour, and reputation, freely to confeſſe, that I have learned it of thoſe, and of ſuch other learned, and reverend Proteſtant Divines: Yea I hold it a part of dutie in me, not onely ingenuouſly, but thankefully alſo to acknowledge thoſe my teachers: eſpecially conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that what they have taught mee herein, appeareth to bee certainely, and irrefutably true. This therefore doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adde credite to the matter and doctrine, contayned in thoſe my bookes, then derogate, or take any from them. But was there ever any reader of other mens workes, that was not allowed to take collections out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to make uſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as occaſion requireth: yea, if that were an exception ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, I might alſo ſay, that as touching the matter, all that you have ſpoken eyther in yovr firſt anſwer, or in your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der,</hi> is likewiſe but a collection out of Popiſh authors and that the Bookes, Chapters, &amp; Pages of <hi>Bellarmine, Stapleton, Suarez,</hi> and of others, might be ſhewed, whence you have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2756:7"/> borrowed, and taken them all. But to what end, were this? For the queſtion is not, what I have learned, or collected out of the one, or you out of the other: but whether of thoſe doctrines, and religions, which wee have ſeverally learned of thoſe our ſeverall teachers, bee the truer, and which of them is approved of God, and by his word: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether Proteſtancie, or Poperie. Heere then, as touching the ſubſtance of the matter delivered in all my bookes, you might have ſpared your labour: for you have therein tould no newes, nor any more, then my ſelfe had before, affirmed, confeſſed, and acknowledged. But you proceede, and ſay, that although you for your part, have anſweted but onely to two Chapters of that my firſt booke (the force of which your anſwer, I have alſo overthrowne in my <hi>Reply</hi>) that the whole booke is nevertheleſſe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and compleatly finiſhed, and extant any time theſe two yeares and a halfe paſt, and yet not divulged, for want of meanes, and opportunitie for the impreſsion: And, for that cauſe, doe you deſire of mee, that I would bee a meane to procure it to bee Printed, by the Proteſtant Preſſe here in <hi>Dublin.</hi> A verie bold, unbeſeeming, and ſtrange requeſt, to be demaunded, eſpecially at my hands. But if it be (as you ſay it is) fully anſwered, and compleatly finiſhed, ſo long ſince, why is not printed all this while? For whereas you pretend want of meanes, and opportunitie for the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: It is well knowne, that the Papiſts (as ſundrie other their workes printed, ſufficiently declare) doe if they liſt, want neyther meanes nor opportunitie for the impreſsion: And I have tould you heretofore, that if your workes, and bookes bee ſo excellent, and ſo worthy the printing, as you make ſhew for, you might got them to bee Printed, eyther at <hi>Doway,</hi> or at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> or at ſome other place beyond the Seas. And therefore it was altogether idle for you, to give me this election, eyther to receive it in a <hi>Manuſcript,</hi> or to procure the printing of it: for it is needleſſe to receive it in a <hi>Manuſcript,</hi> when it may be Printed: And for the printing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2756:7"/> of it, not I, but your ſelfe muſt procure it, if you will have it done. So that as touching that choyce or offer, you make mee, I hold my ſelfe free, and not neceſſarily tyed or bound, to doe eyther the one, or the other. Yea the very name of a Proteſtant Preſſe (if there were no more) might have beene ſufficient to tell you, that it were utterly unmeete, for Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh workes to come into it, eſpecially thoſe that bee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, and directly made, and contrived, againſt ſuch cleere, high, and important points, as bee alſo by law eſtabliſhed. Now then to come to my ſecond requeſt: I truſt, you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe finde nothing in it, unreaſonable: for I therein deſired no more of the anſwerer, but to anſwer, not ſuperficially, or ſophiſtically, but ſubſtantially, ſoundly, and ſatisfactorily, if he could: ſo that if he could not make ſuch an anſwer, hee might have ſaid ſo, and ſo have beene excuſed. But you are loth to diſable your ſelfe, and therefore as touching the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you made to the two Chapters of that my firſt booke, you ſay, that I am not to judge, whether it be ſubſtantiall, ſound, and ſatisfactory, but that the equall, and indifferent Reader, is to judge of it: which I am well contented, hee ſhould doe, by conferring my <hi>Reply,</hi> with that your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwer. And therefore I proceede to my <hi>third requeſt:</hi> which conſiſteth of two partes: (for I make not foure requeſts, or foure conditions, as you ſurmiſe:) The firſt part of that my third requeſt, was this, that I would have him, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was to be the anſwerer, to anſwer in love, and charitie, and with an affection onely to follow Gods truth. Thus far I am ſure, you cannot denie it to bee a reaſonable requeſt. And as touching the other part of it, whereby I deſired him that would anſwer, to put his name to his anſwer, as I had done to that booke of mine: although this be it, you chiefly except againſt: yet even this part of it alſo, was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable: and therefore did I juſtly reprove you, for that in ſtead of your right name, you gave your ſelfe the wrong, falſe, &amp; counterfeite name of <hi>Iohn at Stile.</hi> But yet, in your <hi>Reioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der,</hi> you, herein, ſeeke to excuſe &amp; defend your ſelfe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2756:8"/> by the example of <hi>Abram,</hi> who comming into <hi>Pharaoh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Court in <hi>Egipt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.11.12.13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> called <hi>Sarai</hi> his wife, by the name of his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: and you adde further, and ſay, that <hi>Matthew Sutcliffe,</hi> a Proteſtant writer, did put for his name unto his worke. <hi>O.E.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt concerning <hi>Abram,</hi> though hee were an holy man, yet hee had his faults and imperfections, amongſt which this is reckoned for one, which you here alleage: And can then that which was a fault in him, make yours to bee no fault? But yet in all that, hee neyther changed his name, nor his wifes name, into a falſe, and counterfeite name, as you did. For hee ſtill called himſelfe <hi>Abram,</hi> and his wife <hi>Sarai,</hi> without any alteration, or change of thoſe their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per names. And as touching <hi>Doctor Sutcliffe,</hi> the reaſon why hee put for his name thoſe two letters <hi>O. E.</hi> was, becauſe the man, whom hee anſwered, had likewiſe for his name, ſubſcribed certaine letters: but, the caſe betweene you and mee is not like. For I ſubſcribed my name truely, and as it was, and therefore ſo ſhould you alſo have done. Howbeit, at the firſt, you excuſed your ſelfe herein, by reaſon of the Statute of 2. <hi>Eliz.</hi> which doth (ſay you, in your firſt anſwer) binde mens tongues, and pennes within this kingdome, with the cord of a <hi>Premunire,</hi> from oppugning the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, eyther by word or writing. Vpon which anſwer of yours, it is true, I did, and who could otherwiſe ſuppoſe, but that you then thought (whatſoever you ſay now) that the penaltie for that your firſt offence againſt that Statute, in oppugning the Kings Supremacie, was a <hi>Premunire:</hi> For to what end elſe doe you ſo ſpecially mention, that to bee the penaltie, if you had not thought ſo? I did not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wrong you (as you now alleage in your <hi>Reioynder</hi>) when I taxed you being a Lawyer,<note place="margin">See the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it ſelfe, of <hi>2.</hi> Eliz. cap. <hi>1</hi> made in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> with ignorance in your owne profeſsion, concerning that Statute. For that Statute doth not (as you then ſuppoſed) for any mans firſt offence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the penaltie of a <hi>Premunire,</hi> but (as I then likewiſe tould you) the loſſe of goods and chattels: after once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and attainder, it is indeede for the ſecond offence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2756:8"/> a <hi>Premunire:</hi> &amp; after twice conviction, &amp; attainder, it is for the third offence, high treaſon. Did you then account it, a wrong done unto you, that I ſuppoſed this to be your firſt offence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that ſtatute? Or would you have had me to think (which was more then I knew at that time &amp; more then yet I know) that you had bin once before convicted &amp; attainted of that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, &amp; that this was your ſecond offence in that kinde? For, unleſſe this were thus your ſecond offence, you needed not to have feared, or mentioned a <hi>Premunire,</hi> to have beene your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie in the caſe: you might aſwell, &amp; as wiſely have named, &amp; mentioned the penaltie, to have beene high treaſon, in aſmuch as for the third offence, that Statute alſo maketh it to be high treaſon, aſwell as it maketh it, for the ſecond offence, to bee a <hi>Premunire.</hi> But I conceived (as I thinke any man elſe, not knowing any thing to the contrarie, would have conceived) that it was not any your ſecond offence, nor third offence, that you then, and there meant, or had any reaſon, or purpoſe to ſpeake of, but your firſt offence, the penaltie of which firſt offence, is, by that Statute, neyther <hi>Premunire</hi> nor high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as I ſaid before) and conſequently (if you would deale ingenuouſly) you muſt confeſſe, that you then miſtooke, and were deceived in opinion, whileſt you thought the penaltie for that your firſt offence to bee a <hi>Premunire,</hi> by that Statute. But then you ſay, that you will not bee ſo ſawcie, as to taxe mee with ignorance in my profeſsion, concerning the ſame Statute, and yet you ſee not (ſay you) how the ſubſcribing of your name unto the anſwer, could have beene any legall plea, to have ſaved you from penaltie, if you had beene indicted upon that Statute: Neyther doe I ſee, how it could, although you would faine wreſt my words from their true ſence, unto that conſtruction. For, whereas you have ſaid, that my requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Anſwerer, to put his name unto the Anſwer, was, in effect, aſmuch, as to debarre any man from anſwering unto it? I thereunto replyed, that hee that in anſwering, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to put his name to his anſwere, is ſo farre from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from anſwering, that cleane contrarywiſe, hee is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (that is, by ſuch requiring of him to anſwer in that ſort) permitted to anſwer (if hee pleaſe) ſo as hee put his name
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2756:9"/> thereunto. I did not ſay (as you ſeeme purpoſely to miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue and miſtake) that by anſwering in that ſort, <hi>viz.</hi> with his name ſubſcribed to his anſwer, he was to be freed from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of penaltie contayned in that Statute of 2. <hi>Eliz.</hi> I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo abſurd, or ſenceleſſe to ſay or thinke it. Yea you might have obſerved, that I there ſhewed and expreſſely affirmed the cleane contrarie, namely, that the penaltie even for the firſt offence againſt that Statute (whether with his name ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or not ſubſcribed, or howſoever,) was loſſe of goods, and chattels. And therefore whether this were ignorance of that point of the Statute in me, or groſſe, perverſe, and malicious cavilling, and quarrelling in you, let the equall Reader judge. But yet in your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> you further ſay: that you cannot <hi>imagine why I ſhould ſo much</hi> covet the anſwerers right name, unleſſe it be by advantage of the Statute in perſecuting him, to confine him into the Caſtle, there to argue with him, as the Gaoler doth with his priſoner. I know no reaſon you have thus to charge me, with ſo much coveting of the Authors, or Anſwerers name. For though it bee lawfull for mee ſo to doe, yet have I not beene much inquiſitive after it: much leſſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon have you to charge mee, in your imaginations, with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting him, or ſeeking to confine him as a priſoner within the Caſtle, which I never did: though I confeſſe hee deſerveth it, and a farre greater puniſhment then that: becauſe, contrary to the lawes, and ſtatutes of the Kingdome, which himſelfe profeſſeth, being (as he ſaith hee is) a Lawyer; and contrary to that dutie, which as a Subject he oweth to our moſt noble, moſt gracious, religious, and moſt worthy Soveraigne Lord King CHARLES, and contrarie to that fealtie alſo, or fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, which (profeſsing himſelfe to bee a Chriſtian) hee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe oweth unto CHRIST IESVS, the onely ſpirituall King Monarch, &amp; head of the whole Church Militant, aſwell as of the triumphant, hee doth, and dareth thus audaciouſly to offend. Neyther is proſecuting, or puniſhing of ſuch bold, and notorious offenders to bee called (as you after the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſticall manner untruly call it) <hi>Perſecuting.</hi> For though <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> doth well befit delinquents, and offenders, yet <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is a word properly, and uſually applyed to the Martyrs of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2756:9"/> Chriſt, and is not attributed to any profeſſors of Antichriſt, or Antichriſtian doctrine, unleſſe it bee <hi>Catacrestically,</hi> &amp; abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively. Howbeit I deale not with you by authoritie, or as a Iudge, or Iuſticer, but doe onely debate, diſpute, and reaſon the matter with you, ſeeking, and endeavouring firſt by this meanes, (if I can,) to reduce, and reclayme you, and the like unto you, from thoſe your grand errours, unto a moſt certaine, and evident truth. But if yet ſtill you urge the Statute of 2. <hi>Eliz.</hi> made in this kingdome, which maketh the penaltie, even for the firſt offence, to be, although not a <hi>Premunire,</hi> yet loſſe of goods and chattels, and that therefore in reſpect of this loſſe and damage it was not a thing reaſonable for me, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund an anſwer with the Anſwerers name, thereunto ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: Thereunto I then further ſay: Firſt, that I know no reaſon why you, or any man elſe, ſhould make any anſwer, or any Bookes, or writings at all, againſt the Kings Supremacie, which you ought in all good dutie to uphold, and defend. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I demaunded not any anſwer at all to be made eyther by you, or any other; but, if any did, or would anſwer, then I deſired, that hee would anſwer in that ſort, <hi>viz.</hi> with his name ſubſcribed: ſo that hee might have choſen, whether hee would have anſwered, yea, or no: and by not anſwering, hee might have kept, and freed himſelfe from penaltie of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute: but if hee would needes anſwer, then hee was to doe it, at his owne perill, if any perill did enſue. And yet I might alſo further tell you, that ſuch a one poſsibly might have beene the Anſwerer, as needed not to feare that perill, or penaltie. For be there not divers Schollers, in Colledges, and Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and elſewhere, that live onely upon other mens exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and beneficence, and have no manner of goods, or chattels, lands or tenements, of their owne? Might not ſuch an one have anſwered, and put his name to his Anſwer, without any feare of that penaltie. Againe, might not ſome forrein-borne Papiſt, living out of the Kings Dominions, and that were no Subject to the King, having well, and perfectly learned the Engliſh tongue, have beene the Anſwerer, and put his name likewiſe to his Anſwer, without any feare of that danger. Or, (which was moſt likely,) might not ſome Engliſh m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2756:10"/> ſome Iriſh man, living &amp; abiding perpetually at <hi>Rhemes, Rome, Doway,</hi> or ſome other place beyond the Seas, have beene the Anſwerer? And would you then have thought it a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable for ſuch a one to have beene demaunded to put, and ſubſcribe his name to his Anſwer? For theſe men living conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually beyond Sea out of the Kings Dominions, feare not, (as wee ſee by experience,) nor thinke, ſo long, as they be ſo farre diſtant, that they neede to feare the penaltie, or danger of any Law, or Statute amongſt us, to bee executed upon them. Yea, what if it were your ſelfe, that were the Anſwerer of it, (as you tooke upon you to be the Anſwerer of two Chapters in it) had it beene unreaſonable to have demaunded of you, to put your name to the Anſwer, in reſpect of any feare of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, or danger, upon that Statute, or of any other Statute, whatſoever? For what penaltie or danger upon any Statute, ſhould you feare, who in your firſt Anſwer, in the Epiſtle to your Countrey-men, write ſo confidently in this your ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Catholicke cauſe, as if you feared no manner of danger at all, but would willingly undergoe all diſaſters in the world for atteſtation and defence of it? But I am now glad to ſee, that you have ſome feare in you: For, indeede, feare in everie man, and not forwardneſſe or boldneſſe in any, beſt becommeth yours ſo bad a cauſe. But yet further, what reaſon have you now, in your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> to except againſt any of theſe three conditions, or three requeſts, or againſt any part of any of them, as unreaſonable, which in your firſt Anſwer, you tooke no exception againſt? Yea which you then ſeemed well to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and allow well of, ſaying, concerning the ſame my whole firſt Booke, that, <hi>It ſhould ſhortly be anſwered in my owne ſtraine of Divinitie with the three conditions required by me.</hi> Yea, laſtly if you would needs be, (as you were) the Anſwerer to a part of that my firſt Booke, (namely, to two Chapters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,) and thought it not fit to put your right and true name unto it: yet, ſhould you not, in ſtead thereof, have given your ſelfe, a wrong, falſe, and counterfeyte name, (which is the thing, I reproved in you:) For, as I ſaid formerly in my <hi>Reply,</hi> ſo I ſay againe, that it had beene much better for you, to have put no name at all to that your Anſwer, then a falſe, wrong,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2756:10"/> and counterfeyte name, as you did.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From thence, you goe on, and renevv a former taxation of yours, namely, for that being a Lawyer by profeſsion. I nevertheleſſe meddle with theſe matters of Divinitie, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning religion: But, concerning this, I told you before, that I had made a ſufficient Apologie for theſe my doings, in that my firſt Booke, whereto, as yet I ſee no Anſwer made: and I added further in my ſecond Booke, namely, my <hi>Reply</hi> that even you your ſelfe did juſtifie mee therein, in aſmuch, as you, being likewiſe a Lawyer, (as you then affirmed, and yet ſtill affirme your ſelfe to bee,) did nevertheleſſe meddle with theſe matters of Divinitie, and concerning religion, aſwell, as I. Neyther is it any excuſe, or defence for you to ſay, (as you doe,) that I began to commit this fault, and that you doe but follow me therein: For, if you ſaw it to bee a fault in mee, you ſhould rather have eſchewed it, then committed it, upon any mans example whatſoever. He that knoweth an Act to be a ſinne, and reproveth, and condemneth another man for it, and yet will himſelfe commit it, is not his ſinne and fault,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1.</note> ſo much the greater? <hi>Therefore art thou inexcuſable, O man, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art,</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Paul,) that condemneſt another: for in that thou condemneſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelfe, for thou that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnest, doſt the ſame things.</hi> Yea, you ſay further, that in your Anſwer formerly made, you ſignified this to be a fault, aſwell in your ſelfe, as in mee. But if you then thought ſo, in verie deede, why did you commit it? Or why doe you ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and continue it? For ſo your <hi>Reioynder</hi> declareth: doth not this then more &amp; more aggravate your offence? And doth it not declare you to bee a man of little conſcience, that dare thus wittingly and willingly, to ſinne againſt your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and to perſiſt alſo in it? <hi>For, if our heart condemne us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.20.</note> (ſaith <hi>S. Iohn,) God is greater then our heart, and knowes all things.</hi> It is high time therefore for you, to give over writing in theſe matters of Religion, if it be againſt your conſcience, and that you verily thinke it to be unlawfull for you, ſo to doe. But, as for me, I am not of that minde, neyther have you ſhewed, nor can you ſhew, any ſufficient or good reaſon, to diſſwade mee. For, whereas you ſuppoſe it to bee unlawfull, or unmeete for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2756:11"/> Lawyers, or other lay-men, to meddle with the Scriptures; and matters concerning Religion, as being a thing out of their element, calling, and profeſsion: Firſt, to forbid or denie lay people, the medling with the Scriptures and with Religion, is knowne to bee an old Popiſh policie, and a moſt wicked, and damnable device: by meanes whereof, mens eyes, being in times paſt thus blinded, and as it were put out, it came to paſſe, that both Pope, and poperie, in thoſe dayes ſo mightily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayled, as they did, in the world, &amp; yet ſtill prevayle, amongſt too too many. For what is it elſe but ignorance of Gods word, and will in the people that keepeth them ſo faſt fettered and chayned both to Pope and poperie. Secondly the untruth of this irreligious, and Antichriſtian opinion, is formerly, and at large diſcovered, and manifeſted in my firſt Booke, which I ſee not yet anſwered: And yet thirdly, you muſt further know, (if already you know it not) that a Lawyer, or any other lay-man, hath a double calling, or a double profeſsion: one worldly, which concerneth the things of this life: the other is his Chriſtian calling, which concerneth, &amp; reſpecteth things belonging to a farre better life, namely to a life everlaſting. This <hi>Christian</hi> calling,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> proveth, deſiring men, <hi>to walke worthy of that calling, whereunto they are called.</hi> Againe, hee prayeth for ſome, that God would make them <hi>worthy of this calling S. Peter</hi> likewiſe ſpeaketh thus:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.11</note> 
               <hi>Yee are a choſen genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a royall Prieſthood, an holy nation, a people ſet at libertie, that yee ſhould ſhew forth the vertues of him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>that hath called you, out of darkeneſſe, into his mervailous light.</hi> And ſundrie other Texts of holy Scripture there be to prove, that there is aſwell a Divine, and Chriſtian calling and profeſsion, as there is a worldly, and terreſtriall. For what? Have not men ſoules to looke to, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as bodies? Or, are men to bee no more but naturall, and meere men?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23.</note> Are they not alſo to become Chriſtian men, and to bee regenerated, aſwell as generated? And doth not <hi>S. Peter</hi> tell us, that men are <hi>regenerated, or borne a new,</hi> not by corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, but <hi>by incorruptible ſeede, even by the word of God, who liveth, and endureth for ever.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</note> And doth he not further adviſe ſome, as <hi>new borne babes, to deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that they may grow thereby.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 3 1 2.</note> For, men, after that they bee once begotten and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2756:11"/> borne a new, by Gods word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.12.13.14.</note> and the power of his ſpirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therewithall, are firſt <hi>Babes</hi> in Chriſt, and afterward by degrees, they grow to bee ſtrong men, and able to digeſt ſtrong meates, untill they come, at laſt, to bee a perfect man, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh. Yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.27.</note> doth not Chriſt himſelfe bid men to <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not for the meate which periſheth, but for that meate which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth unto life everlaſting?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.39 40.41.42.</note> And did he not alſo further tell <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> that ſhee was troubled about many things, but this was the <hi>unum neceſſarium, the one thing that was neceſſarie,</hi> which <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry had choſen,</hi> namely the hearing of his word? Seeing then that Gods word, (which is now long ſithence committed to writing, and is in the ſacred, and Canonicall Scriptures to bee found, and where all truth, concerning points of Divinitie, and Religion is to be had,) is ſo neceſſarie, as that it is the foode, meate, and nouriſhment of Chriſtians, to life everlaſting: How can it be rightly, and truely ſaid, that when they be thus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their aliment, they bee out of their element? For is not the life of the ſoule, to bee preſerved, and maintayned aſwell, or rather much more heedefully, then the life of the body? Or will any ſay, that the fiſh is out of his element, when hee ſwimmeth in the water, where he liveth, and moſt delighteth? Yea as the fiſh removed out of his proper element, dieth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while after: and as the bodie that is deſtitute of corporall foode to ſuſtaine it, muſt needes decay, and die. So the ſoule that hath not this ſpirituall foode of Gods word, to cheriſh, and maintayne it in a ſpirituall life, muſt likewiſe needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, decay, and pine away, untill it come in the end, to utter ruine. You ſee then, that a true Chriſtian,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.16</note> 
               <hi>(Who though he bee in the world, yet is not of the world, but hath his affection ſet upon things that are above, &amp; not on things which are on earth,)</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20</note> is ſo farre from being out of his element, as that, contrarywiſe, hee is within his right, and true element, in reſpect of his ſoule, and the things belonging to a better world, and keepeth himſelfe within the compaſſe, &amp; bounds of that his divine, &amp; Chriſtian calling, ſo long, as hee humbly and reverently, heareth, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſearcheth the word of God, delighteth in it, muſeth and meditateth upon it, talketh of it, and thereout learneth truths and true religion, and propoundeth them alſo unto others, for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2756:12"/> their benefite and inſtruction, aſwell as of himſelfe. Yea, all duties of a Chriſtian, a Lawyer, or other lay-man, may and ought to doe, and performe, as hee is able, and as occaſion requireth: ſo that hee doe them diſcreetely, and with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to all manner of perſons, and ſo long as withall, hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudeth not into thoſe duties, that bee proper, and peculiar to the office, and function of the Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters. As for that your other reaſon, whereby you would diſſwade me, becauſe theſe are points of great difficultie, &amp; ſurpaſſe a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers abilitie, (as you ſpeake:) although I arrogate nothing to my ſelfe, yet why ſhould you ſay, that it ſurpaſſeth a Lawyers abilitie, to deale in theſe things, when as you your ſelfe, being a Lawyer, doe nevertheleſſe intermedle in them? Or why ſhould it ſurpaſſe or exceede a Lawyers talent, or a Lawyers abilitie, in mee, more then in you? Indeede, if a man be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a meere Lawyer, in reſpect of that his meere worldly calling, he is not fitte to deale in matters concerning God, and his religion; But if hee bee a Chriſtian Lawyer, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in the Booke of God, and well grounded in the points of his faith and religion, (as all Lawyers, and other lay-men ought to be,) then in reſpect of that his divine and Chriſtian calling, hee may meddle with points of Divinitie and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, <hi>Eatenus, Quatenus,</hi> ſo farre forth as is before ſhewed, and as is in my firſt Booke more at large declared. And yet there is alſo a more ſpeciall reaſon, why I ſhould bee permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to intermeddle herein, becauſe being not onely a Lawyer, but a Iudge alſo in the Common-weale, it well becommeth mee, and is my dutie, (as I conceive it,) for that reaſon, (ſo much as in me lyeth,) to ſeeke to have the Lawes, and Statutes of the Realme, eſpecially in theſe moſt high, and moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant points, aſwell as in other, that bee inferiour points unto them, to be obſerved of all his Majeſties Subjectes within this kingdome. Neyther are there any ſuch great doubts, or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, in theſe points, as you would perſwade: yea, they bee verie cleare, plaine, open, and evident points, and ſuch as any man, though but of meane underſtanding, may eaſily, and readily conceive, and apprehend. For, firſt, the verie name of a Subject, (if there were no more) may ſerve to teach any man,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2756:12"/> that the King, whoſe Subject hee is, hath of due right a Regall, and Temporall Supremacie, not onely over him, but over all the reſt of his Subjects within his owne Dominions: and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the verie name of a Chriſtian, may ſerve to teach a man, to beleeve, and to profeſſe, no other religion, but that which Chriſt himſelfe taught, eyther by himſelfe, or by his Apoſtles, as alſo, to acknowledge no other to bee the ſpirituall King, head, and Monarch, of the whole Chriſtian Church, but the ſame CHRIST IESVS onely.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Now then, you are come, at laſt, to the matter it ſelfe. Where firſt of all you affirme, and confeſſe two Supremacies: the one ſpirituall, the other temporall. The ſpirituall Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, or ſpirituall Monarchie, (which indeede, rightly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 18.36.57. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20.21.22.23.</note> and properly belongeth unto CHRIST IESVS,) you attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute unto the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> But, by what right? Namely, as being his Deputie; Vicar, or Attorney, (as you call him.) But can you ſhew any letter of Attorney, or any Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Commiſsion, or Warrant from him, or from his word, to prove the ſame? You have ſought long, but could never yet finde or ſhew, any ſuch warrant, although you have preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded divers, which prove no ſuch matter. If then it bee high treaſon, in a ſubject, to take upon him, to bee a Vice-roy, or Lord-Deputie in a terreſtriall kingdome, without a warrant, or Commiſsion from his King: Is, it not likewiſe, as grand &amp; as high a treaſon, in the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to take upon him, to bee Vice-roy, or Deputie unto Chriſt, in his ſpirituall kingdome, without any warrant, or commiſsion from him? But as in the point of the ſpirituall ſupremacie, hee thus intolerably wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, his Crowne, and dignitie: ſo doth hee alſo intolerable wrong to Emperours, Kings, and Princes, and to their Crownes, and dignities, in reſpect of their Civill, and Temporall ſupremacie, &amp; authoritie, rightly, &amp; auncient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging to them, over Perſons Eccleſiaſticall, and in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alſo Eccleſiaſticall, within their ſeverall Dominions. And this to men that bee not extreamely wilfull, perverſe, and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I have very ſufficiently, and abundantly proved, in my firſt, and ſecond Bookes; whereunto, you neyther in your firſt Anſwer, nor yet in your ſecond, (which is your <hi>Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2756:13"/> have alledged any thing that is of force, or weight ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to refell or confute any one Argument I brought, in that behalfe. And herein I refuſe not the judgement, of any equall, and judicious perſon whoſoever. Howbeit, in that your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> to prove the Popes ſupremacie, you cite one Text of Scripture, namely, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. The wordes whereof, becauſe you doe not fully ſet them downe, I will here recite, that the Reader may the better perceive, how well, or ill, they fitte your purpoſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8.9 10 11.12.13.</note> the wordes be theſe. <hi>If there ariſe a matter to hard for thee, in judgement, betweene bloud, and bloud betweene plea, and plea, and betweene ſtroke, and ſtroke, being matter of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie within thy Gates, then ſhalt thou ariſe and get unto the place, which the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe. And thou ſhalt come unto the Priests, Levites, and unto the Iudge, that ſhall be in thoſe dayes, and enquire, and they ſhall ſhew thee the ſentence of judgement, and thou ſhalt doe according to the ſentence, which they of that place, (which the Lord ſhall chooſe) ſhall ſhew thee: according to the ſentence of the Law, which they ſhall teach thee, thou ſhalt doe: Thou ſhalt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from the ſentence which they ſhall ſhew thee, to the right hand, nor to the left. And the man that will doe preſumptuouſly, and will not bearken unto the Priest, that ſtandeth to miniſter there, before the Lord thy God, or unto the Iudge, even that man ſhall die: and thou ſhalt put away the evill from Iſrael, and the people ſhall heare, and feare, and doe no more preſumptuouſly.</hi> Here, for the honour of the Prieſt, you ſay, that hee is in this caſe to bee obeyed, upon penaltie of death: and why doe you not ſay aſmuch for the honour of the Iudge, that is, of the civill Magiſtrate? For the wordes of the Text doe ſhew, that diſobedience aſwell to the one, as to the other, was puniſhable with death. But you will ſay peradventure as the Ieſuites did, that the Latin tranſlation, called <hi>S. Ieromes,</hi> was, in times paſt, <hi>Ex decreto Iudicis morietur home ille, By the decree of the Iudge, ſhall that man die,</hi> that obeyeth not the Prieſt.<note place="margin">In his Booke against the Ieſuites, part. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>33. 34 35.</hi>
               </note> To whom that reverend, and learned Biſhop <hi>Doctor Bilſon,</hi> anſwereth, that it was a corrupt tranſlation, and that the verie ſame tranſlation, not long ſithence, was not, <hi>Ex decreto Iudicis,</hi> but, <hi>&amp; decreto Iudicis:</hi> hee that obeyeth not the commaundement of the Prieſt, and the decree of the Iudge, that man ſhall die. This was, (ſaith he,) the text of the <hi>Bible,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2756:13"/> which you call <hi>S. Ieromes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nich. de Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in Deut. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> not much more then two hundred yeares ſince, when <hi>Nicholaus de Lyra,</hi> &amp; your ordinarie Gloſſe, did comment upon it: and ſo they read to this day, as alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny written coppies, which I have ſeene, (ſaith hee.) And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no ſmall blemiſh to the Papiſts, that, in former times, they had alſo thus corrupted, even that which they call <hi>S. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes</hi> tranſlation. Hee further ſheweth, that the originall <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> and the <hi>Greeke</hi> tranſlation of the <hi>Septuagints,</hi> bee alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt that their then corrupted tranſlation, in this point. And ſo did <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> alſo repeate this Text.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> epiſt. <hi>3.8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> libr. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>4</hi> epiſt. <hi>9</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Et homo quicunque fecerit in ſuperbia, ut non exaudiat ſacerdotem, aut Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, quicunque fuerit in diebus illis, morietur homo ille: Et omnis popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, tum audierit timebit. And the man whoſoever ſhall in pride, not heare the Prieſt, or the Iudge, which ſhall be in thoſe dayes, that man ſhall die, and the people, when they ſhall heare of it, ſhall feare.</hi> Firſt then, obedience, is by the wordes of this text, commaunded, aſwell toward the Iudge, that is to ſay, the civill Magiſtrate, as toward the Prieſt. For you ſee, the Prieſt, and the Iudge, therein, to bee not all one, but directly diſtinguiſhed, yea, by Iudges, as by the chiefe rulers, was Iſrael ſometimes governed, and that for ſundrie yeares, untill kings were appointed, as the Booke of <hi>Iudges,</hi> it ſelfe declareth. And when Kings were appointed, both Prieſts, and Iudges were ſubject to the Kings, as the Bookes of <hi>Samuel,</hi> of the <hi>Kings,</hi> and of the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> doe ſhew: And for an evident proofe hereof, you may take the example, of that godly, and religious King, <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> amongſt the reſt. For hee not onely ſet Iudges in the land, throughout all the fenced Cities of <hi>Iudah,</hi> Citie by Citie, but hee ſaid likewiſe to thoſe Iudges. <hi>Take heede what yee doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6.7.8 9.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>for yee judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: wherefore now let the feare of the Lord bee upon you, take heede, and doe it: For there is no iniquitie with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts. Moreover, in Ieruſalem, did Iehoſhaphat ſet of the Leuites, and of the Prieſts, and of the chiefe of the Fathers of Iſrael, for the iudgement of the Lord, and for contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, when they returned to Ieruſalem: and he charged them, ſayng: Thus ſhall you doe in the feare of the Lord, faithfully, and with a perfect heart. And what cauſe ſoever ſhall come unto you, of your
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2756:14"/> brethren, that dwell in the Cities, betweene bloud and bloud, betweene Law and Commaundement, Statutes and Iudgements, yee ſhall warne them, that they treſpaſſe not against the Lord, and ſo wrath come upon you, and upon your brethren: this doe, and yee ſhall not treſpaſſe. And, behold, Amariah, the Priest, ſhalbe the chiefe over you, in all matters of the Lord: and Zebadiah, the ſonne of Iſhmael, a ruler of the houſe of Iudah, for all the Kings matters: and the Levites ſhall be Officers before you. Deale couragiouſly, and the Lord ſhall be with the good.</hi> Where you ſee, that in the time of the Kings, the Iudges, and the Prieſts alſo, were ſubject to the King, and at his ordering, and appointment: For all theſe, both Iudges, Prieſts, and Levites, did King <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> thus conſtitute, and appoint. But now, ſecondly, obſerve, that both the Prieſt, and the Iudge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.11</note> mentioned in this Text of <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. were to Iudge, and give ſentence, not as they liſted themſelves, but <hi>according to the Law;</hi> which God himſelfe had given in thoſe caſes. So that the ſentence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal</hi> 2.7.8.9 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.10.11 12, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23 11.12.13. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 56.10.11. <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.13.14 <hi>Ezec.</hi> 22.25.26. <hi>Micah.</hi> 3.5. 6 7. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23.4.5.6.7.8. <hi>&amp;c. Iere.</hi> 26.7.8. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.1.2 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.40.</note> not onely of the inferiour Prieſts, but even of the chiefe or high-Prieſt himſelfe, was not alwayes certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, and evermore infallible, (as you ſay it, was,) unleſſe it were directed, and done, according to that law. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they might, and did erre in their judgements. Yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny complaints were in the old Teſtament, againſt them, for their errours, and going aſtray from Gods law: inſomuch, that although they ſaid, (as the Papiſts likewiſe doe of their Prieſt of <hi>Rome,) Non peribit lex à Sacerdote, That the law ſhall not periſh from the Prieſt, (Ierem.</hi> 18.18.) yet God himſelfe ſayed otherwiſe, namely, that, <hi>Lex peribit à Sacerdote, The law ſhall periſh from the prieſt, Ezech.</hi> 7.26. And for further proofe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, remember that <hi>Aaron</hi> was the high Prieſt, and yet that he with the reſt of the Prieſts, and people, erred when they made the golden Calfe. Againe, were they not the Prieſts, and Prophets, that gave ſentence of death againſt <hi>Ieremie,</hi> Gods true Prophet? was that therefore a juſt ſentence, which was ſo given againſt him? Was it not alſo in a Councell, that <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> the high Prieſt, commaunded men that ſtood by, to ſmite <hi>S. Paul</hi> on the mouth? was it therefore well done, and juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? Was not, (moreover,) the high Prieſt preſent in that Councell, which commaunded the Apoſtles to teach no more
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2756:14"/> in the name of IESVS? was that therefore a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement? or a good and allowable decree, that was thus made againſt them? Yea, was not the high Prieſt preſent in that Councell, wherein CHRIST himſelfe was condemned?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26.59 62.63.65.66.</note> And did not hee, in that Councell, ſay expreſſely of Chriſt, that hee had ſpoken blaſphemie? It is then verie apparant, that not onely the inferiour Prieſts, but even the high Prieſt alſo, though joyned, &amp; aſſembled with others in a Councell, might nevertheleſſe poſsibly erre, and did erre ſometimes, in his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and giving of judgement. And therefore, ſo alſo may the Pope of <hi>Rome erre,</hi> not onely as hee is ſingly conſidered by himſelfe, but even though hee be joyned with others in a Councell, admitting, that hee were the high Prieſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2 3.4. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.20.</note> in the Chriſtian Church, which hee is not, as I have ſhewed in my <hi>Reply, pag.</hi> 10.11. whereto you have made no Anſwer in your <hi>Reioynder.</hi> For the ſacred Scriptures, acknowledge no other high Prieſt, in the Chriſtian Church, but CHRIST IESVS onely, nor any other to be the chiefe <hi>Sheepheard,</hi> or <hi>Supreame Paſtor, over all the ſeverall Paſtors, of all the ſeverall flockes in the world,</hi> but onely CHRIST IESVS. But yet here, third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, obſerve, that this Text of <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. (which you cite,) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth onely the Iewiſh policie, or Common-wealth of the Iewes, as being a part of the <hi>Iudiciall law,</hi> proper to that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and which is now abrogated, and aboliſhed. For to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine thoſe harder, and difficulter queſtions, and litigious caſes, concerning bloud, and the other things there mentioned, the partie grieved is required to reſort to the <hi>Leviticall Prieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu</hi> 17.8.9</note> (of which ſort there be none at this day amongſt Chriſtians:) and againe, <hi>To the place, which the Lord their God ſhould chooſe,</hi> which was in aftertimes, <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where the Temple was builded, and where <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> alſo, (according to this law,) erected, and conſtituted <hi>a Synedrion,</hi> or Councell, conſiſting of <hi>Levites, Prieſts,</hi> and of the chiefe of the Fathers of Iſrael, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.8.9. But none is bound at this day, to goe to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> to have his litigious and doubtfull caſes, to bee decided and determined, by any <hi>Leviticall Prieſt,</hi> or other <hi>Iudges</hi> there: Neyther is <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> nor is the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> or his <hi>Priests,</hi> any of thoſe Prieſts, deſcended of the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Levi.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2756:15"/> And therefore alſo, will not this text of <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. any way ſerve your turne, nor helpe to maintayne your Popes ſo long vainely fancied Supremacie.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But I proceede, proſecuting matters, not confuſedly, as you doe, but for the moſt part, in that ſort, and order, as they be layed downe in my <hi>Reply,</hi> that ſo the Reader alſo may the better and the more eaſily perceive, both what you have An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in this your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> and what, and how much you have left unanſwered,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom <hi>4.</hi> de verb. Eſa vid. Dom.</note> as alſo how good, or bad your Anſwers bee. In my <hi>Reply</hi> therefore, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. I ſaid, that <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> (diſtinguiſhing thoſe two offices, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Regall, and Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotall,) did ſay thus: <hi>Ille cogit, hic exhortatur: ille habet arma ſenſibilia, hic arma ſpiritualia: The King compelleth, the Prieſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth: the King hath ſenſible weapons, the Prieſt hath ſpirituall weapons.</hi> Hereunto you Anſwer, that <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> meant one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the King with his ſenſible weapons, (of impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, baniſhment, pecuniarie mulcts, temporall death, and other penalties,) ſhould force, (when other meanes fayled,) the rebellious children of the Church, to performe their dutie unto their Prince, &amp; Prelate &amp; not, that the Prince hath any power over the Paſtor, unto whom, (ſay you,) by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, hee is ſubjected; and thus you make the King, to have power onely over ſuch, as you here call the children of the Church, but not over Biſhops, Paſtors, and other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Miniſters: and of this opinion you would drawe <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> to bee, againſt his owne good will, and liking. But although by his words precedent, and ſubſequent, (which you ſo much ſpeake of.) it appeareth that Kings and Princes are to bee ſubject, to Biſhops and Paſtors, in reſpect of the due adminiſtration of thoſe their ſacred offices, functions, and miniſteries, committed to them from God: yet in reſpect of themſelves, and of their owne Perſons, hee held them verie clearely, to bee not ſuperiour, but ſubject, to Kings, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>13.1.</hi> Chryſ. ho. <hi>23.</hi> in epistol. ad Rom.</note> For whereas <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Let everie ſoule be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the higher powers:</hi> The ſame <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, (which I mervaile you have ſo ſoone forgotten,) that, <hi>omnibus iſta prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiuntur, Sacerdotibus quo que ac Monachis, &amp; non ſolum ſecularibus. Theſe things be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to all, even to Prieſts alſo, &amp; to Monckes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2756:15"/> and not to lay, or ſecular men onely.</hi> Yea hee ſaith further, in the ſame place, that though you bee an <hi>Apoſtle, though an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, though a Prophet, or whatſoever you bee, you must be ſubiect to theſe higher powers.</hi> Remember againe,<note place="margin">Chryſ. ad Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Antioch homil. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that ſpeaking of the <hi>Emperour,</hi> hee ſaith, that <hi>Non habet parem ullum ſuper terram, He hath no Peere, nor equall upon earth.</hi> Yea, hee ſaith of him, that hee was, <hi>Caput &amp; ſummit as omnium ſuper terras hominum, The head, and one that had the ſupremacie over all men upon earth.</hi> Yea, <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> himſelfe, did yet further, really, and actually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this ſubjection, to theſe higher powers, even in his owne perſon: For did not the <hi>Emperour</hi> exile and baniſh him?<note place="margin">Socrat. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi> graec, &amp; cap. <hi>14.</hi> Latine. Theodor. lib. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>2.4.13</hi> Theodor. lib. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>2.4 13.</hi>
               </note> And did not hee, though Archbiſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe thereunto, and yeelde obedience? Was not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Liberius,</hi> though a Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> exiled, and baniſhed by the <hi>Emperour,</hi> and did not hee alſo quietly ſubmit himſelfe unto it, as being done by the <hi>Emperours</hi> commaundement, and authoritie? And was not alſo <hi>Atbanaſius,</hi> baniſhed by the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours</hi> authoritie, and did not he likewiſe patiently, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diently undergoe it? You ſee then, that not onely lay people, and ſuch as you call the children of the Church, but even thoſe alſo that were Fathers in the ſame, as namely Biſhops, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Archbiſhops, and even Biſhops of <hi>Rome themſelves,</hi> were, in thoſe former, and auncient times,<note place="margin">Pelag. Epist. <hi>16.</hi> Concil. edit. Bin. tom. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>633.</hi>
               </note> ſubject to theſe higher powers, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to Emperours, Kings, and Princes: <hi>Quibus nos etiam ſubditos eſſe ſanctae Scripturae praecipiunt:</hi> To whom, (ſaith alſo <hi>Pelagius</hi> another Biſhop of <hi>Rome) the holy Scriptures com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, even us that be Biſhops and the Biſhops of Rome to be ſubiect.</hi> So that thoſe Biſhops, in thoſe dayes, performed this ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and obedience, unto them, as being moved thereunto, out of dutie, and good conſcience, and becauſe God, in his holy Scriptures, had ſo commaunded. But theſe two points, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that, Emperours, Kings, and Princes bee ſubject to that authoritie, meſſage, and miniſterie, which God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Biſhops, and Paſtors: And, that Biſhops againe, and Paſtors, &amp; all Miniſters Eccleſiaſticall, be, nevertheleſſe, ſubject to Emperours, Kings, and Princes, in reſpect of their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is largely declared, both in my firſt Booke, &amp; in my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply</hi> alſo aſwell as here. As for thoſe precedent, and ſubſequent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2756:16"/> wordes in <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> (which you ſo often ſpeake of,) even you aſwell as I, might verie well have omitted them, as being needleſſe to be mentioned, becauſe the matter, and ſubſtance of them, was before graunted, and confeſſed by me, in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Bookes,</hi> as it is likewiſe here againe in this, and yet you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the neerer of your purpoſe. And therefore you had no cauſe to complaine of the omiſsion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by me, when the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citall of them by you, will do you no more good, nor prove, or inferre any more matter in your behalfe, then that which was formerly by me confeſſed, and granted unto you: But leaſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all, had you to inſinuate, as though by omiſsion of thoſe precedent, and ſubſequent wordes, I had a meaning to delude my Reader, by concealing the truth: For you ſee, that I had no ſuch purpoſe, or meaning, to conceale that truth, which my ſelfe had formerly delivered, and graunted, and which I ſtill confeſſe with <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> touching the ſubjection of Princes to Gods authoritie, committed to his Miniſters: But it is your ſelfe in verie deede, which abuſe, &amp; delude your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in this caſe, by concealing truth. For although you tell ſome truth, you tell not the whole truth, as you ought, but conceale a part of it, or, (which is worſe,) you denie a part of it, inaſmuch as you affirme, the ſubjection of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, and Princes to that authoritie, which God hath committed to his Biſhops, and Paſtors. But the other part of truth, concerning the ſubjection, which Biſhops, Paſtors, and all Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters, (aſwell as lay people,) owe and are to performe to Emperours, Kings, and Princes, in reſpect of their owne perſons, this you conceale, and doe not affirme: Yea, you doe directly denie it, although <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> (as here is manifeſt) doth directly affirme it. Henceforth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wrong not <hi>S Chryſoſtome</hi> in this point as you doe, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude your Reader any longer with theſe your falſe Comments and untrue ſurmiſes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But in my <hi>Reply pag.</hi> 2. I further cited the text of 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.2. where <hi>S. Paul</hi> exhorteth Chriſtians, to pray chiefly, &amp; eſpeciall for Kings, and all that are in authoritie, that, under them, <hi>We may lead a quiet, and peaceable life,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (which you ſay, I Engliſh thus,) in all godlineſſe, and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2756:16"/> But you are deceived: for, although I put theſe wordes ſo together in the Engliſh, yet I make them not all, to be the Engliſh of thoſe <hi>Greeke</hi> wordes. Everie meane <hi>Grecian</hi> knoweth, that the Engliſh of thoſe <hi>Greeke</hi> wordes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is no more, but in all godlineſſe: but I added the other wordes, (and honeſtie,) not as being ſignified by thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Greeke</hi> wordes, but as being other wordes, annexed in the Engliſh Text, the <hi>Greeke</hi> whereof, I did not then mention, which is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now all being put together, both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the Text is, (as I rightly recited it,) <hi>in all godlineſſe, and honeſtie.</hi> And therefore in all this you doe but <hi>Nodum in ſirpo quaerere,</hi> which becommeth you not. But why doe you further ſay, that I cite this Text to no purpoſe: I ſhewed you in my <hi>Reply,</hi> to what end and purpoſe, I cited it: namely, to declare, that Kings and Princes, are to reſpect aſwell pietie, godlineſſe, and religion, as civill hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and correſpondencie of humane ſocietie. For, beſide, that the wordes of the Text, doe plainely import ſomuch, can any reaſonable man ſuppoſe, that eyther <hi>S. Paul</hi> would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort Chriſtians, or that Chriſtians themſelves would pray for Kings, and Princes, for this reſpect, and to this end onely that they ſhould maintayne externall worldly peace, civill hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and humane ſocietie, without any reſpect or regard had at all, unto pietie, godlineſſe, and to that Chriſtian religion, they held and profeſſed, and which they more eſteemed then their lives, and more then all earthly treaſures and worldly happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whatſoever? Yea, to this end, and purpoſe it was, that I there alſo mentioned ſome ſpeeches of <hi>Iuſtinian, Valentinian,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> Emperours, teſtifying, and declaring their chiefeſt care within their Empyres and Dominions, to be, for, and concerning Gods religion: whereunto you have not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. But yet for further proofe hereof, I alledged in the ſame my <hi>Reply pag.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Aug. contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Creſcon. lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> that cleere teſtimonie alſo of <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> where hee ſheweth, that <hi>It is enioyned Kings from God that in their kingdomes, they ſhould commaund good things, and forbid evill things, not onely ſuch things, as belong to humane ſocietie, but ſuch things alſo, as belong to Gods religion.</hi> You ſay, the wordes of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> be theſe <hi>In this, Kings, as they bee commaunded
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2756:17"/> from heaven, doe ſerve God as they be Kings, if in their kingdomes, they commaund good, prohibite ill, not onely what pertaynes to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſocietie, but alſo what pertaynes to divine religion.</hi> Let the wordes bee as you relate them, all commeth to one effect, as touching that purpoſe for which I alledged him. For what? Is it not all one in ſence, to ſay, that Kings are enjoyned from God, and Kings are commaunded from heaven? For when you ſay, that Kings are commaunded from heaven; I make no doubt, but you meane thereby, the ſame thing that I doe. when I ſay, it is enjoyned Kings from God: &amp; when you ſay againe, that Kings doe, (as they are commaunded from heaven,) ſerve God as Kings, if in their Kingdomes, they commaund good, and prohibite ill, not onely what pertaynes to humane ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but what alſo pertaynes to divine Religion: Doe not theſe wordes of yours, as clearely, and as ſtrongly prove, the Kings authoritie, in matters Eccleſiaſticall, and concerning Religion, as my wordes doe, <hi>when I ſay, that it is enioyned Kings from God, that in their kingdomes, they ſhould commaund good things, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid evill things, not onely ſuch things, as belong to humane ſocietie, but ſuch things alſo, as belong to Gods religion?</hi> Yea, even your ſelfe, forced by the unreſiſtable evidence of this teſtimonie of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> doe at laſt yeeld, and graunt, that Kings may commaund in things belonging to religion: But then what thoſe things bee, which the King may commaund, belonging to religion, you ſeeme to ſay, that they be Theft Rape, and ſuch like. And yet you cite the ſame <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> affirming, that <hi>utiliſsium, &amp; ſaluberrimum est, &amp;c.</hi> It is moſt profitable, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that the King make lawes to reſtraine the free will of man, from tranſgreſsing in ſuch things, as the law of God doth intimate unto us. Hereby, you may perceive, that you needed no better confuter then your ſelfe. For be onely, Theft, Rape, and ſuch like civill offences, prohibited by the law of God? And be not Idolatrie, falſe worſhip, blaſphemie, and other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences againſt God and his religion, by the ſame law of God alſo prohibited? Yea, <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> himſelfe, (as you ſee,) here diſtinguiſheth betweene things belonging to humane or civill ſocietie, and things belonging to divine religion: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt not confound thoſe things, which hee hath ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2756:17"/> directly diſtinguiſhed. Now, Theft, Rape, and ſuch like offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, concerne civill, or humane ſocietie, and bee offences againſt the ſecond Table of Gods Law: but there be alſo offences, that bee done immediatly againſt God, which bee compriſed in the firſt Table of his Law. And did you never reade nor heare, that the King is, <hi>Custos utriuſque Tabulae, The keeper of both the Tables?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18.19.</note> Why was the Booke of Gods law, at the firſt inſtitution of Kings in the Common-weale of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> required to be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the King? And why was hee charged to reade therein, all the dayes of his life, and to keepe all the wordes, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances contayned in it, if hee were not aſwell to ſee the duties of the firſt Table of the Law, as of the ſecond, to bee obſerved within his kingdome? For, the Booke of Gods law, comprehendeth more then the duties of the ſecond Table. And you muſt obſerve that this was enjoyned to him, not in reſpect of his private converſation onely, as hee was a man, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Regall and Princely office and function ſpecially: For, when he was ſet upon the throne of his Kingdome, then it was, that, he was enjoyned theſe things, as the verie wordes of the Text it ſelfe, doe expreſſely teſtifie. Wherfore, well ſpake <hi>S. Auguſtine, That a King ſerveth God one way, as hee is a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug epiſt. <hi>50</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and another way, as he is a King: as hee is a man, hee ſerveth God by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faithfully: As hee is a King, hee ſerveth God in ſetting forth lawes to commaund, that which is good, and to remove the contrarie. So that Kings, as Kings, ſerve God, in doing that for his ſervice, which none but Kings can doe.</hi> Yea, that Kings may puniſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, blaſphemie, ſacriledge, ſchiſme, hereſie, and all the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the firſt Table, aſwell as Thefts, Rapes, Murthers, Adulteries, and other offences againſt the ſecond Table of his law,<note place="margin">Aug. cont. <hi>2.</hi> Gaudentis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> yet further directly ſheweth againſt the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts,</hi> ſaying. <hi>Cry thus, if, you dare, let murthers be puniſhed, let adulteries be puniſhed, let other degrees of luſt, and ſinne, be puniſhed: onely ſacriledges,</hi> (that is, wronging of Gods truth, and his Church,) <hi>we will not have to be puniſhed by Princes lawes.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Aug. contr. epiſt. Parmen. lib. cap. <hi>7.</hi> Galat. <hi>5.19.20.21.</hi>
               </note> he ſpeaketh thus. <hi>Will the Donatiſts, though they were convinced of a ſacrilegous ſchiſme, ſay, that it belongeth not to the Princes power to correct, or puniſh theſe things? Is it, becauſe ſuch powers, doe not extend to corrupt &amp; falſe religion?</hi> The workes of the fleſh, <hi>S. Paul
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2756:18"/> reckoneth to be theſe: Adulterie, fornication, uncleanneſſe, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe idolatrie, witchbraft, hatred, debate, emulation, wrath, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, ſeditious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cont. Epiſtol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>armen. libr. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hereſies, envie, murthers, drunkenneſſe, gluttonie, and ſuch like What thinke theſe men,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine? May the crime of idolatrie bee iuſtly revenged by the Magistrate? or may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches be rightly puniſhed by the rigor of Princes lawes? and yet will they not acknowledge, that heretikes and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>biſmatickes, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the ſame, when S.</hi> Paul <hi>rehearſeth them al ogether with the other fruites of iniquitie? W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll they reply that earthly powers are not to meddle with ſuch matters? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o what end then, doth he beare the ſword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23</note> 
               <hi>which is called Gods miniſter, ſerving to puniſh malefactors? Chriſt</hi> ſaith in the Goſpell: <hi>Goe out into the high wayes, and hedges and compell them to come in,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. cont. <hi>2.</hi> Gaud. Epist. lib <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi> Epiſtol, So. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ont. <hi>2.</hi> Gaud. epiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>17.</hi> &amp; epiſtol. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that mine houſe may be filled. Wee take wayes,</hi> (ſaith <hi>S Auguſtine,) for hereſies: and hedges, for ſchiſmes: becauſe, wayes, in this place, ſignifie the diverſeneſſe; and, hedges, the perverſeneſſe of opinions. If then thoſe that be found in the high wayes, and hedges, that is in hereſies, and ſchiſmes, must be compelled to come in, let them not miſlike, that they be forced: For this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by Princely power, occaſioneth many to be ſaved, who though they be violently brought to the feaſt of the great houſholder, and compelled to come in, yet being there, they finde cauſe to rejoyce, that they did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, though at firſt againſt their wills.</hi> But here you tel me, (though ſomewhat unſeaſonably,) that you cited in your Anſwere, a Decree or Canon, made in the firſt Councell of <hi>Nyce,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring evidently, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (whom you unjuſtly, and untruely call, the ſupreame Paſtor of the whole Militant Church,) had the Supreamacie in that time, &amp; that unto this pregnant proofe produced by you, I onely reply, as Maskers doe with <hi>Mumme.</hi> Why? what needed any reply at all unto it? For I had anſwered it before, in my firſt Booke, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 12. Where I affirmed, and ſhewed it to bee a forged, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyte Canon, by diverſe Councels, as namely by the ſixth Councell of <hi>Carthago, cap.</hi> 3. by the <hi>Affrican</hi> Councell, <hi>cap.</hi> 92. <hi>&amp;</hi> 101. <hi>&amp;</hi> 105. and by the <hi>Milevitane</hi> Councell, <hi>cap.</hi> 22. Yea the verie fifth, and ſixth Canons, (which bee confeſſed to bee undoubtedly true Canons,) of the Councell of <hi>Nyce,</hi> doe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſufficiently declare, that other Canon, (which you, and other Papiſts alſo alledge,) to bee falſe, and forged. And not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2756:18"/> onely thoſe Councels, but the Decrees of other Councels alſo, decreeing againſt the ſupremacie of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (as is ſhewed in the ſame my firſt booke, <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 16. 17. 18.) do therby likewiſe conſequently declare, that Canon of the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> which you ſpeake of, to be a new forged thing. But if you deſire yet further proofe thereof, againſt the objections, and allegations that Papiſts make in this caſe, then reade that Booke of juriſdiction, <hi>Regall, Epiſcopall, Papall,</hi> made by that worthy, learned, and reverend Biſhop <hi>Doctor Carleton, cap.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 69. 70. 71. 72. 73. 74. 75. 76. 77. And reade alſo for the ſame purpoſe, <hi>The Catholicke Appeale</hi> for the Proteſtants made by that reverend, worthy, and learned Biſhop <hi>Doctor Morton, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 467 468 469. 470. 471. 472. 473. 474. 475. 476. and there ſhall you ſee this Canon, ſo fully maintayned to bee forged againſt the adverſaries, as that it is now a ſhame for you, or any other Papiſt, to cite or produce it, for a witneſſe of the Popes ſupremacie. But upon ſuch falſe, and forged teſtimonies, it is, that the Popes ſupremacie, is chiefely founded. Howbeit I hope by this time, you perceive, that howſoever, the Pope, and Poperie, have beene heretofore long maskers in the world, and gone diſguiſed, yet at laſt they have beene diſcovered, and made knowne to bee ſuch, as they bee indeede: and, that it had beene much better for you, to have beene mute, or mum, then by this your provocation, to have occaſioned, the ſhame, and ignominie of the Pope, and Popiſh Church, in the point, of forgerie to be thus diſplayed, and layd open, as alſo you may here ſee, that I have no way wronged <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> or wreſted him to a wrong conſtruction, (as you calumniate,) when I alledged him, to prove the Kings authoritie aſwell in matters Eccleſiaſticall, and concerning Religion, as in matters Civill, and Temporall. Which that you, and everie man elſe, may yet the better, and the more fully perceive, I have here thought it good to ſet downe, his owne verie wordes in <hi>Latine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. contra Creſcon. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> and they be theſe: <hi>In hoc enim Reges ſicut eis divinitus praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Deo ſerviunt, in quantum Reges ſunt, ſi, in ſuo regno, bona iubeant, mala, prohibeant, non ſolum quae pertinent ad humanam ſocietatem, verumetiam, quae ad divinam religionem. For in this,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>doe Kings, as is commaunded them from God, ſerve as they be Kings, if in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2756:19"/> their kingdomes, they commaund good things, and forbid euill things, not onely thoſe things, which belong to humane ſocietie, but thoſe things alſo, which belong to Gods Religion.</hi> Can any thing be more plainely, or more directly ſpoken for proofe of this point?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Here then you may withall perceive, the truth of that diſtinction, which I uſed in my <hi>Reply (cap.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 4.) For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you, in your Anſwer, amplifying the <hi>Sacerdotall,</hi> or <hi>ſpirituall power,</hi> had ſaid that how much the foule in perfection exceeds the bodie: the eternall bliſſe, the temporall felicitie: the divine lawes, the humane lawes: By ſo much did the ſpirituall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie exceede the temporall: Thereunto I replyed, and ſayed, that whileſt you thus ſpake, you ſhould have remembred, and obſerved, wherein, and in what reſpects it was, that this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the one above the other, did conſiſt. For as it is true, that in reſpect of converting ſoules, and fitting them for Gods kingdome, by preaching of Gods word, adminiſtring of the Sacraments, and exerciſe of the <hi>Eccleſiasticall diſcipline,</hi> the ſpirituall function, and authoritie is to bee preferred before the <hi>Regall,</hi> or <hi>Temporall:</hi> So no leſſe true is it, that in reſpect of the temporall power of the ſword, externally to commaund, compell, and to puniſh offenders, in cauſes both Eccleſiaſticall, and Civill, the Regall, and temporall office, and authoritie, is to bee preferred before the <hi>Epiſcopall,</hi> or <hi>Sacerdotall.</hi> This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, becauſe it killeth, and ſtriketh dead your cauſe, you cannot endure, and therefore doe you, in your <hi>Reioynder</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme againſt it, and <hi>call it a diſtinction never heard of before, and that it was lately hatched in the Vniverſitie of Mollinmighan,</hi> (as you ſcoffingly ſpeake,) <hi>in the Colledge there, of your owne diviſing and nomination, and whereof you are the father, and the founder.</hi> But (to let this paſſe, as an idle fiction of a fantaſticall braine,) why will you not acknowledge the truth of this diſtinction, which is ſo cleare, plaine, and evident in it ſelfe? The firſt part of it, you neyther doe, nor can denie, namely, that in reſpect of converting ſoules,<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Mat hom. <hi>83.</hi> Ad popul antioch. homil. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> and fitting them for Gods kingdome, by preaching of Gods word, adminiſtring of the Sacraments, and exerciſe of the Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, the ſpirituall office and authoritie is to bee preferred before the <hi>Regall,</hi> or <hi>Temporall.</hi> For this is, verie apparant, even by <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> himſelfe, who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2756:19"/> ſpeaketh to Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters on this wiſe. <hi>No ſmall ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> (ſaith hee,) <hi>hangeth over your heads, if you doe ſuffer any hainous offender, to be partaker of the Lords Table: his bloud ſhall be required at your hands, whether hee be a Captaine, Lieutenant, or a crowned King, forbid him: in theſe caſes, thy power is greater then his.</hi> Againe hee ſaith. <hi>Si vis videre diſcrimen, quantum abſit Rex à Sacerdote, expende modum poteſtatis, vtrique traditae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. de verb. Eſa. vidi Dom. hom. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If you will ſee the difference how great it is, betweene the King, and the Prieſt, weigh the meaſure of the power, or authoritie, graunted unto them both.</hi> And there ſhewing the power, and authoritie, which God hath committed to the Prieſt, he ſaith: <hi>Eo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Deus, ipſum regale caput ſacerdotis manibus ſubiecit:</hi> and in that reſpect, (ſaith hee,) <hi>hath God ſubiected the head of the King, to the hand of the Priest.</hi> So that it is onely in reſpect of their Miniſterie, power, and authoritie, graunted them from God, &amp; not in all reſpects, nor to all intents, and purpoſes, that this their excellencie and preheminencie conſiſteth. Yea, he further ſheweth, that their power and offices, bee diſtinct, and limitted, and that the one may not intrude into the office, and bounds of the other. For, when King <hi>Vzziah,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Ozias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.16.17 18.</note> entred into the Temple to burne incenſe, which pertayned to the Prieſts of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and not to the King: <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> reproving and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning this, ſaith thus unto the King:<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. de verbis Eſaiae vidi Dom. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mane intra tuos termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos; alij ſunt termini Regni, alij termini ſacerdotis: Keepe you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your owne bounds: For, the limits or bounds of the Regall calling, be one: and the limits or bounds of the Sacerdotall calling be another,</hi> And againe hee ſaith, that, <hi>Res eſt mala, non manere intra fines, nobis à Deo praeſcriptos. It is an ill thing, not to abide within the limits or bounds preſcribed unto us of God.</hi> Hee againe thus diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth their offices: <hi>Regi, corpora commiſſa ſunt: ſacerdoti, animae: Rex maculas corporum remittit, Sacerdos autem maculas peccatorum: Ille cogit, hic exhortatur: Ille neceſsitate, hic conſilio: Ille habet ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſenſibilia, hic arma ſpiritualia. Ille bellum gerit cum barbaris, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi belium est adverſus Daemones. To the King,</hi> (ſaith he,<note place="margin">Homil. <hi>5.</hi> Idem ibidem. hom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>are bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies committed; to the Prieſt, ſoules: the King remitteth the ſpots of the bodies, the Prieſt the ſpots of ſinnes. The King compelleth, the Prieſt exhorteth, the one with neceſsitie, or constraint, the other with advice, or counſaile: The King hath ſenſible weapons, the Prieſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2756:20"/> hath ſpirituall weapons: The King maketh warre with the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, and the Prieſt hath warres againſt the Divels</hi> Againe hee ſaith: <hi>Regi, ea quae hic ſunt, commiſſa ſunt: mihi caeleſtia: mihi quum dico, ſacerdotem intelligo. To the King are thoſe things committed, that bee here: To mee, are things heavenly committed: And when I ſay to mee, I meane (ſaith hee) the Prieſt.</hi> So that, although hee there affirmeth the <hi>Sacerdotall power,</hi> or office, to bee more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent or greater, then the <hi>Regall</hi> yet withall hee ſheweth you wherein, and in what reſpects it is, namely, (as I ſaid before,) in reſpect of thoſe things, which properly belong to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, miniſterie, and function of a Prieſt, or Biſhop: of which ſort, is preaching of Gods word, adminiſtring of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and binding and looſing of ſinners, by <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>Abſolution,</hi> as the caſe requireth: But hee may not by vertue of that his Eccleſiaſticall and Prieſtly office, uſe any externall, civill, coactive power or compulſion, which you ſee, even by the evident teſtimonie of the ſame <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, rightly and properly belongeth to the King, and not to the Prieſt. Now then here you may perceive withall the other part of my diſtinction to be likewiſe undoubtedly true, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That in reſpect of the Temporall power of the ſword, thereby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally to commaund, compell and to puniſh offendors, in cauſes both Eccleſiaſticall, and Civill, the Regall, and temporall office, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, is to bee preferred before the Epiſcopall, or Sacerdotall.</hi> For it is cleare that God hath committed this Civill and Temporall ſword, onely to Kings and Princes, and ſuch like terreſtriall Potentates, and not to Biſhops or Prieſts: For ſo alſo doth <hi>S. Paul</hi> himſelfe directly ſhew. And who is there but hee knoweth that it properly appertayneth to the power, &amp; office of this civill and temporall ſword, to commaund, compell, and to puniſh offendors, civilly and in a temporall manner? For the ſame Apoſtle ſaith of everie of theſe higher powers, that beare this temporall Sword, that hee beareth it not in vaine. Yea hee ſaith, that hee is the Miniſter of God, a revenger unto wrath to him that doth evill. Here is no exception of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or of any cauſe, but hee that offendeth, or doth evill, bee hee a lay-man, or a cleargie-man, or be he an offendor in a cauſe Civill, or cauſe Eccleſiaſticall, hee appeareth to bee ſubject to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2756:20"/> this ſword, and authoritie of theſe <hi>higher powers.</hi> For, ſeeing the expreſſe wordes of the Text, be,<note place="margin">Bernard. ad Senonen. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obiepiſc epiſt. <hi>42.</hi> Chryſoſt. in Rom. hom. <hi>23</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let everie ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers: Who,</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Bernard,) hath excepted you,</hi> (ſpeaking to an Archbiſhop,) <hi>from this generalitie. Hee that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in an exception,</hi> (ſaith hee,) <hi>uſeth but a deluſion.</hi> And you may remember, that even <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> alſo himſelfe, as hee ſubjecteth Kings to Biſhops, Prieſts, and Paſtors, in reſpect of their power and commiſsion graunted them from God: So on the other ſide, in reſpect of the <hi>Regall ſword, power, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> given and graunted likewiſe from God, to Kings and Princes, he declareth verie fully that Biſhops, Prieſts, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and all Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters whatſoever, aſwell, as lay people, are to be ſubject to them. But this point concerning the ſubjection of all Biſhops, Prieſts, and Paſtors, and even of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelfe, aſwell, as of others, unto Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, and Princes, as alſo in cauſes even Eccleſiaſticall, aſwell, as Civill, and temporall, is ſo cleerely, plainely, and plentifully proved, both in my firſt, and ſecond Bookes, and in this alſo, (all your anſwers, evaſions, quirkes, and quiddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, being therein, utterly fruſtrated, confuted, and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,) as that it is to mee a matter of wounder, that you ſhould not ſee, and ſo acknowledge the truth of it. But it ſeemeth you cannot ſee the wood for trees, which I am ſorrie for.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Howbeit to make this point, yet the more evident, <hi>(viz,)</hi> the ſubjection of Prieſts, and Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters, unto the King: and therewithall, the Kings ſupremacie, or ſupreame commaund, over them, even in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, I alledged in my <hi>Reply, cap.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 5. the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded not onely the <hi>Levites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.25.26.</note> and that in a matter Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, and concerning their verie office, but hee commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo even <hi>Aaron,</hi> the high Prieſt, in a matter likewiſe Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, and concerning his verie office,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.46.47.</note> ſaying thus unto him: <hi>Take the cenſer, and put fire therein of the Altar, and put therein incenſe, and goe quickely unto the congregation, and make an attonement for them, for there is wrath gone out from the Lorde, the plague is begun, then Aaron tooke, as Moſes had commaunded him, &amp;c.</hi> Here you ſay, I abuſe my <hi>Reader,</hi> by falſely citing this text: for the right wordes, (ſay you,) are theſe: <hi>Moſes ſaid to Aaron,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2756:21"/> take the Cenſer, and drawing fire from the Altar, put incenſe upon it, going quickely to the people, to pray for them.</hi> To pray, (ſay you,) and to make attonement, doe differ, and be not all one: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, indeede, not I, but, you are the man that abuſe your Reader, by falſely citing the wordes of this Text: For you, therein follow the wordes, of your vulgar Latin tranſlation, which is untrue, and unſound, and I follow our Engliſh tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, which is according to the Originall, in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and therefore true: which you alſo, if you were a good <hi>Hebrician,</hi> would know, and perceive, even in this verie particular. But whether wee take your tranſlation, of <hi>Praying</hi> for the people, or our tranſlation, of <hi>Attonement-making,</hi> it commeth all to one paſſe, as touching that purpoſe for which I cited it, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to prove, that <hi>Moſes</hi> commaunded <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Prieſt, in a matter Eccleſiaſticall, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his verie office. For your ſelfe do ſay, that, this <hi>praying</hi> for the people, was a religious act, to bee wrought by <hi>Aaron,</hi> as being intermediate betweene the people, &amp; God, to reconcile, or gaine unto them the favours of heaven. And, on the other ſide we ſay, <hi>that to burne incenſe, to mak attonement for the people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.18.</note> is likwiſe expreſſely, a thing properly pertayning to the Prieſts office. So that as touching that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for which I cited that text, it maketh (as I ſaid before) no difference. But then you go further, &amp; ſeem to ſpeake, as if <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> had not there commanded <hi>Aaron.</hi> But when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake to <hi>Aaron</hi> in this ſort: <hi>Accipe thuribulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Take the cenſer.</hi> Be not theſe wordes of commaunding, eſpecially in this caſe, and at this time, being alſo ſpoken by a Superior, namely by him, that was as the Scripture calleth him, a king in the common-weale of Iſrael:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.25 26.27.</note> Yea bee they not wordes, of as full, and cleere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, as when hee ſpake in like ſort, to the <hi>Levites,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Take the booke of this law, and put yee it in the ſide of the Arke of the Covenant of the Lord our God, &amp;c.</hi> The Text it ſelfe ſheweth that theſe were wordes of commaunding, in <hi>Moſes:</hi> And ſo witneſſeth alſo your owne tranſlation, that herein, <hi>Moſes prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit Levitis, Moſes commaunded the Levites.</hi> Yea, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> aſwell as his ſucceſſor <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> commaunded not onely the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> but the Prieſts alſo, and all the congregation, and people of Iſrael, appeareth by that anſwer, and acclamation, they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2756:21"/> gave to the ſame <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> ſaying thus unto him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.16.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>All that thou haſt commaunded us, wee will doe, and whetherſoever thou ſendeſt us, wee will goe. As wee have obeyed Moſes in all things, ſo will we obey thee: onely the Lord thy God be with thee as bee was with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: whoſoever ſhall rebell againſt thy commaundement, and will not obey thy wordes, in all that thou commaundest him, let him bee put to death.</hi> But then, when you cannot gaineſay, but that <hi>Moſes</hi> commaunded <hi>Aaron,</hi> and that in matters Eccleſiaſticall and concerning his very office: you come to your laſt refuge, and doe ſay, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was the high Prieſt, and ſo, as an high Prieſt commaunded <hi>Aaron.</hi> But firſt how doe you prove this, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was an high Prieſt? And yet if you could prove it, what would you, or could you gaine from thence? for your ſelfe doe ſay, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was as well a king, as a Prieſt: &amp; therefore why might hee not commaund him, as hee was a king, rather then otherwiſe? for did he, in his time, commaund the Prieſts. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, &amp; the whole People of Iſrael, otherwiſe, or in any other ſort or ſence, then <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> his ſucceſſor did, who was no Prieſt? how be it, if <hi>Moſes</hi> had been both a Prieſt and a King, would not the holy Scripture ſomewhere, haue teſtified, and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo much, aſwell as it doth, in the like caſe, of <hi>Melchiſedech. Gen.</hi> 14.18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.1? For as touching thoſe Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which you bring to prove <hi>Moſes</hi> to be a Prieſt, it ſhall by and by appeare, that they prove it not. Againe if <hi>Moſes</hi> were the high Prieſt, what will you make <hi>Aaron</hi> to be? for it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and confeſſed of all ſides, that <hi>Aaron</hi> was the high Prieſt: and if <hi>Moſes,</hi> were alſo another high Prieſt, at the ſame time:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.5.</note> then, beſide that, there ſhould be two high Prieſts together at one time, how could the one commaund the other, they being both of equall authority? Or can he be rightly, and truely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Summus Sacerdos,</hi> that hath a Superior Prieſt over him, to commaund him? It is cleere, that the Scripture doth expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifie of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he was a King, and therefore of that there can be no doubt: but that he was alſo a Prieſt, or an high Prieſt, (as you ſuppoſe) it doth not affirme, no not in that Place, where the purpoſe of the holy Ghoſt was to ſhew, what Offices he bare, during all his life time, and what maner of man he was amongſt the Iſraelites, ſo long, as he had been amongſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2756:22"/> them, vntill that time, that he was to die, and to take his laſt farewell of them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.5. <hi>&amp; Deut.</hi> 34.10.</note> for there it onely appeareth, that he was a King and a Prophet, but not a Prieſt. Had he bene alſo a Prieſt, no doubt, it would not haue bene there omitted, but ſpecified likewiſe, aſwell as his other two Offices. Yea reade through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> the hiſtorie concerning <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; you will ſtill finde, that he was a ſupreame civill Magiſtrate, a ſupreme Commaunder,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.13 14.15.16.17.18.19.20.21.22.23.24.25.26.</note> and ſupreame Iudge in Iſraell. For it is, ſaide, that, <hi>When Moſes ſate to iudge the people, the People ſtood about Moſes, from morning vnto even: And when Iethro Moſes Father in Law, ſaw all that he did to the People, he ſaid, what is this, thou doeſt to the People? Why ſitteſt thou thy ſelfe alone, and all the People ſtand about thee from morning vnto even?</hi> And becauſe this was too toylſome &amp; troubleſome a buſineſſe for him alone to doe, he adviſed him to appoint ſome others to help him, &amp; to beare the Burthen with him, in hearing &amp; judging of cauſes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Moſes</hi> choſe able men, out of all Iſrael, <hi>and made them heads over the People, Rulers over thouſands, Rulers over hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreths, Rulers over fifties, and Rulers over tens. And theſe iudged the people, at all ſeaſons: the hard Cauſes, they brought to Moſes, but every ſmall matter, they iudged themſelves.</hi> When, againe, <hi>Moſes</hi> heard the murmuring, and ſaw the weeping of the People of Iſrael, throughout their families, he was much grieved, and ſpeake thus to the Lord:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.10.11.12.13.14.15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Wherefore haſt thou afflicted thy ſervant, and why have not I found favor in thy ſight, ſeeing thou haſt put the charge of all this People vpon me? &amp;c.</hi> By all which, you ſee that <hi>Moſes</hi> was, as a King, Prince, or ſupreame commaunder over all Iſrael, and conſequently, as a King, commaunded <hi>Aaron</hi> and the reſt of the Prieſts, aſwell, as he commaunded the Levites, or any of the reſt of the People. Moreover, if <hi>Moſes</hi> had bene the high Prieſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.5.</note> he might haue offered Sacrifice himſelfe, and needed not to haue ſent others, (as he did) to ſacrifice: neither needed he to haue commaunded,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.46.47.</note> or required <hi>Aaron,</hi> to burne incenſe, (as he did) to make an Attonement, for the People, for himſelfe might haue done it. But whatſoever Bellarmine, or other Papiſts, hould in this caſe, you, for your part, doe not hould them, to be both high Prieſts together, at one and the ſelfe ſame time, but in ſucceſſion one after another: accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2756:22"/> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be the high Prieſt, firſt, and then <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 5 4.</note> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Howbeit, the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>No man taketh this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to himſelfe, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron.</hi> If then <hi>Moſes</hi> were called of God, to this honor of high Prieſthood, let the like warrant be ſhewed from God, for the Authorizing of him therevnto, that is to be ſhewed for <hi>Aaron.</hi> But this you cannot ſhew. Beſides, if <hi>Moſes</hi> were the high Prieſt firſt, and <hi>Aaron</hi> afterward: why doth that Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the Patterne, or Preſident in that Caſe, not <hi>Moſes,</hi> but <hi>Aaron?</hi> For if <hi>Moſes</hi> had bene the firſt high Prieſt, no doubt he would haue ſaid, <hi>That no man taketh this honor vnto himſelfe, but he that is called of God, as was Moſes:</hi> But he ſaith not ſo, but he ſpeaketh in this ſort. <hi>(viz) No man taketh this honor to himſelfe, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron:</hi> As if <hi>Revera,</hi> not <hi>Moſes</hi> at all, but <hi>Aaron</hi> onelie were the firſt high Prieſt. And ſo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, S. Chriſoſtome directly affirmeth,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. de verbis Iſaiae vidi Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homil. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> for ſpeaking of <hi>Aaron</hi> he ſaith expreſſely, that <hi>Is primus fuit Pontifex, He was the firſt high Priest.</hi> Againe if <hi>Moſes</hi> were the high Prieſt, ſo conſtituted of God, how came he afterward, to looſe that honor, or to be deprived of it, and another, namely <hi>Aaron,</hi> to be put in his Place, in his life time, he committing no fault nor any fault de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be in him, for which he ſhould be deprived of that his Prieſthood? But, laſtly, what cauſe, or neede is there, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Moſes</hi> to be, (as you fancy him) an high Prieſt, extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily elected, and appointed, when there was to be ſeene at the ſame time, an <hi>High Prieſt</hi> after the ordinary maner, in <hi>Eſſe,</hi> and allowed of God, namely the ſame <hi>Aaron?</hi> For in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 22. 23. I haue proved, that the Prieſthood before the law given, did ordinarily belong to the firſt borne: and of theſe two Brothers, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> I haue alſo there proved, that not <hi>Moſes,</hi> but <hi>Aaron,</hi> was the Elder, and conſequently, that by right of Primogeniture, <hi>Aaron</hi> was the Prieſt, and not <hi>Moſes.</hi> Yea I haue there further proved, that the Prieſthood thus being in <hi>Aaron,</hi> was ſo farre from being removed, or taken from him that contrariwiſe, it was continued in him, and afterward confirmed vnto him, by God himſelfe, and to his ſeede, after him. But yet you would prove <hi>Moſes</hi> to be a Prieſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.12 13.14.12.</note> becauſe he did conſecrate, and annoynte <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his ſonnes, to the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hood.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2756:23"/> But to this I have anſwered before in my <hi>Reply</hi> pag. 25. 26. ſhewing, that this proveth not <hi>Moſes</hi> to be a Prieſt, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called: for he did this by Gods owne ſpeciall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which he might not diſobey or refuſe but ſtood bound to obey and performe, although he were a Civill Magiſtrate, King, Prince, Prophet, or what office &amp; calling ſoever hee had. You cite alſo <hi>Deut,</hi> 18.18. where God ſaith thus to <hi>Moſes: I will raiſe them up a Prophet, amongſt their brethren, like unto thee, &amp;c.</hi> This prooveth, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Prophet, and that Chriſt, (of whom, theſe wordes are a Prophecie,) was likewiſe a Prophet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 7.37. but they prove not <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore to be a Prieſt, becauſe he was a Prophet. But the chiefe text you rely upon, is that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. where it is ſaid: <hi>Moſes and Aaron amongſt the Prieſts, &amp; Samuel amongſt them that call upon his name: theſe called upon the Lord, and he heard them.</hi> Howbeit, to this alſo I have anſwered before in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 23.24. Firſt, that the being of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron,</hi> with, or among the Prieſts, is no proofe, that therefore they were Prieſts: It is true, that <hi>Aaron</hi> was a Prieſt, but that is proved by other cleere places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not neceſſarily deduced out of this: becauſe a man may be among Prieſts, &amp; yet be no Prieſt. Secondly, I ſhewed, that the Hebrew word there uſed, is, <hi>Cohanim,</hi> which is a word of an ambiguous ſignification, ſignifying, aſwell Princes, as Prieſts:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.18</note> As for example, <hi>The ſonnes of King David,</hi> are ſaid to bee, <hi>Cohanim,</hi> that is, <hi>Princes, or great Rulers:</hi> &amp; ſo it is explay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam,</hi> 20.26.</note> and declared in 1, <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.17. And ſo it is likewiſe ſaid, of <hi>Ira</hi> the <hi>Iairite,</hi> that hee was <hi>Cohen le David,</hi> that is, a <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>chiefe Ruler</hi> about <hi>David.</hi> For, to conſter theſe, to be Prieſts, in the proper and uſuall ſignification of the word, they not being of the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Levi,</hi> were verie abſurd. And to theſe thus formerly alledged in my <hi>Reply,</hi> you have anſwered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in your <hi>Rejoynder.</hi> Yea, <hi>S. Ierome</hi> himſelfe, in his owne obſervation, ſheweth, that the Hebrew word, though he tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it <hi>Sacerdotes,</hi> in the one caſe and <hi>Sacerdos</hi> in the other caſe, yet ſignifieth, as I before affirmed. For, ſaith he, <hi>Ira Iairites erat ſacerdos David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. tradit Hebr. in libros Regum to. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>id eſt Magiſter, ſicut alibi ſcriptum eſt: Filij autem David, erant ſacerdotes, idest Magistri fratrum ſuorum.</hi> But becauſe you alſo object <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> as the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> likewiſe did object
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2756:23"/> both <hi>S. Ierome,</hi> and <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> in this caſe, (writing upon this <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 99.) to prove <hi>Moſes</hi> to bee a Prieſt: I had rather you ſhould take your Anſwer thereunto, from the wordes of that reverend and learned Biſhop <hi>Doctor Bilſon,</hi> then from me: who, anſwereth the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and conſequently you, in this ſort.<note place="margin">In his Booke called, the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian rebellion part. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>102.103.</hi> Hier. in Pſal. <hi>98.</hi> Aug. in Pſal. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>All that S. Ierome ſaith, is this, that Moſes had the rule of the Law, and Aaron of the Prieſthood: and that eyther of them did foreſhew the comming of Chriſt with a Priestly kinde of Proclamation: Moſes, with the ſound of the Law: and Aaron, with the Bels of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Where, <hi>S. Hierome</hi> calleth the Propheticall function of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to teach the people, the lawes of God, a Prieſtly kinde of Proclamation &amp; foreſhewing, that the Son of God, ſhould come in the fleſh, to teach us the will of his Father. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> uſeth the word, in the like ſence, for that ſacred ſervice, which <hi>Moſes</hi> yeelded to God, in reporting his lawes and precepts to the people. And therefore in the ſame place, he ſaith of <hi>Samuel</hi> alſo, that hee was made high Prieſt, which is expreſſely againſt the Scriptures, if you take the Prieſt for him that was annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to offer ſacrifice unto God. For <hi>Samuel</hi> was but a <hi>Levite,</hi> and no Prieſt, much leſſe an high Prieſt. The ſons of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.</note> are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned in the Scripture it ſelfe, among the <hi>Levites,</hi> apart from the Prieſts office, and linage: And, the high Prieſthood, was, long before, given to <hi>Phinees,</hi> and his houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 25.13 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.</note> by covenant from Gods owne mouth, and in the dayes of <hi>Samuel,</hi> was held by <hi>Abiah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ahitub,</hi> who was directly of the diſcent of <hi>Phinees. S. Augustine</hi> elſewhere debating this queſtion of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> reſolveth in doubtfull manner: <hi>Moſes and Aaron, were both high Prieſts, or rather Moſes the chiefe, and Aaron under him: or elſe Aaron chiefe for the Pontificall attire, and Moſes for a more excellent Miniſterie.</hi> And in that ſence, <hi>Moſes</hi> may be called a Prieſt, if you meane as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> doth, an interpreter of Gods will to <hi>Aaron,</hi> &amp; others, which is the right vocation of all Prophets, that were no Prieſts, &amp; common to them all, ſave that by a more excellent prerogative then any other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Olde Teſtament,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.</note> had God ſpake to <hi>Moſes</hi> mouth to mouth, and face to face. as a man ſpeaketh to his friend. But this doth not hinder his civill power which was to bee chiefe Iudge, and ſoveraigne executor of Iuſtice amongſt them, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2756:24"/> by vertue thereof to put them to death, that were offenders againſt the Law of God. And in his ſtead, ſucceeded, not <hi>Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> nor <hi>Phinees</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> the Captaines, and leaders of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So farre hee. Thus then you ſee, in what ſence it is, that both <hi>S. Ierome,</hi> and <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> did, or might call <hi>Moſes</hi> a Prieſt, and yet not bee ſuch a Prieſt ſtrictly, and properly taken, as you fancie him: Yea, you ſee, that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> likewiſe affirmeth <hi>Samuel</hi> to be a Prieſt, who nevertheleſſe <hi>revera,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellarmin. de verb. Dei lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and properly, was not a Prieſt, as before is ſhewed: And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo himſelfe confeſſeth ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much of <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſaying expreſſely. <hi>Samulem non fuiſſe ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſed Iudicem tantum: Non enim deſcendit ex familia Aaron, ſed Core conſobrini ejus</hi> 1. <hi>Paralip.</hi> 6. <hi>That Samuel was not a Priest, but onely a Iudge: for he deſcended not of the family of Aaron, but of Core.</hi> And he ſaith further, that <hi>S. Hierome</hi> likewiſe, (<hi>libr.</hi> 1. <hi>in Iovinianum,) oſtendit Samuelem non fuiſſe Sacerdotem, ſhewed that Samuel was not a Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe two <hi>Chapters of Exodus,</hi> 28. and 29. cited by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> whereby he will prove <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be truely, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, a Prieſt. If you reade thoſe Chapters, you ſhall finde no ſuch matter, but rather the contrary, namely, that not <hi>Moſes,</hi> but <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 28 1.2, 3.4.</note> were the Prieſts. For God ſaith there, to <hi>Moſes: Take Aaron thy Brother and his Sonnes with him, from amongſt the children of Iſrael, that he may minister unto me in the Prieſts Office, even Aaron, Nadab, and Abibu, Eleazar, and Ithamar, Aarons ſonnes.</hi> It is true, that, there, you may reade that <hi>Moſes</hi> made holy <hi>Garments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.1.2.3.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and offered certaine <hi>Sacrifices.</hi> But obſerve withall, that all this was done by Gods owne expreſſe and ſpeciall commaundement, and to no other end, but this, <hi>viz,</hi> for the conſeruating of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>his Sonnes,</hi> to the <hi>Prieſthood.</hi> So that by thoſe two Chapters, it further appeareth, that not <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> but <hi>Aaron</hi> onely and <hi>his Sonnes,</hi> were the Prieſts: But as the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his booke before named part. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>103. 104.</hi>
               </note> in time paſt, would have proved <hi>Samuel,</hi> to be a Prieſt, becauſe it is ſaid, that he Sacrificed: ſo you ſay the ſame of King <hi>Saul,</hi> that he alſo ſacrificed, and thereby would likewiſe prove him to be a prieſt. Howbeit the former revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Biſhop, <hi>D. Bilſon,</hi> doth againe ſhew both them and you, how much you deceave your ſelves, by ſuch phrazes, and maner of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2756:24"/> ſpeeches: and that when they are rightly vnderſtood, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre no ſuch concluſion, as you, and they would deduce out of them. My collection, (ſaith he,) is grounded upon the law of God. <hi>Samuel</hi> was none of the Sonnes of <hi>Aaron, Ergo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Samuel was no Prieſt.</hi> It is true, that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He tooke a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king lambe and offered it for a burnt offering unto the Lord. So Iephta</hi> ſaid:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>That thing which first cometh out of the Dores of my houſe to me, I will offer it for a burnt offering:</hi> And yet Iephtah was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſt nor Levite. So the Angell ſaid to <hi>Manoah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 13.</note> If thou wilt make a burnt offering, offer it unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> And yet <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noah</hi> was of the tribe of <hi>Dan.</hi> Of <hi>David,</hi> that was no Prieſt, the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Then David offered burnt offerings and peace offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings before the Lord.</hi> And againe, <hi>David built there an Altar unto the Lord, and offered burnt offerings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>and peace-offerings and the Lord was appeaſed towards the Land.</hi> And likewiſe <hi>of Salomon: The King went to Gibeon to ſacrifice there:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>a thouſand burnt offerings did Salomon offer upon the Altar. Thriſe a yeare did Salomon offer burnt offerings, and peace offerings, upon the Altar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>which he built to the Lord: and he burnt incenſe upon the Altar, that was before the Lord.</hi> Nothing is oftner in the Scriptures, then theſe kinde of ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: By the which, no more is meant, but that either, they brought theſe things, to be offered, or elſe they cauſed the Prieſts, to offer them: For in their owne Perſones, they could not ſacrifice them, becauſe they were no Prieſts. In that ſence, the Scripture ſaith of <hi>Saul, That he offered burnt offerings at Gilgal before Samuel came:</hi> not that <hi>Saul</hi> offered it with his owne hands,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.</note> as you before did fondly imagine and ſaid, <hi>Hee was depoſed for aſpiring to the ſpirituall function:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 3.18.</note> But he commaunded the Prieſt to doe it, who was then preſent in the hoſt, with the Arke of God, as the next chapter doth witneſſe, in two ſpeciall Places. And as for the reproofe that <hi>Samuel gave to King Saul,</hi> it was (ſaith he,) for diſtruſting and diſobeying God. For when God firſt advanced <hi>Saul</hi> to the Kingdome, he charged him by the Mouth of <hi>Samuel, to goe to Gilgal, and there to ſtay ſeaven Dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>(before he ventured to doe any Sacrifice,) till the Prophet were ſent to ſhew him what he ſhould doe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam</hi> 13.</note> But ſeeing his enemies gathered to fight againſt him, on the one ſide, and his people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inking from him on the other ſide, becauſe <hi>Samuel</hi> came not he began
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2756:25"/> to ſuſpect that <hi>Samuel</hi> had beguiled him, and therefore upon his owne head, againſt the commandement of God, willed the Prieſt, to goe foreward with his Sacrifices, and to conſult God, what he ſhould doe. This ſecret diſtruct, and preſumption, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the charge which God had given him, was the thing, that God tooke in ſo evill part: And ſince he would not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte himſelfe to be ruled by God, and expect his leaſure, God reiected him, as unfitte to governe the People. Neither did <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> challenge him, for invading the Prieſts Office, but for not ſtaying the time, that God prefixed him, before the Prophet ſhould come. So farre he, whom I thus recite the more at large, for your better ſatisfaction, in this Point. But yet moreover, that worthy,<note place="margin">In his Booke of iuriſdiction Regall, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall, Papall, pag. <hi>31. 32. 33.</hi> &amp;c.</note> learned, and reverend Biſhop alſo, <hi>D. Carleton,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other arguments which he bringeth to prove <hi>Moſes</hi> to be a Ciuill Magiſtrate, and a Prince, but not a Prieſt, alledgeth that Text of Exodus, 4.16. where <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſaid to be, as a God to <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> as a Mouth to <hi>Moſes.</hi> The word there uſed, is <hi>Elohim,</hi> and the ſame, that is alſo uſed in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. and is never applyed throughout the whole Scriptures, when it is given to men, but to ſuch as were Kings, Princes, Iudges, and other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Magiſtrate: and at no time to Prieſts, vnles they were them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the chiefe Magiſtrates, or received Authority from the Chiefe Magiſtrate. Give you an inſtance in the holy Scripture, to the Contrary, if you can, or elſe confeſſe the truth of it. And here you may alſo obſerve one reaſon among the reſt, which Chriſt himſelfe giveth, why they be called Gods, in that <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 82.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6.</note> For in that Pſalme, it is, that theſe words are written, <hi>I have ſaid, ye are Gods:</hi> which be the words, that Chriſt citeth, in the Goſpell of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.34.35.</note> and ſaith thereupon thus: <hi>If hee called them Gods, unto whom the word of God was given, &amp;c.</hi> So that this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to be one reaſon, why Kings, Princes, and Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18 19 <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.8. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11.12.</note> be called Gods, namely, becauſe they have the word of God, given, or committed to them, although not to preach it, (as Biſhops, Paſtors, and Doctors doe,) yet by way of ſpeciall commiſſion to keepe it, to eſtabliſh it by Authority, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund obedience to it, to puniſh the Violaters of it, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage countenance, protect, and defend the Profeſſors, and Practiſers of it. For it is certaine, that all that Pſalme, whence
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2756:25"/> Chriſt tooke thoſe words, is wholy, and entirely underſtood, of Kings, Princes, and ſuch like Civill Magiſtrates, &amp; not of Prieſts, Biſhops, or other Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters, as any man may perceave, that will reade that Pſalme. Seeing then, this word, <hi>Elohim,</hi> is given to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that comparatively, and in reſpect of <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt, it muſt be graunted, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Civil Magiſtrate, and as a King, or Prince, in reſpect of him, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, But neither Prieſt, nor high Prieſt, as you ſurmiſe. And as for that Text before mentioned of Pſalm. 99. verſ. 6. how much ſoever you and others, ſtand vpon it, yet give me leave here once more to tell you, that being well conſidered, you may, in your owne iudgment, eaſily perceave, that you can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force nothing thereout, to prove <hi>Moſes</hi> to be a Prieſt, properly ſo called, although <hi>Aaron</hi> was: for, the purpoſe, and intention, of thoſe words, is no more but this, to ſhew, that not onely <hi>Moſes</hi> a Civill Magiſtrate, but <hi>Aaron</hi> alſo a Chiefe Prieſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the other Prieſts, and <hi>Samuel</hi> likewiſe a Prophet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, that called upon the name of the Lord, were all heard of him, when they prayed. Now, becauſe all thoſe when they prayed &amp; called vpon the name of the Lord, were heard, and obtained their requeſts: is that any argument, that therefore they were all Prieſts properly ſo called? No man, I thinke, will be ſo abſurd, as to make ſuch an inference.</p>
            <p n="9">9. I therefore now come to <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> the Succeſſor of <hi>Moſes:</hi> he, (aſwell, as <hi>Moſes,</hi>) did as a Prince, or King, commaund the Prieſts, Levites and all Iſraell, and dealt in matters alſo Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall aſwell as Temporall, as I have ſhewed in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 6. hereunto you in your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> anſwere nothing, that is of any weight, or moment. Your beſt anſwer is, That what <hi>Ioſuah</hi> did in matters Eccleſiaſticall, he did it by the direction and adviſe of <hi>Eleaſar</hi> the Prieſt: which if it be graunted, maketh nothing to the Queſtion. For the Queſtion is not, by whoſe direction, or adviſe, but by whoſe Authority, thoſe things were done. It is not denyed, but that Prieſts might, (as was fitte they ſhould,) give their beſt direction and adviſe vnto their Kings and Princes: But this derogateth nothing from that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which Kings and Princes have and beare, within their owne dominions. Yea, how impertinent, weake, and feeble
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2756:26"/> this your anſwere is, you might have perceived before, by my <hi>Reply pag.</hi> 9. 10. if you had ſo pleaſed. Touching <hi>King Ioſuah,</hi> I ſaid in my <hi>Reply, pag.</hi> 6. 7. That he commaunded the high Prieſt, aſwell as the other Prieſts, and dealt alſo in matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, and concerning Gods ſervice, and religion: And amongſt other Text of Scripture, for proofe thereof, I alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that Text of 2, King 23.4. where it is accorded, that the King commaunded <hi>Hilkiah, the high Prieſt, and the Prieſts of the ſecond order, &amp;c.</hi> Hereunto you anſwere, that there is no ſuch matter in the Place by me cited: and that the force of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, conſiſteth in theſe coyned words of mine: The King commaunded <hi>Hilkiah,</hi> (whom you call <hi>Helcias:</hi>) which words not being in Scripture (ſay you,) I am a wilie Wittneſſe for ſtrengthning my cauſe, to produce ſo ſhamefull an untruth, and though I be a Iudge, yet you ſee no commiſſion I have to uſe falſhood. Theſe words be able to provoke a mans patience. But you muſt know, that bad words and a bould face, will doe you no good. Let others therefore iudge, whether you, or I, be the honeſter man in this Point. You ſay, there is no ſuch matter in the Place by me cited. Wherefore I deſire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but to turne to that place I cited, which is according to our Engliſh Bibles, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 23.4 and according to your Latine Bibles, 4. Reg. 23.4. and there ſhall he ſee, whether there be any ſuch matter, or no and, whether theſe words: <hi>The King commaunded Hilkiah,</hi> (whom you call <hi>Helcias,</hi>) be words coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by me, (as you ſhame not to ſpeake,) or whether they be in the Scripture it ſelfe, extant, and apparant. For, firſt, thoſe words, be in the <hi>Hebrew:</hi> Secondly, they be in our Engliſh Tranſlations: and thirdly, they be alſo even in your owne vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latine Tranſlation. For even in that your owne Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the words be theſe: <hi>Et praecepit Rex Helciae Pontifici, &amp; Sacerdotibus ſecundi ordinis, &amp;c. And the King commaunded Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias the high Priest, and the Prieſts of the ſecond order, &amp;c,</hi> Now then, is it not Impudency intollerable in you, to deny this. You ſhall therefore doe well, yet at laſt, to confeſſe, that this good, and godly King, <hi>Ioſias, commaunded Hilkiah,</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Helcias,</hi>) the high Prieſt, and the Prieſts of the ſecond Order: and that he alſo dealt in matters Eccleſiaſticall, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2756:26"/> religion, as I there ſayed, and have further declared, in the ſame place of my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 6.7. To that which I alledged concerning King <hi>Aſa,</hi> and King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 7. 8. who likewiſe had Authority, (as is there ſhewed,) over Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Eccleſiaſticall, and in cauſes alſo Eccleſiaſticall, you anſwer nothing in your <hi>Reioinder</hi> that deſerveth to be replyed unto. And concerning King <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> alſo, your anſwere is likewiſe very idle, and friuolous, and ſcarce worthy the mentioning. For whereas I alledged, amongſt other things,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19 8.9.10.11</note> That this King <hi>Iehoſaphat, did conſtitute, or ſet in Hieruſalem of the Levites, and of the Priests, and of the Chiefe of the families of Iſrael, for the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and cauſe of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> (which words were ſufficient, to prove my purpoſe there, namely, the Kings Authority over Prieſts, and Levites, and in cauſes alſo Eccleſiaſticall,) you to ſhew your great learning, and iudgment, in this point, doe taxe me for omitting, or not rehearſing of ſome ſubſequent words, in the which verſe of that Chapter, which when they be vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and rehearſed, doe indeede make more againſt you, then for you: for, the words be theſe. And behould, (ſaith the King,) <hi>Amoriah the high Prieſt, ſhall be the Chiefe over you, in all matters of the Lord: and Zebadiah, the ſonne of Iſhmaell, a Ruler of the houſe of Iudah ſhall be for all the Kings affaires.</hi> By which words, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, That King <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> did aſwell conſtitute, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointe <hi>Amariah</hi> the Prieſt, to be the Chiefe over that Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, Councell, or Synedrion, which he ſet at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for all matters of the Lord, as he did conſtitute, and appoint <hi>Zebadiah,</hi> to be the Chiefe amongſt them for all the Kings affaires. For the words of the Text, put no difference, but that he might, and did conſtitute, the one to be the Chiefe in the one caſe, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, as he did conſtitute the other, to be the Chiefe in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe. As for that reaſon you bring, for a difference, it is nothing worth: for, it is graunted, that the King did not, nor could by his Regall Authority, (without a ſpeciall commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, or warrant from God,) conſecrate, or make a Prieſt, neither is it there ſaid, That King <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> did conſecrate, or make <hi>Amariah,</hi> to be a Prieſt: But he being a Prieſt before, the King did there conſtitute and appoint him, (as lawfully he might,) to be the Preſident, or Chiefe in that <hi>Synedrion,</hi> or
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2756:27"/> Aſſembly, in all matters of the Lord: aſwell as he did, or might conſtitute <hi>Zebadiah,</hi> to be, therein, the Chiefe, or Preſident, for all the Kings affaires.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Now then to come to King <hi>Solomon,</hi> I proved him alſo in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 7. to have had authoritie over the Prieſts, and Levites, and to have dealt likewiſe, in matters Eccleſiaſticall, and concerning Religion: But to that Text of 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 8.14.15. by mee alledged, for proofe thereof, you anſwer not. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that Text of 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.27.35. where <hi>Solomon</hi> depoſed <hi>Abiathar,</hi> the high Prieſt, and put <hi>Sadocke</hi> in his place, you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and graunt it to be true, that hee did ſo: But this, ſay you, hee did, as being a Prophet, and not as a King. This anſwer of yours, I before confuted, and tooke a way in my <hi>Reply.</hi> pag. 20. 21. whether I againe referre you: becauſe that ſtandeth ſtill in full force againſt you, you having ſaid nothing againſt it, in your <hi>Reioynder.</hi> But now I adde further unto it, that it doth moreover appeare, even by the wordes of the Text it ſelfe. that <hi>Solomon</hi> did not doe this, as a Prophet, but as a King; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee therein did no more, but execute that, which a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or man of God, had before ſpoken from God, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the houſe of <hi>Ely:</hi> For ſo the words of the Text doe ſhew, that, <hi>Solomon caſt out Abiathar, from being Prieſt unto the Lord: that hee might fulfill the wordes of the Lord, which hee ſpake againſt the houſe of Ely in Shilo,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.27. and 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.27.28.29.30.31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where, the Prophet, or man of God, (as hee is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,) that uttered the Propheſie, and the King that executed the Propheſie muſt of neceſsitie bee diſtinguiſhed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as hee that received, and uttered the Propheſie is in the receiving, and uttering of it, to bee called, and ſuppoſed a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: So King <hi>Solomon,</hi> that was onely the executer, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former of that Propheſie, is in the execution, and performance of it, to be tearmed, and deemed a King, and not a Prophet. But whilſt I thus prove, the authoritie of Kings, over the high Prieſt, becauſe King <hi>Solomon</hi> depoſed <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and put <hi>Sadock</hi> in his place: You would inferre, that <hi>Elias,</hi> by the like reaſon, had the ſupremacie, becauſe hee, (as you ſay,) depoſed King <hi>Benhadad,</hi> and put <hi>Hazael</hi> in his place. Howbeit, you are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in much deceived. For it is not reade, in like ſort, that <hi>Elias</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2756:27"/> the one King, and put the other in his place.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.12.22.17.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.52. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37.</note> 
               <hi>The power to depoſe Kings, belongeth onely unto God, who giveth kingdomes, to whomſoever hee pleaſeth.</hi> But what the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> did, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Hazael</hi> to bee king over <hi>Syria,</hi> and concerning <hi>Iehu</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, to bee King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hee had a ſpeciall, and direct com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement for it, from God himſelfe. For the Lord ſaid thus unto <hi>Elias. Goe returne on thy way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 19.15.</note> 
               <hi>to the wilderneſſe of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus, and when thou commeſt, annoynt Hazael to bee King over Syria: And Iehu the ſonne of Nimſhi, ſhalt thou annoynt, to be King over Iſrael.</hi> So that it was God, (and not <hi>Elias,</hi>) that put downe the one King, and rayſed up the other. As for <hi>Elias,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 9.1.2.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and other Prophets, they were but the publiſhers and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Gods will and pleaſure, in all ſuch caſes, and not the depoſers of any Kings. Touching that you ſay of Queene <hi>Athalia,</hi> there was good reaſon for her to bee depoſed: For ſhee was a meere uſurper, and <hi>Ioas</hi> was the true, and rightfull heyre. For, <hi>Behold, (ſaith the Text,) the Kings ſonne muſt raigne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 23.3.</note> 
               <hi>as the Lord hath ſaid of the ſonnes of David.</hi> Neyther was it <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoida,</hi> the Prieſt alone, but the reſt of the rulers, and people alſo, that according to their duties both to God and the King, by an unanimous conſent, depoſed that wicked uſurper <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> and put <hi>Ioas</hi> in the kingdome, to whom the right of it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayned. For the words of the Text are.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.11.</note> 
               <hi>Then they brought out the Kings ſonne and put upon him the Crowne, and gave him the teſtimonie, and made him King: and Iehoida, and his ſonnes, annoynted him, and ſaid God ſave the King.</hi> And concerning King <hi>Vzziah,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Ozias,</hi> (whom you alſo mention,) it is true, that he went into the Temple of the Lord, to burne Incenſe, upon th' Altar of ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe &amp; that <hi>Azariah</hi> the Prieſt went in after him, &amp; with him foureſcore Prieſts of the Lord, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Eziah,</hi> &amp; ſaid unto him: <hi>It pertayneth not to thee Vziah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.16.17.18.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>to burne Incenſe unto the Lord, but to the Prieſts the ſons of Aaron, that are conſecrated, to offer incenſe. Goe thou forth of the ſanctuarie, for thou haſt tranſgreſſed, &amp;c.</hi> And for this his preſuming to burne incenſe he was ſtricken with a leproſie: which when <hi>Azariah</hi> the chiefe Prieſt, and the other Prieſts ſaw, and beheld, they cauſed him haſtily to depart from thence, and hee was even compelled to goe out becauſe the Lord had ſmitten him. So
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2756:28"/> that hee was not compelled to goe out of the Temple, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of any force, weapons, or violence, offered to his perſon, by <hi>Azariah,</hi> or any other, of the Prieſts: but becauſe the Lord had ſmitten him, <hi>(viz.)</hi> with a leaproſie. And therefore even your owne tranſlation, which you call <hi>S. Hieromes,</hi> hath it thus. <hi>Sed &amp; ipſe perterritus acceleravit egredi, eo qued ſenſiſſet il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lico plagam Domini. That hee made haſt himſelfe to goe out, as being terrified, with the preſent ſence of the Lords blow upon him.</hi> It is true, that <hi>Azarias</hi> the Prieſt, and the other Prieſts with him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the King. But how? by words onely, as namely, by telling him of his ſinne, adviſing him to goe out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and uſing divine threats, and ſuch other lawfull, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable courſes, as became Prieſts to uſe, but not by ſwords, and weapons, force of armes, or ſuch like externall power co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active. And thus doth <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> alſo himſelfe teſtifie, even in this verie caſe, and therefore bringeth in the Prieſt, ſaying thus unto God.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. de verbis Eſaiae, vidi Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homil. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I have done, (ſaith hee,) my dutie, to warne, and reprove him: I can goe no further: Nam ſacerdotis est, tantùm ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guere, &amp;c. For it is the Prieſts office, onely to reprove, and freely to admoniſh, and not, (ſaith he,) to aſſaile with armes, not to uſe tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets, not to handle ſpeares, not to bend bowes, not to caſt darts, but onely to reprove, and freely to admoniſh, &amp;c.</hi> But if it had beene ſo, that <hi>Azariah,</hi> and the reſt of the Prieſts with him, had forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and by bodily and externall violence, expelled, and thruſt the King out of the Temple, (which nevertheleſſe you ſee S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expreſſely denieth to have beene done,) yet were this no proofe, that therefore, they expelled, depoſed, or deprived him of his kingdome. Yea this king, <hi>Vziah,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called <hi>Ozias,</hi> notwithſtanding whatſoever theſe Prieſts did againſt him, and notwithſtanding his leaproſie, wherewith hee was ſtricken, was nevertheleſſe, not depoſed, nor deprived of his kingdome. For although he was a leaper, unto the day of his death, and dwelt as a leaper in an houſe, apart from others, according to the law: yet during the time, of that his leaproſie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.21.23.</note> did hee continue King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and all that while was <hi>Iotham his ſon over all the kings houſe, and iudged the people of the land, as a regent, or curator like a Lord Protector, or Lieutenant to his father.</hi> Neyther is it ſaid, that <hi>Iotham</hi> his ſonne
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2756:28"/> raigned in his ſtead, or governed as a king in his owne right, untill after the death of that his Father.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. antiq lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 11 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26 1.3.</note> And this appeareth to bee evidently true, by computation of time: for, <hi>Vzziah</hi> lived but ſixtie eight yeares in all, as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> witneſſeth: and hee was ſixteene yeares olde when hee began to raigne: and hee raigned fiftie two yeares, as the Scripture it ſelfe teſtifieth: So that from the time hee began to be a King, hee continued a King unto his dying day. But what meane you by all this? For if hereby you would proove it lawfull for the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to depoſe Kings, you ſee that the former precedents, and examples of thoſe Prophets, and Prieſts, which you produce, doe warrant no ſuch matter; admitting that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> were the chiefe or high Prieſt in the Chriſtian Church, which hee is not as I have now, and often ſaid, and ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Yea they rather declare the cleane contrarie to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, Romiſh and rebellious poſition. But if I will needes ſtill urge, that <hi>Salomon,</hi> as a King did depoſe <hi>Abiathar</hi> the high Prieſt, and put <hi>Zadocke</hi> in his place: It may bee anſwered, (ſay you,) that this act of <hi>Solomons</hi> was <hi>error facti,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not warrantable <hi>de Iure.</hi> It ſeemeth by this your manner of anſwering, that you care not much what you anſwer, ſo that you make any anſwer at all, bee it never ſo groſſe, abſurde, or unſound. For firſt, this your diſtinction, of, <hi>de facto,</hi> and <hi>de Iure,</hi> in this, and the like caſes, I have refelled, and confuted, before in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 13. &amp; pag. 86. &amp; 87. But, ſecondly, when the Text it ſelfe, ſpeaketh of this fact of King <hi>Solomon,</hi> by way of approbation of it, doth it become you, or any man elſe, to ſay, or ſuppoſe, that it was, <hi>error facti,</hi> in him? Or that it was an Act not lawfull for him ſo to doe? For hath not the Scripture it ſelfe, before expreſſely tould vs, <hi>That Solomon depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or cast out Abiathar from being Priest unto the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.27.</note> 
               <hi>that hee might fulfill the words of the Lord, which hee ſpake againſt the houſe of Ely in Shiloh.</hi> Now then, can that be ſaid to bee erroniouſly or unlawfully done, which God himſelfe well liked, and allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, and would have to bee done, for the performance, and fulfilling of his owne wordes? Yea, conſider yet further that the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> had power, and authoritie over the Prieſts, not onely to depoſe them, but alſo, to put them to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2756:29"/> death. And this you may ſee in King <hi>Saul,</hi> who put to death divers Prieſts,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sa.</hi> 22.18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 21.</note> and in King <hi>Ioash</hi> alſo, who put to death <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah, the ſonne of Iehoida the Prieſt:</hi> How juſtly, or unjuſtly, worthily or unworthily, theſe Prieſts were put to death, I here diſpute not: but I mention theſe examples, to ſhew the power &amp; authoritie that the Kings had in thoſe times, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly even to put Prieſts to death, aſwell as lay-perſons, upon juſt cauſe, and if they did offend ſo farre, as to deſerve it.</p>
            <p n="11">11. But, now, though there were a ſupremacy over the high Prieſts, aſwell, as over the other Prieſts, and Levites, in the Kings, under the Old Teſtament: and that they alſo dealt in maters Eccleſiaſticall: yet thereupon, it followeth not, (ſay you,) That Kings and Princes under the New Teſtament, have the like <hi>Supremacy,</hi> over Biſhops, and other Clergy men, or the like Authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, and concerning reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Why ſo? becauſe, (ſay you,) there is now a change and alteration of the Prieſthood, and of the Law. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12. But doth not the ſame Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> (which you cite,) tell you, wherein that Alteration and change conſiſteth, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely, that it is, in reſpect of the Leviticall Prieſthood, under the ould Law, or under the ould Teſtament: which is now changed into the Prieſthood of Chriſt, under the new Law, or under the new Teſtament? why then will you ſtretch, and extend it any further? yea, neither doth that Epiſtle, nor any other ſacred, or canonicall Scripture, teſtifie an Alteration or change, in this Point, or as touching this Particular whereof, we now ſpeake, but the cleane contrary: <hi>videlicet:</hi> that aſwell under the new Teſtament, as under the ould, Kings, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to have a ſupremacy, over all Biſhops, Paſtors, and other Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters, and an Authority alſo in cauſes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, aſwell, as civill and temporall, within their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. The firſt part of this Aſſertion, is manifeſt, by that Text in the new Teſtament, which I have ſo often recited, and where <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith expreſſely thus:<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>13.1.</hi> Chryſost. in Rom. hom, <hi>23</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubiect to the higher Powers:</hi> yea, <hi>Though you be an Apostle, though an Evangeliſt, though a Prophet, or whoſoever you be,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Chriſoſtome</hi> But what ſhall I neede to prove this ſo cleere a Point, ſo many times, and ſo often? For both in my firſt Booke, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 1. 2. 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2756:29"/> my <hi>Reply,</hi> chap. 1. pag. 39. 40, 41. &amp;c. and pag. 51. 52. 53. 54. &amp;c. this pointe is fully, and abundantly proved. Yea the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome themſelves, in former an ancient times, for the ſpace of divers hundreth yeares after Chriſt, did acknowledge this Subiection, to theſe higher powers, namely to their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors: as I have demonſtratively ſhewed by the examples of <hi>Milciades, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, mentioned in my firſt Booke, pag. 23. 24. 25. 26. And by <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> the firſt, <hi>Agatho, Hadrian,</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, mentioned in my <hi>Reply,</hi> chap. 1 pag. 11. 12. 13. 19. To all which, though particularly alledged by me, you according to your wonted wiſe maner, thought it beſt to anſwere nothing. Yea, both the parts of this Aſſertion, namely, that Emperors, Kings, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces under the new Teſtament, have Authority, not onely over Perſons Eccleſiaſticall, but in cauſes alſo Eccleſiaſticall, I have ſo ſufficiently proved throughout the firſt Chapter of my firſt Booke, and throughout the firſt Chapter of my ſecond Booke, which is my <hi>Reply,</hi> and in this booke alſo, as that all the Power, and force you have brought or can bring againſt it, will never be able, ſo much, as to ſhake it, much leſſe to ſubdue, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it.</p>
            <p>Yet for the more abundant proofe of this Authority of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors</hi> and Kings in maters Eccleſiaſticall, and concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: I alledged in my <hi>Reply,</hi> chap. 1. pag. 13 14. the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, and Example of that famous Chriſtian <hi>Emperor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the Great:</hi> whereunto, in your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> you have, (as well became your great learning, and wiſedome,) anſwered iuſt nothing at all. I alledged alſo, in the ſame my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 15. the example of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> that Chriſtian Emperor: where, you deny not, this Emperors making of Conſtitutions and Lawes, in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, and concerning Biſhops, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſticall Perſons. But you ſay, thoſe Lawes be not obſerved, by the Proteſtant Cleargie, and you give an inſtance in one particular. What is this to the purpoſe? For, the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was not, nor is, whether our Proteſtant Cleargie, obſerve thoſe Lawes, and Conſtitutions, yea, or no: But whether <hi>Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> that Chriſtian Emperour, made thoſe, or any ſuch lawes, and Conſtitutions, concerning Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2756:30"/> perſons. Now then whilſt you graunt, that hee made thoſe Lawes, and Conſtitutions concerning Eccleſiaſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and concerning Eccleſiaſticall perſons, you graunt ſo much as I contended for, that is to ſay, you graunt the whole matter that was in queſtion. And therefore why ſhould I diſpute any longer with you? Nevertheleſſe, you yet further ſay, that I much diſadvantage my cauſe by alleadging <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, who accounted &amp; called the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> the chiefe and head of all the holy Churches. But you ſhould doe well to obſerve in what ſence and reſpects, the Emperour ſo called, and accounted him: namely not that hee had in thoſe dayes, a ſupremacie over <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> who was then the Emperour:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uthen. conſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>15.</hi> Novel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> For <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> himſelfe teſtifieth the cleane contrarie to that conceit. <hi>Wee commaund, (ſaith hee,) the moſt holy Archbiſhops, and Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes of Rome, of Conſtantinople, of Alexandria, of Antioch, and of Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vag. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iceph: libr. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> Yea the fifth generall Councell it ſelfe was alſo called by the commandement of this Emperor <hi>Iuſtinian.</hi> So that it clearely appeareth, that hee had the ſupremacie, &amp; comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding authoritie over them all. But in reſpect of the ſoundneſſe of the faith, which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> held in thoſe times, againſt hereſies, and errors, it was, that the Emperour prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him before the other Biſhops, accounting himſelfe chiefe, or head amongſt them, for that cauſe. In which regard alſo, it is, that hee would have the Eaſterne Churches, to be imitators of him, and to follow him. Neither did this Emperor <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> write unto him, as to an univerſall or ſupreme Biſhop, in thoſe dayes over all, but onely, as to a Biſhop of a Province, or of a parte of the Chriſtian world, and namely, in this ſort <hi>Iohanni, Sanctiſſimo Archiepiſcopo almae urbis Romae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de. libr. <hi>1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.4.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; Patriarchae. To Iohn the moſt holy Archbiſhop, and Patriarch, of the famous Citie of Rome.</hi> Againe, in that Epiſtle, he deſired this <hi>Iohn</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to write his letters to him, and to the Biſhop of that his royall Citie of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> whom hee there calleth brother to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (and not his ſervant, or ſubject:) Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the Gloſſe it ſelfe, maketh this obſervation, and ſaith thus: <hi>Hic eum parificat: Here the Emperour equalleth the B ſhop of Conſtantinople, to the Biſhop of Rome.</hi> And, indeede, the firſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> conſiſting of 150. Biſhops,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2756:30"/> (Canon. 2. &amp; 3.) and the Generall Councell of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> alſo conſiſting of 630. Biſhops. (Act. 16.) and the ſixt Generall Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> (Can. 36) doe all decree the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> to be equall to the <hi>Sea</hi> of Rome: except one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that, in the meeting and aſſembly of the Biſhops, the Biſhop of Rome was, for Order ſake, to have the firſt Place, and the Biſhop of Conſtantinople, the ſecond Place: which, together with the reaſon thereof, you may ſee more fully declared in my firſt Booke, chap. 1. pag. 17. 18.</p>
            <p>I alledged further, in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 15. 16. 17. 18. many and ſundry Chapters, &amp; Lawes, made by the Emperour, <hi>Charles</hi> the great, otherwiſe called <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> concerning men, and matters Eccleſiaſticall, the Particulars whereof, you may there ſee: which becauſe you knew not how to anſwere, you paſſe them over with this ſaying, that they are not worth the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering: why ſo? in regard, (ſay you,) there is thereby no more diſcovered, then by thoſe before mentioned of <hi>Iustinian.</hi> And is not that mough, if it were no more but ſo? and yet is there more diſcovered in the one, then in the other. Howbeit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36 <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.31. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18.36.37. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25 <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8.13. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20.21.22.23. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.10.8.19.</note> the Lawes of thoſe two Emperors, <hi>(vizt,)</hi> both of <hi>Iuſtinian &amp; Charlemaine,</hi> I alledged not to any ſuch end, as you ſtill, &amp; ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, untruly ſuppoſe, <hi>(vizt,)</hi> thereby to prove the Spirituall Supremacy, to belong to Emperours, or Kings, (for the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Monarchy and Supremacy, I attribute, (as I ſaid before,) neither to Emperor, nor King, nor to Pope, nor Prelate, but to Chriſt Ieſus onely, the ſole Monarch, and head, of his whole Church,) but to this end, and purpoſe onely, namely to prove, that Emperours, and Kings, had in thoſe former, and auncient times, Authority over Perſons Eccleſiaſticall &amp; in cauſes alſo Eccleſiaſticall: which becauſe you neither doe, nor can deny, what doe you elſe but graunt them: &amp; conſequently, you here graunt once againe, the thing that is in queſtion, as a matter cleere, and vndenyable: and therefore what neede I to diſpute or debate this matter (any longer) with you? But here, (if I doe not miſtake you,) you ſeeme much to reſtraine the Power and Authority, of Emperors, and Kings, as though they might not make any new Lawes, or Conſtitutions, but onely ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, confirme, and put in execution, the olde, and former Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2756:31"/> lawes: If this be your meaning, you ſee how this conceit is confuted &amp; confounded, even by thoſe former pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents and examples of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> and <hi>Charlemaine.</hi> For it is evident, that <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> made many new lawes, and new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, which were not before: and ſo did alſo <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> frame and make divers and ſundrie new lawes, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Conſtitutions. And did not <hi>Conſtantine</hi> that firſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Chriſtian Emperour alſo make many new Lawes, and new Conſtitutions, concerning Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall matters, which were not made before his dayes? You may alſo remember,<note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt, <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>Serviunt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Chriſto leges ferendo pro Chriſte: Kings ſerve Chriſt by making lawes for Chriſt.</hi> And therefore they may, as occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, aſwell make new lawes for Chriſt, as commaund thoſe, that were formerly made for him, to bee put in execution. But if you meane, that you would have Emperours, and Kings, to make no lawes, nor cauſe any to bee put in execution, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Church, but ſuch as will well ſtand with the Lawes of God, his truth, Religion, and Ordinances, you therein ſay the ſame thing that Proteſtants doe.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8.</note> For they ſay with <hi>S. Paul, that they may doe nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth.</hi> And, that the power, &amp; authoritie of Emperours, Kings, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (if it be rightly uſed, and not abuſed,) is for God, and not againſt God, and for Chriſt, his Church, and Religion, and not for Antichriſt, or any untruths, hereſies, or errors whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Or if your meaning bee, that you would have Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, and Princes, in their making of lawes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, his Church, &amp; Religion, to take the adviſe, directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; counſell, of godly, learned, &amp; Orthodoxe Biſhops, and teachers, this is, alſo not denied, but graunted unto you: But then muſt you graunt on the other ſide, that if they bee not Orthodoxe Biſhops, and true teachers, but falſe teachers, or if they be ſuch as deliver errors, in ſtead of truths: ſuch mens erroneous counſailes, directions, and adviſes, are not to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, but to bee rejected, as I have ſhewed more fully in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 37. 38.</p>
            <p n="12">12. But after theſe times of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> mentioned in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 18. you come next in your <hi>Reioynder,</hi> to your
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2756:31"/> accuſation of <hi>Luther,</hi> &amp; <hi>Calvine,</hi> mentioned in my <hi>Reply,</hi> p. 49. So that here you skip over no leſſe then fifteen whole leaves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in that my <hi>Reply.</hi> Yet what have you now to ſay againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvine?</hi> In your firſt Anſwer, you tooke occaſion, (for I gave you none,) to inveigh againſt them, as if they had beene Adverſaries to Kings, and Princes, and to the obedience due to them. In that my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 49. I ſaid, that the works, and writings of them both did ſhew, &amp; openly proclayme the contrarie to the world. And this is indeede, verie apparant:<note place="margin">Luth. tom. <hi>1.</hi> in Gen. cap. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; tom. <hi>3.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nota. in Deut capit. <hi>6.</hi> fol. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; fol. <hi>552.</hi> Rom. <hi>13.1.2 3.4.5.6.</hi> Luth. tom. <hi>2.</hi> reſp. ad Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. cather fo. <hi>150.</hi> &amp; <hi>152</hi>
               </note> For, where as ſome objected, <hi>That the rule, or governement of one man over another, might ſeeme, a tyrannous uſurpation, becauſe all men are naturally of like condition: To this, (ſaith Luther,) must wee that have the word of God oppoſe the commaundement, and ordinance of God, who hath put a ſword into the hand of the Magistrate, whom therefore the Apoſtle calleth, Gods Miniſter.</hi> Againe, hee ſaith: <hi>I grieve, and bluſh, and groane to ſee, how ſcornefully, our Emperours, and Princes of Germanie, are abuſed by the Pope: whom hee leadeth, and handleth, like bruite beaſts, both for ſpoile, and ſlaughter, at his owne pleaſure. This Poperie, (ſaith hee,) is lively deſcribed by S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>where bee ſaith, They deſpiſe Rulers, or Governours: by Rulers, ſignifying ſecular Princes. Now the Popiſh Cleargie, have by their owne authoritie, exempted themſelves, from tributes, ſubiection, and all charges of the Common-weale, contrarie to the doctrine of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Paul: Yea, ſo farre is the Pope, from acknowledging the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignetie of Princes, over him, that hee will ſcarce admitte them to kiſſe his feete. Calvine,</hi> likewiſe, writeth thus. <hi>The word of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calvin. Instit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> ſect. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>(ſaith hee,) teacheth us to obey all Princes, who are eſtabliſhed in there thrones, be it by what meanes ſoever: Yea, though they doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, then the office of Kings, yet must they bee obeyed, and though the King be never ſo wicked, and indeede, unworthy the name of a King, yet muſt ſubiects acknowledge the image of Divine power, in his publike authoritie, and, as touching obedience, they muſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and honour him, aſwell as if hee were the godlyeſt King in the world. Nebuchadnezzar was a mightie invader and ſubduer of other Nations: yet God ſaith by his Prophet, that he had given thoſe lands, and countries unto him. Ezech.</hi> 29. <hi>&amp; Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>Neyther would he have any rebellion, or reſistance to be offered, but contrarywiſe commaunded obedience to be performed unto him. Iere.</hi> 27. <hi>And therefore we muſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2756:32"/> never ſuffer theſe ſeditious conceites, to poſſeſſe our mindes, as to thinke an evill King muſt be ſo dealt withall, as hee deſerveth, but we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly charged to obey the King, though he bee a ſavage Tyrant, and never ſo bad.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beza confeſſ. cap. <hi>5.</hi> ſect. <hi>45</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> alſo ſpeaketh in like ſort. <hi>Private men, (amongst whom, I account inferiour Magistrates, in reſpect of their King,) have no other remedie, (ſaith hee,) againſt Tyrants, to whom they are ſubiect, but amendment of their lives, prayers, and teares: which God in his good time, will not deſpiſe. And if it ſo fall out, that wee cannot obey the commandement of the King, but that wee muſt offend God, the King of kings, Then muſt wee rather obey God, then man: Yet ſo, as that wee remember, that it is one thing, not to obey: and, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>to reſiſt, and to betake ourſelves to Armes, which wee may not doe.</hi> Againe hee ſaith: <hi>The impudencie of our Adverſaries, is herein moſt notorious, that they who contrarie to the word of God, have openly ſubiected Kings, and kingdomes, to their authoritie, and be themſelves the most rebellious ſect under heaven yet dare netwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to obiect the guilt of that crime unto us.</hi> Theſe being the doctrines, and poſitions of <hi>Luther, Calvine, Beza,</hi> and other Proteſtants, concerning Kings, and kingdomes, let the equall Reader Iudge, what, and how great the wrong is, you doe unto them, and whether alſo, that is, or can poſsibly be true, which you write, both in your Anſwer, and, againe, in your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder,</hi> namely, <hi>That Kings, and Princes may more confidently build the ſafetie of their perſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.36. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.21.22.23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15.16. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>and eſtates upon the loyaltie, of their Catholicke ſubiects, then upon any Proteſtant ſubiects.</hi> Why, more confidently, I pray you? For, is this a good reaſon which you bring, <hi>(viz.)</hi> becauſe, although Papiſts give the ſpirituall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, headſhip, and Monarchie, over the whole Church upon earth, unto the Pope, (which indeed, they ſhould not do, in aſmuch as it is a Regall right, and Prerogative, properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing unto <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>) yet doe they acknowledge in Kings, a ſupremacie in Temporall matters yea, this reaſon, (if you did well obſerve it,) maketh rather much againſt you: For, it ſheweth that Papiſts bee <hi>revera,</hi> neyther ſo good Chriſtians nor yet ſo good ſubiects,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.19.</note> as Proteſtants bee. Not ſo good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: becauſe, <hi>They bold not the head</hi> CHRIST IESVS, (as <hi>S. Paul ſpeaketh,</hi>) but have, without any warrant, or commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from him errected to themſelves, another head, Monarch,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2756:32"/> and Spirituall King, namely the Pope of <hi>Rome:</hi> Not ſo good ſubjects becauſe they acknowledge not, to belong unto Kings, an authoritie over perſons Eccleſiaſticall, and in cauſes alſo Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, aſwell as Civill, and Temporall, as Proteſtants doe. For, whereas you ſay that the Proteſtant Subjects, doe take from the King, the Temporall ſupremacie, aſwell as the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, it is too lewd, and loud a ſlaunder. Yea what is there, that the Proteſtants doe more earneſtly contend for, againſt the Pope, and againſt his partakers, then the Spirituall ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, or Spirituall kingdome, to be given to Chriſt Ieſus? And the Civill, or Temporall ſupremacie over perſons Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and in matters Eccleſiaſticall, aſwell as Temporall, to bee given unto Kings and Princes, within their Dominions? But becauſe you yet further object againſt the Proteſtants, both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious doctrines, and rebellious practiſes, and affirme that many inſtances of this kinde may bee reade in the Booke of dangerous Poſitions: For a cleere and full Anſwer to all that you have ſaid, or rather Papiſts have, or can ſay, in that caſe, I referre you unto that Booke, which is called <hi>An exact Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie of Romiſh Doctrine in the Caſe of Conſpiracie &amp; Rebellion:</hi> and the <hi>Reply</hi> to him, that calleth himſelfe, the <hi>Moderate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer thereof.</hi> In which Bookes ſo conjoyned in one Volume, you may reade, and ſee at large, a cleere juſtification of <hi>Luther, Calvine, Beza,</hi> and other Proteſtants in this point, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywiſe the Papiſts, to bee notoriouſly guiltie therein. And this you may alſo ſee further debated, and ſhewed in that Booke, which is called, <hi>The true difference betweene Christian ſubiection, and unchriſtian Rebellion:</hi> In the third part whereof, be refelled the Ieſuites reaſons, and authorities, which they alleadge for the Popes depriving of Princes, and the bearing of Armes by Subjects againſt their Soveraignes: and where the tyrannies, and injuries of Antichriſt, ſeeking to exalt himſelfe above Kings, and Princes, bee further diſcovered and declared, &amp;c. Theſe things, I would not here thus farre have ſpoken of, had not you provoked me thereunto, not only by your firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but by your continuance, &amp; ſtill ſtiffe-ſtanding in theſe your needleſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſons, &amp; calumniations But you proceed, &amp; come next from p. 50. in my <hi>Reply,</hi> to p. 79. where, againe you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2756:33"/> skippe over fourteene leaves more together, in the ſame booke. In that pag. 79. It is true, that I ſaid. That not onely thoſe kings of <hi>England</hi> before mentioned, namely King <hi>William Rufus,</hi> king <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> and ſome others, thus contended, and oppoſed themſelves againſt the Pope of <hi>Rome:</hi> But King <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> alſo, who was before all theſe, made the like Kingly oppoſition. For when <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> otherwiſe called Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Seventh,</hi> was bold to demand of this King, an Oath of fealtie, to bee made to him, as if the King were to hold the kingdome of him, as of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord: This King would by no meanes yeeld thereunto, but ſent him a full negative Anſwer, writing thus unto him. <hi>Fidelitatem facere nolui, nec volo, quia nec ego promiſi, nec anteceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res meos, anteceſſoribus tuis, id feciſſe comperio. I neyther would doe, nor will doe fealtie, becauſe</hi> I <hi>neyther promiſed it, nor doe I finde, that any of my Predeceſſors have done it to any of your predeceſſors.</hi> I have here recited, the whole, &amp; entire ſentence, &amp; not produced onely a part of it, as you did, verie lamely, and imperfectly. And now what have you to ſay againſt it? Firſt concerning that of King <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerour,</hi> you anſwer not a word. And touching thoſe particulars, which I had before alleadged, concerning the others Kings, namely concerning <hi>William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>First,</hi> and King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> and other Kings of England, that contended, and oppoſed themſelves againſt the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> his encreachments, and uſurpations, your anſwer is verie idle and impertinent. For you anſwer, as if I had affirmed, that thoſe Kings had utterly renounced, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, or put downe, the Popes ſupremacie in their times, whereas I affirmed onely, that they contended, and made op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt him; which they might, and did doe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they then made not an utter extirpation, and aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, out of that their kingdome. And that they made oppoſition to him, I have ſhewed and proved in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 75. 76. 78. 79. 80. And verie ignorant are you in the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of England, if you know not ſo much: and verie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, if knowing ſo much you will not acknowledge it.</p>
            <p n="13">13. From thence you come to pag. 81 of my <hi>Reply,</hi> where I write thus: <hi>But now what meaneth my adverſarie to bee ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2756:33"/> audacious, as to denie the firſt foure Generall Councels, to have beene called by the Emperours?</hi> Here you ſay, I was pleaſed to ſalute you with that language, which better fitted <hi>an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderative Ieſter, then a deliberate Iudge.</hi> Why? what is the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or what are the words, which ſo much offend you? You afterward ſhew, namely, becauſe I there uſed that terme of <hi>extreamely audacious?</hi> But what is it elſe, but <hi>extreme audaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> to denie as you then did, and ſtill doe, ſo cleere, evident, and plaine a truth? For my part, the matter conſidered, I ſee not, but you might have thought, that I ſpake moderately, and temperately enough, whilſt I ſpake in that ſort, and gave you no worſe language: For ſome others poſsibly would have ſaid, that you had beene, therein, extreamely, and intolerably impudent. But you forget, as it ſeemeth, or care not to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, what language or words, you here utter, concerning me, which I have more cauſe to take ill at your hands, then you have to bee offended, at thoſe other words of mine. But to come to thoſe foure Generall Councels: I affirmed them, (which you denied,) to have beene called by the Emperours. The firſt of them, is, <hi>The firſt Generall Councell of Nyce:</hi> That this was called by the Emperour, I proved in that my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 81.82. by the teſtimonie of <hi>Ruffinus, Euſebius, Socrates, Theodoret, Sozomon, Zonaras, Nicephorus, Platina,</hi> and by the <hi>Synodall Epiſtle of the Nycene Fathers themſelves.</hi> And doth not hee then deſerve to bee accounted, at leaſt extreamely auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that will dare to denie this ſo manifeſt, and palpable truth, teſtified ſo abundantly, and by ſo many witneſſes? But whilſt among other witneſſes for proofe of this point, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> affirming, that <hi>Conſtantine, apud urbem Nicaeam, Epiſcopale Concilium convocavit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffin. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Called the Councell of Biſhops to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, at the Citie of Nyce:</hi> You ſay, that I there uſed, a little wile, which amongſt the vulgar ſort will bee called Craft or Couſenage: becauſe, ſay you, I omitted thoſe wordes, <hi>Ex ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotum ſententia:</hi> which bee in <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> and which words, if they had beene mentioned, would have declared, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Conſtantine ſummoned or called the Councell of Nyce, by the adviſe, conſent, or approbation of the Prieſts.</hi> Howbeit, firſt it is not of neceſsitie, that the omiſsion of thoſe wordes, muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2756:34"/> it to bee done, with a minde and purpoſe to defraude, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and couſen, as you verie odiouſly ſuggeſt. Yea, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſhew, that I did not craftily, or couſeningly, conceale, or omitte thoſe wordes, for mine owne advantage, as you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, behold, you ſhall finde, in the verie next page, namely, pag. 82. that I doe expreſſely mention them, and doe directly affirme,<note place="margin">Ruffin. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> out of the ſame <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> that this Councell of <hi>Nyce,</hi> was aſſembled, or called, <hi>Ex ſacerdotum ſententia, By the adviſe and conſent of the Prieſts:</hi> and thereby I alſo proved, that it was not done by the adviſe &amp; conſent of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> alone. Now then who is the wily, Craftie, and Couſening Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I hope the honeſt; and equall Reader will by this time eaſily diſcerne, and judge. But thirdly, I did there further an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, (as I doe likewiſe here againe,) that it maketh nothing to the matter in queſtion, at whoſe ſuite, or requeſt, or by whoſe adviſe or conſent, that Councell was ſummoned: For the queſtion, was not, nor is, by whoſe perſwaſion or ſuite, or by whoſe adviſe, or conſent, but by whoſe commaunding authoritie, it was called. Now it is verie apparant, by thoſe former teſtimonies, that it was called, and aſſembled, by the commandement, or commanding authoritie of the Emperour: which declareth infallibly, the ſupremacie, and authority, which the Emperour had in thoſe dayes over all the Biſhops, and even over the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelfe, aſwell as over the reſt, whilſt hee might and did thus commaund, aſwell the one as the other, to appeare in a Generall Councell. I alſo cited <hi>Euſebius, Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and their wordes, to prove likewiſe that the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> called, and aſſembled that Generall Councell at <hi>Nyce:</hi> But you are pleaſed not to ſee, or not to acknowledge, where thoſe wordes are to bee found in their Authors: And yet might you have ſeene and found them, (if you had ſo pleaſed,) in their ſeverall Authors: as namely in <hi>Euſebius de vita Constantini, lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; lib</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 37 <hi>in Socrates, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. in the <hi>Greeke,</hi> and <hi>cap.</hi> 5 in the <hi>Latin:</hi> and in <hi>Theodoret, lib.</hi> 1 <hi>cap</hi> 7. So that even that alſo which I ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> is not a famous fiction (as you infamouſly and untruely report it,) but a verie certaine, &amp; apparant truth, as there you may ſee. And all the reſt of the Authors, which I
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2756:34"/> there cited, doe likewiſe teſtifie, and prove the ſame thing for which I there alleadged them. Yea, this point is ſo cleere and evident, that whilſt you thought to confute it, you have your ſelfe further confirmed, and confeſſed it.<note place="margin">Ruffin. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For when you purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to alledge <hi>Ruffinus</hi> againſt mee, doe cite his wordes, thus: <hi>Tumille, Then hee,</hi> (meaning <hi>Conſtantine,) ex ſacerdotum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, apud urbem Nycaeam, Epiſcopale concilium, convocavit: By the ſentence, or conſent of the Prieſts, did call the councell of Biſhops, at the citie of Nyce:</hi> And when againe, you likewiſe intending to alledge <hi>Damaſus</hi> againſt me, doe affirme, that he ſaith: <hi>That Conſtantine, did not gather the councell,</hi> but <hi>cum conſenſu Silveſtri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Damaſus lin Pont. concil. <hi>6</hi> act. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>with the conſent of Sylveſter: and that ſo much alſo, is expreſſed in the ſixt councell.</hi> Doe you not, in all this, ſufficiently confeſſe, that the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> did, by his commanding au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, <hi>call this councell of Nyce,</hi> although hee did it, by the conſent, or approbation of <hi>Sylveſter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of other Prieſts? Now then to come to the ſecond generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, (which was the firſt <hi>Conſtantinopolitane,</hi>) I have likewiſe proved in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag 83. by the teſtimonies of <hi>Theodoret, Socrates, Sozomen, Zonaras,</hi> and the verie Councell it ſelfe, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the Emperour, <hi>Theodoſius the elder,</hi> that it was called by the commaundment, or commaunding Authoritie of the ſame Emperour. To all which proofes, and teſtimonies, yon, (according to your wonted learning &amp; wiſdome,) anſwer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in your <hi>Reioynder.</hi> But in your firſt auſwer, to prove this Councell, not to bee called by the commaundement of the Emperour, but of <hi>Damaſus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> you cited <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret libr.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. and in your <hi>Reioynder</hi> you proſecute it, and ſay, <hi>That the Biſhops meeting in this ſecond generall councell, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Pope Damaſus doe teſtifie, that they aſſembled at Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, by reaſon of his letter ſent the yeare before to Theodoſius.</hi> But what meane you thus to abuſe your Reader? For firſt there is no ſuch thing in that place of <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodor lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> that doth prove this ſecond Generall Councell, to have beene any more called by <hi>Damaſus,</hi> then by the other Biſhops mentioned in the ſame Letter, or in the ſame Epiſtle. For, that Letter, or Epiſtle, was not written, or directed to one alone, as namely to <hi>Damaſus,</hi> (as you would make men beleeve,) but to many and diverſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2756:35"/> Biſhops plurally. For thus is the direction, <hi>(viz.) To our moſt honourable Lords, our verie Reverend brothers, and fellowes in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, Damaſus, Ambroſius, Britton, Valerian, Acholius, Anemius, Baſil, and the reſt of the holy Biſhops aſſembled in the noble Citie of Rome. The holy Councell of Orthodoxe Biſhops, gathered together in the great Citie of Conſtantinople, ſend Greeting.</hi> So that, it was not <hi>Damaſus</hi> alone, (as here you ſee,) but the reſt of thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhops alſo, aſſembled at <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſent thoſe Letters, mentioned in that Epiſtle to the moſt holy Emperour <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius.</hi> And ſecondly, even thoſe Letters of <hi>Damaſus,</hi> and of the reſt of the Biſhops, ſent to the Emperour, concerning that matter of calling the Councell were onely perſwaſive, and not commaunding Letters: In aſmuch as it is before, by my <hi>Reply,</hi> verie evident, that this Councell was aſſembled by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, or commaunding Letters of the Emperour. And conſequently it was not <hi>Damaſus</hi> alone, but other Biſhops alſo joyned with him, that ſent thoſe their Letters to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, whereby hee was excited, moved, and perſwaded, to call, and commaund that Councell to bee aſſembled at <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> Now then, ſeeing that <hi>Theodoret</hi> whom you cite to prove, that Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> by his commaunding Letters, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Councell,<note place="margin">Theodor. l. b. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> proveth no ſuch matter: Yea hee expreſſely witneſſeth the contrarie, affirming it directly, to have beene called by the commaundement of the Emperour: Doth or can this any way helpe to excuſe you? Or doth it not rather ſo much the more inlarge, and aggravate your fault herein?</p>
            <p>Concerning the third Generall Councell, (which was the firſt <hi>Epheſine.</hi>) that, That was called by the commaundement of the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the <hi>younger,</hi> I have alſo proved in in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 83. by the teſtimonies of <hi>Evagrius, Liberatus, Socrates, Zonaras, Nicephorus,</hi> &amp; by the <hi>Synodall</hi> Epiſtle it ſelfe. And yet you would make men beleeve, that it was called not by the commaundement of the Emperour, but of <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> And for proofe hereof, you cite <hi>Proſper in Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico,</hi> affirming it to have beene held <hi>Caeleſtini authoritate. By the authority of Celeſtine.</hi> But you ſtill much miſtake, for this was no commandement, or commaunding authoritie in <hi>Celestinus,</hi> but a perſwaſive onely, which Biſhops might, and did uſe to the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2756:35"/> Emperours, verie often, for the obtayning of Councels. So that by theſe wordes, is no more meant, or ſignified, but that <hi>Celestinus</hi> uſed ſuch authoritie, that is, ſuch power, credite, and eſtimation, as hee had with the Emperour, to cauſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this Councell to bee aſſembled. And that this word, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas,</hi> doth ſo ſignifie, and is verie often uſed in that ſence, your <hi>Dictionaries,</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> writers, will ſufficiently teach you. Yea, your ſelfe, in your <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> doe cite <hi>Paulus Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conus,</hi> in his <hi>Hiſtoricall collections,</hi> that hee ſpeaketh of the laſt of the firſt foure Generall Councels, (which was the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Calcedon,</hi>) in this ſort. <hi>Papae Leonis auctoritate, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paul. Diac. lib. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>By the authoritie of Pope Leo, and commaund of Martian the Emperour, the Councell of Culcedon was ſummoned.</hi> Here you ſee a plaine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, made betweene this <hi>authoritie,</hi> &amp; the <hi>commaund.</hi> The commaund, or commanding authoritie, being attributed to the Emperour <hi>Martian:</hi> and the other authoritie, namely the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive, being attributed to <hi>Leo,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> And yet ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was it onely <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but other Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, and Biſhops, likewiſe, as namely <hi>Cyrill</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zonar. in Theodoſ. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niore.</note> and <hi>Iuvenall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that perſwaded, and excited the Emperour, to call and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, this third Generall Councell at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> as <hi>Zonaras</hi> teſtifieth.</p>
            <p>And as touching the fourth Generall Councell, which was, as I ſaid, that at <hi>Calcedon:</hi> I have proved in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 85. by the teſtimonie of the verie Councell it ſelfe, and by ſundry Epiſtles alſo, of <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that this Councell of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> was ſummoned by the commaundement of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: whereunto may be alſo added, that your owne teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of <hi>Paulus Diaconus,</hi> before cited, who ſaith, (as even your ſelfe alledged him,) that this fourth Generall Councell of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> was ſummoned or called by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Martian</hi> the Emperour, and not of <hi>Leo,</hi> although <hi>Leo</hi> did alſo interpoſe and uſe his authoritie, and credite with the Emperour, for the effecting of it. Now then, when beſide the cleereneſſe of other proofes, you ſaw by this expreſſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie or <hi>Prulus Diaconus,</hi> (whom your ſelfe alledged,) that this Councell of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> was ſummoned, or called by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2756:36"/> of the Emperor <hi>Martian,</hi> why ſhould you, or any man elſe, ſay, or ſuppoſe the contrarie thereunto? Yea even <hi>Leo</hi> himſelfe, in divers of his Epiſtles, ſheweth, (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore,) that neyther hee, nor any other Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> did, in thoſe dayes, ſummon or call, eyther this, or any other Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell, but that it belonged to the Emperours, ſo to doe, as you may ſee more fully, by the wordes and actions, of the ſame <hi>Leo,</hi> formerly mentioned in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 84.85. But I there alſo further alledged, a fifth Generall Councell, called, <hi>Mandato Iuſtiniani, By the commaundement of Iustinian the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</hi> And other Councels I likewiſe there alledged, called by Emperours: to all which, you anſwer nothing. Nor doe you anſwer to <hi>Cardinall Cuſanus,</hi> there alſo produced by me, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and affirming expreſſely, though it were againſt the Pope, that, <hi>The firſt eight Generall councels, were called by the Emperours.</hi> Yea, this is ſo cleere a caſe, and ſo evident a truth, that <hi>S. Hierome</hi> maketh it to bee of the eſſence of a Generall Councell: <hi>Dic quis Imperator juſſerit hanc Synodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> convocari: Tell us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. lib. <hi>2.</hi> in Ruffin.</note> 
               <hi>(ſaith hee,) what Emperour commaunded this councell to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled:</hi> thereby declaring, that it was held for no Generall Councell in thoſe dayes, unleſſe it were called, and aſſembled by the commaundement of the Emperour. Now then, upon all theſe premiſſes, I leave it to the equall Reader, to judge, whether hee that denieth this ſo cleere, plaine, and palpable, a truth, be not juſtly worthy to bee accounted, at leaſt, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely audacious,</hi> if not extreamely impudent.</p>
            <p n="14">14. And yet you would ſeeme to ſay further, that <hi>S. Peter</hi> by his authoritie and commaundement, called the Councell which was at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in the Apoſtles times, (<hi>Act.</hi> 15.) and, that hee was alſo the Preſident therein. But you prove it not, neyther is there any ſuch thing in the Text appearing, that hee commaunded or called that Councell. Yea, hee had no ſuch commaunding, or compulſive authoritie over the reſt of the Apoſtles. The <hi>Greeke Scholiaſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>That hee did nothing imperiouſly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. Schol. in Act. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or with commaunding authoritie, but all things by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent.</hi> And therefore, in thoſe times of the Apoſtles, did that Councell at <hi>Ieruſalem, (Act.</hi> 15.6.) come together, and was aſſembled by common conſent, and agreement amongſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2756:36"/> themſelves: But afterward, indeede, in the ſucceeding times, when the Emperours became Chriſtians, <hi>The Eccleſiasticall affaires,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Socrates,) did much depend upon them, ſo that the greateſt Councels were in time paſt, and ſtill are,</hi> (ſaith <hi>hee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. libr. <hi>5.</hi> in Prooemio.</note>) <hi>at this day, called by their appointment.</hi> Neyther was <hi>Peter,</hi> the firſt man, that ſpake in that Councell, (as you affirme, ſeeking thereby to prove him to bee alſo the Preſident therein:) For the Text ſheweth, <hi>that there had beene great diſputation, before Peter roſe up, and ſpake, Act.</hi> 15.7. Yea, it ſeemeth, that <hi>Iames</hi> rather then <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> was the Preſident in that Councell: For <hi>Iames</hi> was he, that gave the definitive ſentence, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.19.20. &amp; to that ſentence of his, did both <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of that Councell, conſent, and condeſcend, and accordingly, was the decree drawne and made up, in that Councell, and ſent unto the Churches, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.22.23 24.25.26.27.28.29. Neyther is it true, that to Preſide, or to be Preſident, in Councels, is a right properly belonging to the Pope, whatſoever you ſay: Yea, it is verie evidently, and abundantly diſproved in Eccleſiaſticall hiſtorie, by ſundrie Councels, wherein others,<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han. ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litar. vitan: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes.</note> and not the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> were the Preſidents. And <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelfe ſaith expreſſely, of <hi>Hoſius,</hi> that hee was, in his time, <hi>Concilio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Princeps, the chiefe, Prince, or Preſident of the Councels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. But in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 30. I ſaid further, that <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> did approve of the Authoritie of the Emperours, in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall cauſes: and this I proved by two inſtances, and not by one onely, (as you ſay:) The firſt was this, that when <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was commaunded to conferre, with one <hi>Arius,</hi> concerning matters of faith: hee anſwered: <hi>Who is ſo farre out of his wits, that hee dare refuſe the commaundement of his Prince?</hi> The other, was this. <hi>That the Emperours commaundement made him to appeare before the Councell of Tyrus: and finding that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, not to be indifferent, but partially affected, Hee and the reſt of the Orthodoxe Biſhops, appealed to the Emperour.</hi> To the former you anſwer nothing at all, in your <hi>Rejoynder.</hi> To the latter, you ſpeake ſomewhat, and doe ſay, that, <hi>That which I call the councell of Tyrus, was no councell at all.</hi> And this you would prove by the teſtimonie of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelfe, where he ſaith thus. <hi>Qua fronte, talem conventum, Synodum appellare audent, cui
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2756:37"/> comes Praeſedit, With what face dare they call ſuch an aſſembly! a Synod, or Councell, in which the Count did Preſide?</hi> But doe you thinke this, to be a reaſon ſufficient, to prove it to be no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at all, or in any ſort, becauſe a <hi>Count</hi> being a Lay-man did Praeſide in it, as Deputie, or Lieuftenant to the Emperour, and in his ſtead? Doth not your ſelfe ſay in your <hi>Rejoynder,</hi> that the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the <hi>Younger,</hi> ſent <hi>Count Candidianus,</hi> as his Lieuſtenant to the Councell of <hi>Epheſus?</hi> will you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude, that this Councell of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> was alſo therefore no Councell at all, becauſe this <hi>Count Candidianus,</hi> being a lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, was Preſident, or Lieuftenant it it, in ſtead of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour? For you may aſwell conclude the one, as the other by that reaſon. Doe not therefore miſconſter nor miſtake, that holy man <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> nor wrong, nor delude your Reader by a fallacie, <hi>à dicto ſecundum quid, ad dictum ſimpliciter.</hi> For if you reade him diligently, and obſervantly, you will finde, that he denyed it not to bee a Councell, ſimply and abſolutely, but in ſome reſpects; as, namely, in reſpect it conſiſted of <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops, and of that <hi>Arrian Preſident,</hi> and that, their plotte, purpoſe, and endeavour was to advance <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> againſt Gods truth, and the <hi>Orthodexe</hi> Biſhops of that time, and againſt the decrees of the former famous Councell of <hi>Nyce,</hi> in that point: and in reſpect alſo, that not juſtice, but vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or tyranny was there intended, and ſuch like. And this you might have perceived, if you had gone on, with the words of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> which are theſe, (viz.) <hi>Qua fronte, talem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Athan. apolo. <hi>2</hi> pag. <hi>567.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Synodum appellare audent, cui Comes praeſidet? Et ubi ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culator apparchat? Et Comentarienſis ſive Carcerarius, pro Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Eccleſiae, adventantes introducebat? ubi Comes verba faciebat, caeteri praeſentes in ſilentio erant, vel potius Comiti obſequium ſuum, accommodabant, &amp;c.</hi> Againe he there ſaith. <hi>Qua ſpecies ibi Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>566.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ubi vel caedes, vel exilium, ſi Caeſari placuiſſet, conſtituebatur?</hi> And againe hee ſaith. <hi>Niceni Concilij Decreta irrita, ſua autem, rata volunt: Et Synodi vocabulo uti audent, qui tantae Synodo non obtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perant: Nihil illis Synodi curae ſunt, ſed inanem ſpeciem Synodi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texunt, ut ſublatis Orthodoxi viris, ea quae verae, &amp; magnae Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>619.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>de Arianis, ſtatuta ſunt, demoliantur.</hi> And therefore hee ſaith further, thus <hi>Quaeres cumita agerentur, ab ijs tanquam è concilio injurioſcrum, receſsimus. Quod enim libuit, fecere. That whilſt theſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2756:37"/> things were thus done, wee ſaith hee, departed from them, as from a Councell of injurious perſons: For they did what they listed:</hi> You ſee then in what reſpects it is, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> diſliked, and condemned this Councell of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> as not worthy the name of a Councell: Yet, for all that, hee affirmed it not to be no Councell at all ſimply and abſolutely, and to all intents, and purpoſes, as you would perſwade. For if it had been no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at all, or in any ſort, why was it convocated or aſſembled, as a Councell? Or why was <hi>Athanaſius</hi> commaunded by the Emperour to appeare there? Or why did the ſame <hi>Athanaſius</hi> afterward appeale from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to th Emperor? yea even <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> himſelfe, affirmeth it to be a councell, ſuch a one as it was, &amp; giveth it expreſſely, the name of a Councell, when he ſaith, as you heard before, that he, and the reſt of the Orthodoxe Biſhops departed from thence, <hi>tanquam è Concilio iniurioſorum, as from a Councell of iniurious Perſons.</hi> So that, a Councell him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe here acknowledged it to bee, though a bad Councell, though a Councell of injurious, and wicked Perſons, and a Councell not worthy to bee called a Councell, becauſe it thus intended and endeavored, the advancement of <hi>Arrianiſme.</hi> But what? Will you ſay, that the many and ſundrie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels convocated, and aſſembled in times paſt, wherein <hi>Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi> was eſtabliſhed, were therefore no Councels at all, or in any ſort? Yea this of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> (aſwell as thoſe,) was held to be a Councell, (though a wicked, and impious one,) not onely by <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> but by <hi>Socrates</hi> alſo, and by <hi>Theodoret</hi> likewiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat. libr.</hi> 1. <hi>c</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 21 <hi>ca.</hi> 22. <hi>Theodor. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 28. <hi>c.</hi> 29 <hi>c.</hi> 30.31.</note> who in their ſeverall Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories, doe often call it expreſſely by that name, of the Councell of <hi>Tyrus.</hi> And even that Chriſtian Emperour alſo, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> himſelfe, wrote un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, by the ſame name, calling them the Councell of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi> And it is yet further recorded, that, by the Emperours commaundement, this Councell of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> (expreſſely againe ſo called.) was removed from <hi>Tyrus,</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then you ſay, that the fact, whereof <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by the <hi>Arrians,</hi> in that Councell of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> was a meere civill crime, belonging to the Temporall Tribunall: to wit the killing of <hi>Arſenius,</hi> and cutting of his hand. But you are full deceived: For it was not onely the killing of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſenius,</hi> and the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2756:38"/> cutting of his hand, (as you alledge,) but it was further, the uſing of that hand,<note place="margin">Socrat libr. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> (ſo ſuggeſted to bee cut of,) to <hi>Magicke,</hi> and <hi>Sorcerie,</hi> that was layd to his charge: Yea, ſundrie other things alſo were layd to his charge, as namely, <hi>that hee had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowred a virgin:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoret. lib <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and that one of his Cleargie, had beaten downe the Altar, overthrowne the Lords Table, broken the holy Cuppe, and burned the bleſſed Bible.</hi> For all which miſdemeanours, his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers ſought to get him diſplaced, and depoſed in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. So that it was not a meere Civill crime, that was layd to his charge, as you ſuppoſe, but they were mixt offences, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Civill, and Temporall, and partly Epiſcopall, and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall. And therefore well might it bee called in ſome reſpect, <hi>Negotium Imperatorium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Athan. apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>568.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a matter Imperiall,</hi> namely in reſpect of the accuſation of killing of <hi>Arſenius.</hi> and the cutting of his hand, if you goe no further but to conſider theſe facts one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſingly and apart from the reſt: For ſo alſo did the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> himſelfe, as it ſeemeth, for a while, conceive of it, and therefore wrote to <hi>Dalmatius,</hi> the <hi>Cenſor,</hi> that hee ſhould call before him, ſuch as were accuſed, heare the matter, and puniſh the offenders:<note place="margin">Socra. libr. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> But afterward hee altered his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and ſtopped that courſe of hearing <hi>Athanaſius</hi> matters before the <hi>Cenſor,</hi> and would have them to bee heard, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined before the Councell of Biſhops, which was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Tyrus.</hi> (and which was afterward removed from thence to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to conſecrate a Temple or Church, which the Emperour had builded there.) <hi>The Emperour,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Secra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,) willed the Biſhops aſſembled at Tyrus, to debate, together with other matters, the contentions rayſed about Athanaſius, to the end, (all quarells being removed,) they might afterward cheerefully ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize the conſecration of that Church, and dedicate the ſame unto God.</hi> So that, all the matters layd to <hi>Athanaeſius</hi> his charge, being not ſingly and ſeverally, but joyntly together conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and they all tending, to the ſlaunder, defamation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of ſo worthy, reverend, and renowned a Biſhop, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the event, that it was at laſt, in thoſe times, held, and concluded, to bee <hi>Negotium Synodale, &amp; Epiſcopale, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meete for a Synode, or Councell of Biſhops, to conſider of, and to determine.</hi> And ſo indeede was it done accordingly. Now then,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2756:38"/> when <hi>Athanaſius</hi> went to the Emperour for refuge, appealing from this wicked, and injurious Councell of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> unto the ſame Emperour, in this his Epiſcopall, &amp; Eccleſiaſticall cauſe: Is it not thereby, verie evident, that hee approved of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Emperour in a cauſe Eccleſiaſticall? But if yet, you make any doubt hereof, you may ſee further in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 68. that as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> appealed to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> ſo <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> himſelfe ſaith, that by that example of the Apoſtle, hee would likewiſe <hi>appeale to the Emperour of his time:</hi> and hee ſaith there further, that beyond the Emperour, there was in his dayes no appeale to be made to any, but to God onely, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently not to the Pope.</p>
            <p n="16">16. But you demaund of me certaine queſtions wherein you would be reſolved: The firſt is, whether I hold, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the ſpirituall ſupremacie to be in the King? I cannot but wonder at this queſtion of yours. For I have often told you, in my <hi>Reply,</hi> that it is a Civill and Temporall ſupremacie, over perſons Eccleſiaſticall, and in cauſes alſo Eccleſiaſticall, which I give unto Kings. What? have wee beene ſo long diſputing about the point of <hi>Supremacie?</hi> And doe you not yet know the ſtate of the queſtion betwixt us? <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome, <hi>that would bee Doctors of the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>and yet underſtand not what they ſpeake, nor whereof they affirme:</hi> Of this ſort, it ſeemeth, you are, by this queſtion propounded. But I anſwere you once more, that it is not, (as you have often ſaid, and often miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,) a ſpirituall, but a Civill and Temporall ſupremacie, that I attribute to Emperours, Kings, and Princes, in cauſes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, and over Perſons Eccleſiaſticall. And as for the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſupremacie, it belongeth rightly and properly to Chriſt Ieſus, the onely Spirituall King, Head, and Monarch, of his whole Church. For when hee was demaunded, touching his kingdome, hee anſwered thus: <hi>My kingdome is not of this world:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18 36.</note> thereby declaring, that hee was not a worldly, or terreſtriall King, but a ſpirituall King. And therefore alſo when they would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him. a terreſtriall King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.15.</note> hee would none of it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and departed from them. And ſo likewiſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> true, and faithfull Apoſtle, (ſpeaking of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the reſt of the Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters,) <hi>that the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2756:39"/> weapons of their warfare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>are not carnall, but mightie through God:</hi> that is, they bee divine, and ſpirituall, and not worldly or ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall. And in reſpect of this his ſpirituall kingdome, or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſupremacie, all Emperours, Kings, Princes, and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9.10.11. <hi>Math.</hi> 28.18 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20.21.22.23.</note> aſwell as all Biſhops, and others, of what degree ſoever, muſt acknowledge their ſubjection unto him. <hi>For to him is given all power both in heaven and in earth. And hee it is, whom God hath ſet at his right band farre above all principalitie, and power, &amp; might, and dominion, and everie name, that is named, not in this world onely, but alſo in that which is to come. And hee hath made all things ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, under his feete, and hath given him, over all things, to bee the bead to the church, which is his body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25</note> And, <hi>Hee muſt raigne untill he hath put all his enemies under his feete.</hi> You ſee then, that this ſpirituall kingdome, or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Monarchy and ſupremacie, belongeth onely to Chriſt Ieſus, and not to any terreſtriall Emperour, King, Prince, Pope, or Prelate whatſoever. And therefore when you attribute, (as you doe,) the ſpirituall ſupremacie to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well, how great &amp; intolerable the offence is. For is it not (as I ſaid before) direct high treaſon in a ſubject, to intrude, and uſurpe upon the kingdome of his ſoveraigne, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his ſupremacie, Royall rights, authorities, and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives therein, without any warrant, or commiſsion from him? And is it then any leſſe then high treaſon, for the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to doe the ſame, in the ſpirituall kingdome of CHRIST IESVS? If you ſay that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> is but onely the <hi>Vicar,</hi> or <hi>Vice-roy,</hi> or <hi>Deputie,</hi> unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in that his kingdome: I demaund who conſtituted, or appointed him to bet ſo? For is not he ſtill a traytor to his King, that entreth upon his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, poſſeſſeth, and enjoyeth it, under colour, and pretence, that hee is appointed by his ſoveraigne, to bee the <hi>Vice-roy,</hi> or <hi>Lord deputie</hi> of the kingdome, when <hi>revera,</hi> (whatſoever he pretendeth, hee neyther hath nor can ſhew any Letters-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Warrant, or Commiſsion from his King for the ſame? Such is the caſe of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> For neyther the Pope, nor all his partakers, doe, or be able to ſhew any warrant or commiſsion from Chriſt, in that behalfe: They have beene long ſeeking out ſuch a warrant and commiſsion, but they
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2756:39"/> could never yet, nor ever will be able to finde it. If then this be high treaſon againſt Chriſt, in the Pope: do your ſelfe judge what offence it is in you, or others, that take part with him therein, and bee his adherents, followers, and maintayners. The ſecond queſtion you demaund of mee, is, whether the whole Church being but one, there be any moe heads of it then one? I anſwer, that the whole Church,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12 13.14. <hi>&amp;c. Epheſ.</hi> 1.22.23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.10.</note> being (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it,) <hi>The body of Ghriſt: This one body,</hi> can have no moe then one head: and, <hi>that one head is</hi> CHRIST IESVS, as the ſame <hi>S. Paul,</hi> againe expreſſely teacheth and affirmeth. And therefore, this head, is not the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> as you ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſtrangely dreame your ſelfe incline to this, that there ſhould be but <hi>one Head to this one Body.</hi> How then can you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any moe heads unto it, then this one, which is Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? For, if you make CHRIST IESVS to be one head, and the Pope to be another head, you make this one body to have two heads, and ſo make it a Monſter. As for your diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, of a <hi>Vitall head,</hi> and a <hi>Miniſteriall head,</hi> it is before remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and taken away in my firſt Booke, pag 94. 95. 96. 97. whereto you have not anſwered. And whereas you ſay, that the Church Militant, conſiſting both of <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> is but <hi>Vnum ovile, One ſheepefould,</hi> and that this one <hi>Sheepefould,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.16.</note> there is but <hi>unus Pastor, on paſtor,</hi> or <hi>one ſheepheard,</hi> it is true: but this <hi>unus paſtor, one ſheepheard,</hi> is not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.11.14.</note> (as you ſtill fondly fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,) the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but CHRIST IESVS onely, as appeareth in the ſame Chapter. And in this reſpect, he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo called, <hi>Magnus paſtor ovium, The great ſheepheard of the Sheepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20.</note> Yea, the chiefe, or ſupreme Paſtor, over all the ſeverall Paſtors of all the ſeverall flockes in the world.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2 3 4.</note> For thus <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to them all: <hi>Feede the flocke of God, which dependeth upon you, caring for it not by conſtraint, but willingly: not for filthy lucre, of a readie minde: not as though yee were Lords over Gods heritage, but that yee may be examples to the flocke: And when the chiefe Sheepheard ſhall appeare yee ſhall receive an incorruptible crowne of glory.</hi> Here you ſee, that <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſheweth very plainely that not himſelfe, (though hee were an Apoſtle,) much leſſe the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other Biſhop, was to have this high and tranſcendent name of Chiefe or ſupreme Paſtor, over all
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2756:40"/> the reſt of the ſeverall Paſtors: For to CHRIST IESVS onely hee attributeth, and appropriateth this tittle, as being his peculiar and prerogative: in aſmuch as it is Chriſt Ieſus onely, and not the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor any other man mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall whoſoever that can give this incorruptible crowne of glorie he there ſpeaketh of. Not the Pope then, nor any other, but CHRIST IESVS onely, appeareth to bee the chiefe or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Paſtor, or (which commeth all to one reckoning,) the Vniverſall Biſhop, over all the ſeverall Biſhops, and ſeverall Paſtors, diſperſed in the world. Your owne tranſlation in this Text of 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. is, <hi>Princeps Pastorum, the Prince of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors:</hi> which likewiſe ſtill ſheweth, that not the Pope, but CHRIST IESVS onely, is the ſupreme Paſtor, or the Prince of the ſeverall Paſtors diſperſed on the face of the Earth. And therefore was it alſo decreed in the Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 26. that <hi>Primae ſedis Epiſcopus, non appelletur Princeps ſacerdotum, vel ſummus ſacerdos, aut aliquid huiuſmodi, ſed tantum primae ſedis Epiſcopus: The Biſhop of the firſt Sea, may not bee called, the Prince of Priests, or the the chiefe Prieſt, or any ſuch like, but onely Biſhop of the firſt Sea.</hi> And <hi>Gratian</hi> addeth further as touching the title of <hi>Vniverſall Biſhop,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Distinct. <hi>99.</hi> prim. ſed.</note> 
               <hi>Neyther let the Biſhop of Rome be ſo called.</hi> Now then to come to anſwere you, alſo touching <hi>Nero,</hi> and other Heathen, &amp; perſecuting Emperours, and Kings: It is true, that they have the ſame Civill ſword, power, and authoritie committed to them from God, which the Chriſtian Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and the Chriſtian Kings have, and to the ſame end; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3.4</note> 
               <hi>for the puniſhment of evill doers, and for the prayſe of them that doe well:</hi> But if they puniſh good, and godly men, and well-doers, (as <hi>Nero</hi> did, when hee put <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and <hi>S. Paul,</hi> to death, and as the other Emperours, and Kings doe, which perſecute the true and Orthodoxe Chriſtians) This is not the right uſing, but abuſing of the ſword and authoritie, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them. So that, the power, and authoritie is the ſame to both: but the difference is in the uſe, or abuſe of that Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. All the ſupremacie, power, and authoritie graunted from God, to any Emperours, Kings, and Princes, within their Dominions, ought to be imployed for God, and not againſt him, in any ſort. And according hereunto, the true Chriſtian
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2756:40"/> Emperours, and Kings, uſe their Civill ſwords, and authorities for God, and for advancement of his ſervice, truth, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And although Heathen, and Infidell Emperours and Kings doe commonly abuſe that ſword, and authoritie, (which God hath given them,) againſt God, and againſt his ſervice, ſervants, and religion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>&amp;c. Ezra,</hi> 6.1.2 3 <hi>&amp;c. Ezra</hi> 7.12.13.14.15.16.17 18. <hi>&amp;c. Dan.</hi> 3.28.29. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.24.25.26.</note> Yet if any Heathen Emperour, or King doe commaund any thing for God, or for his ſervice, worſhip, or religion, (as they may doe, and ſometimes have done,) (as appeareth by the examples of <hi>King Cyrus, King Darius, King Artaxerxes, King Nabuchadnezzar, and others:</hi>) therein, they are no leſſe to bee obeyed, then if it had beene commaunded, by the godlyeſt, &amp; beſt profeſſed Chriſtian King in the world. And this you may ſee further declared, in my firſt Booke, Chap. 1. pag 7. and in my <hi>Reply,</hi> pag. 44. 45. Wherefore, it is evident, that even Pagan and Heathen Kings, have the ſame ſupremacie, power, and authoritie, within their Kingdomes and Dominions, to commaund for God, his ſervice, &amp; religion, which Chriſtian Kings and Princes have: although, they doe not, (as they ſhould,) evermore uſe, extend, and imploy, that their power, and authoritie, accordingly, for God, and his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: and conſequently, the defect, is not in reſpect, of any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, or authoritie, (which they want not,) but in reſpect of their underſtandings, wils, and affections, which being depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and corrupted, and not rectified or ſanctified, nor conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Chriſt, and Chriſtianitie, doe carrie them awry, and the wrong way.</p>
            <p>But you propound unto mee, yet further, another queſtion, which is this. What if the King of <hi>Slavonia,</hi> or any other king miſled by frailtie, ignorance, or malice, ſhould imploy their powers to force their ſubjectes from the true Religion, and thereby ſubvert, and ruinate, not onely their owne ſoules, but the ſoules of their ſubjects alſo: Might not the King in this caſe, being, (as you call him,) a ſcabbed ſheepe, (all other meanes fayling of his recoverie,) be compelled by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to imbrace Gods true faith and religion, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte the ſame freedome unto his ſubjects? I anſwer, no. For, firſt, what right, or authoritie, from God, hath the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in this caſe, to compell Kings, and Princes, more th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2756:41"/> other Biſhops, have? Yea, neyther the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor any other Biſhop, or Eccleſiaſticall Miniſter, hath any ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, or authoritie, included, or compriſed, within thoſe their Eccleſiaſticall callings and Miniſteries, as by worldly power, and externall force of Armes, to compell a King to the right religion. It is true, that the Miniſters of Chriſt may exhort, &amp; perſwade the beſt they can, a King erring in his Religion, from his error, and may doe, what their Eccleſiaſticall commiſsion graunted them from Chriſt, will warrant them to doe, but no further may they goe: for then doe they, <hi>Fines alienos inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Invade other mens bounds, (S. Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh,) <hi>as kings have the temporall ſword, to commaund, and to compell:</hi> Biſhops, Paſtors and Miniſters Eccleſiaſticall, have not that but another ſword to uſe, namely, <hi>a ſpirituall ſword,</hi> or <hi>ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17.</note> as <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth &amp; defineth it. And therefore theſe two ſwords muſt bee diſtinguiſhed, and not confounded. Yea, Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, whilſt hee was here upon earth, would not meddle with worldly, or temporall matters. For when one ſpake unto him, deſiring him, <hi>to bid his brother, to devide the inheritance with him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.13 14. <hi>Math,</hi> 16.19</note> 
               <hi>hee refuſed, and ſaid: Man, who made mee to be a Iudge, or a devider over you?</hi> If you object, that Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter: Whatſoever thou bindest on earth, ſhalbe bound in heaven, and whatſoever thou looſeſt on earth ſhalbe looſed in heaven.</hi> Remember, that hee ſpake alſo the ſame thing plural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all the Apoſtles, giving to them all alike the ſame autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18.18</note> ſaying thus <hi>Quicquid ligaveritis, &amp;c. Whatſoever yee binde on earth, ſhalbe bound in heaven: and whatſoever yee looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> You cannot therefore by vertue of thoſe wordes, inferre, that <hi>Peter,</hi> or his ſucceſſors had any more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to depoſe Kings, or to compell them in any ſort, to the right religion, or to any thing elſe, then eyther <hi>Iames,</hi> or <hi>Iohn,</hi> or the reſt of the Apoſtles, or any of their ſucceſſors had, in the like caſe; For, the ſame authoritie, and in the ſame wordes, is, (as you ſee,) graunted aſwell to the one, as to the other. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe, muſt you forget or omit the former part of thoſe wordes ſpoken by CHRIST unto <hi>Peter,</hi> which bee theſe: <hi>I will give unto thee the keyes of the kingdome of heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19.</note> For the ſubſequent wordes, (ſpoken to him,) of binding, and looſing,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2756:41"/> have reference thereunto and: are therefore to bee expounded, not of things earthly, or concerning terreſtiall matters, or worldly kingdomes, but of things concerning another world and kingdome, namely, concerning the kingdome of heaven. And ſo alſo doth <hi>S. Bernard</hi> directly declare, ſaying thus, to <hi>Eugenius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome: Ergo in criminibus, non in poſſeſsionibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard de conſiderat. ad Eugen. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>poteſtas veſtra: Quoniam propter illa, non propter has, accepiſtu cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves regni coelorum. Your power,</hi> (ſaith hee,) <hi>concerneth ſinnes, and not matters of poſſeſsion: becauſe, for thoſe, and not for theſe yee have received the keyes of the kingdome of heaven.</hi> Yea, that the keyes of the kingdome of heaven were alſo graunted equally and alike, to all the Apoſtles, I have further ſhewed, very fully, and plainely, in my firſt Booke, pag. 292. 293. 294. &amp;c. And that no part of the power of thoſe keyes, no, not <hi>Excommunication</hi> it ſelfe, (were it never ſo juſtly, or lawfully awarded,) is of any force, by Gods law and inſtitution, to depoſe Kings, or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anall the duetie &amp; allegeance of ſubjects, I have likewiſe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame my firſt Booke, pag. 299. 300. 301. By what right, or reaſon then, ſhall or can the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (who is alſo <hi>revera</hi> no Miniſter of Chriſt at all, but the very apparant grand Antichriſt, (as I have proved at large, throughout the third part of my firſt Booke,) clayme to have any ſuch exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power coactive, or compulſive over Kings? But moreover this queſtion here propounded by you was ſufficently anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and reſolved before, by <hi>S Chryſostome,</hi> in the caſe of king <hi>Vzziah,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Ozias,</hi> where hee putteth this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the King, and the Prieſt; that <hi>Ille cogit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yſosto. de verbis Eſaiae, vidi Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homil. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>hic ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatur: Ille habet arma ſenſibilia, hic arma ſpiritualia. The King compelleth, the Prieſt exhorteth: the King hath the ſenſible weapons: the Prieſt, the ſpirituall weapons.</hi> And when the Prieſt, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Miniſter, hath gone as far, as he can go in his Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Miniſterie, he muſt not go any further, to uſe any exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power coactive or compulſive, as he there alſo teacheth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 21.1.</note> but muſt in every ſuch caſe leave men unto God, who hath the hearts of all kings, aſwell as of others, in his hands, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and turneth them, when,<note place="margin">Chryſ de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerlotis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and which way ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Yea, <hi>S. Chryſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tome</hi> ſaith yet further expreſſely. <hi>That it is not lawfull for a Biſhop, to oure men with ſo great authoritie, as a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2756:42"/> ſheepheard doth his ſheepe: for it is free for a ſheepheard forcibly to binde his ſheepe, to drive them from their feeding, to ſcare them, and to cut them: but in the other caſe, the facilitie of the cure, conſiſteth no in him that giveth, but onely in him, that taketh the medicine.</hi> This, that admirable teacher perceiving, ſaid to the <hi>Corinthians: Not that wee have any Dominion over you: under the name of faith, but that wee are helpers of your ioy. For of all men, Chriſtian Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops muſt not correct the faults of offenders by force or violence. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Iudges, when they take any tranſgreſsing the lawes, they ſhew themſelves to be endued with great authoritie, and power, and doe compell them, whether they will or no, to change their manners: But here, (ſaith hee,) non vim afferre, ſed ſuadere tantum oportet, atque hac ratione meliorem efficere, quem emendandum ſuſceperis: You may not uſe violence but perſwaſion onely, and by this meanes, make him better, whom you have taken upon you to amend.</hi> Againe hee ſaith: <hi>If any ſheepe goe out of the right way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. de Sacerdotio lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and leaving the plentifull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, graze on barren, and steepe places: The ſheepheard ſomewhat exalteth his voyce, to reduce the diſperſed and ſtragling ſheepe, and to force them to the flocke: But if any man wander from the right path of the Chriſtian faith: The Paſtor muſt uſe great great paines care, and patience: Neque enim vis illi inferenda, neque terrore ille cogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, verum ſuedendu tantùm, ut de integro ad veritatem redeat: For hee may nor be forced, or conſtrained with terror, but perſwaded one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſo hee may returne againe to the truth.</hi> If then your late Councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> under Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> decreed, (as you ſay,) <hi>this externall power coactive, to bee in the Biſhop of Rome:</hi> You ſee, it is not to be regarded: Becauſe ſuch a decree, (if any ſuch were,) is directly contrarie to the teſtimonie of all former approved antiquitie. But yet you muſt alſo remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what <hi>Platina</hi> writeth concerning that Councell.<note place="margin">Plantina de vita Innocen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Venêre multa tum quidem in conſultationem, nec decerni tamen quicquam aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè potuit: Many things,</hi> (ſaith hee,) <hi>came into conſultation, in that Councell, but nothing could plainely be decided: by reaſon, the Pope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, to compoſe ſome tumults, then ſuddainely riſen, died by the way.</hi> So that, this your great Councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> conſulting how to defeate Kings and Princes, of their Temporall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Dominions, but not decreeing, or concluding any thing therein, as being prevented by the Popes haſtened and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2756:42"/> unexpected death, will alſo doe you no pleaſure, in this caſe. But now, why may not I, after ſo many queſtions of yours anſwered, propound you alſo one queſtion? which is this. What if the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for maintenance of his worldly pompe, pride, pleaſure, and ambition, careleſly neglect all right religion, and bee ſo extremely wicked, both for life, &amp; doctrine, as that hee careth not to carrie innumerable ſoules, together with his owne, by heapes, to hell: who ſhall correct, reſtraine, repreſſe, or puniſh him? For anſwer whereunto, you might ſay, that in former, and auncient times, The Emperours had the correction, and the puniſhment, aſwell of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> as of other Biſhops, that were offenders, within their Dominions: But now the caſe is altered, and the world tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned topſie turvie, and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> growne to that height and licenciouſneſſe, as that hee will not allow himſelfe to be cenſured, or judged by any men mortall, be they Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Kings, Princes, Biſhops, Generall Councels, or whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they bee. But whilſt he is thus mounted, not onely above other Kings, and Princes, but even above the Emperours alſo himſelfe. What ſaith <hi>Optatus</hi> of ſuch a one?<note place="margin">Optat. libr. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cùm ſuper Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem non ſit, niſi ſolus Deus, qui fecit Imperatorem: certè quiſe ſuper Imperatorem extollit, iam quaſi hominum exceſſerit metas, ſe ut Deum non hominem, aeſtimat: Foraſmuch as,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>there is none above the Emperour, but God onely, that made the Emperour: Certainely, be that exalteth himſelfe above the Emperour, as one that hath gone beyond the bounds of men, eſteemeth himſelfe, not now any longer as a mac, but as God.</hi> And whileſt withall, hee thus exempteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, from the Lawes, cenſure, and judgement of all men upon earth: what doth hee elſe, by all this, but ſhew himſelfe to be, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That lawleſſe perſon,</hi> mentioned by <hi>S. Paul,</hi> in 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>And which alſo ſitteth in the Church, or temple of God, as God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>and is exalted above all thoſe men upon earth, that be called Gods in the Scriptures,</hi> (of which ſort be Kings, and Princes,) and even above the Emperour alſo himſelfe, to whom belongeth that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſebaſma,</hi> (mentioned in the ſame place of, 2. <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2.4.) in aſmuch as hee is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſebaſtos,</hi> that is, <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> as the Scripture alſo it ſelfe expreſſely calleth him, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.21.25. But laſtly, It is well knowne that by Gods owne inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2756:43"/> the power of the Civill and Temporall ſword, rightly, &amp; properly belongeth to Emperours,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om.</hi> 13.1.2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.5.6.</note> Kings, and Princes, and not to Biſhops, Paſtors, or other Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may Kings and Princes lawfully commaund, compell, and puniſh all Biſhops, Paſtors, and Eccleſiaſticall Miniſters what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, (if they offend,) aſwell as lay-Perſons, by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of that their ſword, committed to them from God: But Biſhops on the other ſide may not by that their Eccleſiaſticall office and function uſe that temporall ſword, nor any tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall externall power coactive thereunto incident or belonging, againſt any King, or other Perſon, for any cauſe whatſoever: becauſe that ſword is not committed to them from God: Yea, this opinion concerning compelling of Kings, ſavoureth more of treaſon, then of reaſon, and therefore is utterly to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, and abhorred.</p>
            <p n="17">17. But then you ſay further, that whatſoever I alledged to inveſt our King with the ſupremacie, the ſame might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by any Iudge in <hi>Spaine,</hi> or <hi>Hungarie,</hi> or other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to prove the ſupremacie, to bee likewiſe in their kings. And why not? For it is a thing of right, belonging to all Kings, to have the ſupremacie within their ſeverall Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and to uſe, and extend that their power and authoritie, for God, and for the advancement of his true ſervice, and right religion, aſwell as for the advancement of Civill Iuſtice, and externall peace, amongſt their ſubjects. And what hurt were it to any, if all the Kings in Chriſtendome, yea if all the kings in the world did this? or rather how great, ample &amp; unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keable a benefite, would thereby accrew and come, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all Chriſtendome, but to the whole world? If all the Kings in Chriſtendome, or in the whole world, did extend their authoritie,<note place="margin">2, <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17 1.2.3.4. <hi>&amp;c. Revel.</hi> 18.4.</note> for the maintenance, and advancement of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, (which is indeede, the adulterate, corrupt, and falſe Religion,) it being, (as the holy Scripture it ſelfe hath noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and declared it to be,) <hi>the Religion of the grand Antichriſt, and of the whore of Babylon, which all Gods people be commaunded to forſake,</hi>) even Papiſts themſelves, out of the error of their judgement, would thinke it to bee well done: How much more, in true, judgement, ought you, and they, to thinke it to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2756:43"/> be well done, if they did all imploy their Civill ſword, power, and authoritie, for the advancement of that, which is indeed, the moſt auncient, true, Chriſtian, Catholicke, and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Religion?</p>
            <p>But you have yet ſtill a conceite, that it is requiſite, &amp; neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, to have a Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> as a ſupreme Paſtor, or a ſupreme Iudge, to decide, and determine all hereſies, errors, doubts, queſtions, and controverſies concerning faith, and religion, that ariſe in the Church, and ſo to preſerve peace and unitie in it, by his infallible, and unerrable judgement. Howbeit, firſt, why ſhould the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> be this ſupreme Paſtor, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Iudge, more then the Biſhop of <hi>Antioch, Conſtantinople, Alexandria, Ieruſalem,</hi> or any other Biſhop? For where hath God conſtituted the one to bee ſo, more then the other? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, how doe you prove the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to have an infallible &amp; an unerrable judgement, more then other Biſhops have? Yea even in the Preface of my firſt Booke, pag. 14.15. 16. and againe in the ſecond part of that ſame my firſt Booke, Chap. 1. pag. 54.55. I have proved, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> may erre, even in matters of faith, aſwell as any other Biſhop: and the ſame doth alſo before appeare in this Booke likewiſe. Thirdly, if the ſupremacie, and Monarchie of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> have this vertue in it, to keepe and maintayne peace and unitie in the Church, and to decide, and determine cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, truely, and infallibly, all doubts, queſtions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Religion: Why doth hee not decide and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all thoſe queſtions &amp; controverſies, that ſo it might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally appeare, to have that vertue in it? or what neede is there then, of Generall Councels, yea of any Councels at all? For, the uſe, and end of Synods and Councels, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, and determine queſtions, and controverſies, that doe ariſe, and ſpread themſelves, to the diſquiet, and trouble of the Church: all which, bee ſuperfluous, if the certaine truth in everie queſtion, may be had, immediately, from his mouth. But indeede this inſtitution of Synods, or Councels, is a divine inſtitution, and therefore muſt ſtand: although, that humane invention of the Popes ſupremacie, needeleſly erected for the ſame uſe, and end, doe utterly fall, and be diſanulled. And
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2756:44"/> what neceſsitie is there of him. For even Generall Conncels, were ſummoned, and convocated in times paſt by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours: and may be ſtill at this day convocated, by the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent, and authoritie, of the ſeverall Kings, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the ſeverall Nations. Neyther is the judgement of one man, (as namely of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> or of any other,) ſo ſtrong, or powerfull, to pull out errors, that be rooted in mens mindes,<note place="margin">Conc. Affric. cap. <hi>138.</hi> epiſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad Celeſtinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> as is the judgement, and conſent of many in a Synod or Councell: <hi>Vnleſſe there be any, that thinketh, God inſpireth one particular perſon with righteouſneſſe, &amp; forſaketh a number of prieſts, aſſembled together in a Councell:</hi> which, the Councell of <hi>Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> held to be verie abſurd, and repugnant to Chriſt his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſo long as they meete together, in his name, and for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his truth. And here you may obſerve a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, betweene the <hi>wiſedome of God,</hi> and the <hi>wiſedome of Men:</hi> For, in the Apoſtles times, there aroſe at <hi>Antioch,</hi> a great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which was, whether Circumciſion were neceſſarie to ſalvation:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15 1.2 3.4 5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> what doe they in this caſe? Doe they chooſe, and appoint ſome one man as chiefe, to whom they will referre the deciding, and determining of this queſtion? No ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And yet if they would have had the controverſie decided, and determined by <hi>One:</hi> who was fitter to have beene that <hi>one,</hi> then <hi>S. Paul,</hi> whom they had amongſt them? But they take no ſuch courſe, but ſend <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and certaine others to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> What to doe? Was it to deſire the judgement on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſome one man there, as namely of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> or of any one other? No. But to have the matter decided, by a Synod or Councell, of the Apoſtles, Elders, and others, therein to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, for that purpoſe: and in which Synod, or Councell, it was determined accordingly. If then, in thoſe times of the Apoſtles, when there was ſo great abundance of the gifts of God, and when as controverſies, might without danger of error, have beene referred unto one onely, The rule of <hi>One</hi> above all the reſt, was not held meete, and convenient: Now when the gifts are leſſe, and the danger of error more, Can is be thought a wiſedome conſonant to the <hi>wiſedome of the holy Ghost,</hi> to erect, and conſtitute. (as the ſeduced world hath done,) <hi>One man,</hi> namely, the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2756:44"/> Iudge, and that a verie ſure, and infallible one, (as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him,) for the deciding and determining of all doubts, queſtions, and controverſies, that ariſe, throughout the whole world, concerning Faith and Religion, and upon whom, as being, (in their opinions,) the Monarch, and head of the whole, and univerſall Church upon Earth, they doe, (though overboldly, and dangerouſly,) relye, and depend? It is true, that the regiment or governement of the Church is <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall:</hi> but that is not in reſpect of the Pope, but in reſpect of CHRIST IESVS, who is, indeede, the right, true, and ſole Monarch, and head of his whole Church: But in reſpect of the Biſhops and Paſtors, that be rulers, or governours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt, it is, (as the Proteſtants have rightly taught, and defended againſt the Papiſts, not <hi>Monarchiall,</hi> but <hi>Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall.</hi> Yea, Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, told his Apoſtles, (and, in them, all Biſhops, their ſucceſſors,) when they contended for a Majoritie, or Monarchy among themſelves: that <hi>Reges gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium dominanturijs: vos autem non ſic:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.24 25.26. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Quis eorum Maior.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The kings of Nations beare dominion over them, but yee may not doe ſo, one over another.</hi> For, of this was the queſtion, or contention: and therefore of this muſt the anſwere bee accordingly underſtood. Theſe words then doe cleerely declare, that there ſhould bee no Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call King, or Eccleſiaſticall Monarch amongſt them, to rule, or raigne over all the reſt: although terreſtriall Kings and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches did, and are well allowed to raigne and rule over the people of thoſe Nations, whereof they be Kings. But againe, hath not <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> himſelfe told us long agone, not onely how needeleſſe and ſuperfluous, but how pernicious alſo and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it was to the whole Church, to admitte of one to bee an <hi>univerſall Biſhop,</hi> or an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Monarch,</hi> to rule,<note place="margin">Gregorie.</note> and raigne over all the reſt? <hi>For then,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>if hee which is the Eccleſiasticall Monarch, or the univerſall Biſhop, doe fall, the whole and univerſall Church falleth with him.</hi> And what <hi>Gregory</hi> thus ſpake, and as it were prophecied ſo long ſince, was afterward found true and came to paſſe accordingly, to the lamentable woe of the whole Church, in the ſucceeding times, by that meanes. Yea the ſame <hi>S. Gregory</hi> hath yet further certified us how pernicious, and dangerous this was, and would bee, not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2756:45"/> onely to the whole Church, but even to himſelfe alſo, that would take upon him, to be the Eccleſiaſticall Monarch, or ſupreme and univerſall Biſhop over all.<note place="margin">Gregory.</note> 
               <hi>For,</hi> (ſaith hee,) <hi>what wilt thou anſwer unto Chriſt, who is the true head of the univerſall Church, in that day of iudgement, when by this name of univerſall Biſhop, thou ſeekeſt to ſubiugate, all the members of his Body unto thy ſelfe? Whom doſt thou imitate herein, ſave onely him, who in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thoſe legions of Angels, which were his fellowes, ſought to mount aloft to the top of ſingularitie, where hee might bee ſubiect to none, and all others might be ſubiect unto him.</hi> As for the having of Biſhops of Dioceſes, and Provinces, it no more proveth that therefore there may or muſt be one univerſall Biſhop, or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Monarch over all: then that, becauſe there be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Kings in divers and ſeverall Kingdomes, therefore there ſhould be one univerſall King over all the Kings and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in the world. And beſides, there were Biſhops of Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſes, and Provinces in the times both of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom nevertheleſſe they tooke no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt, nor diſallowed: But him that would take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to be an Eccleſiaſticall Monarch, or a ſupreme and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Biſhop over the whole Church, him they would not endure, but vehemently impugned and deteſted him, and that not without verie apparant, juſt, and good cauſe, as here you ſee. But, moreover, did you never reade <hi>Iohn Gerſon de Aufe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribilitate Papae.</hi> What he affirmed in ſome caſes, may generally and abſolutely be affirmed: namely, That the Pope may bee utterly aboliſhed, and taken cleane away, &amp; that without any leſſe or hurt at all to Chriſtendome, yea to the great, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple good, not onely of Chriſtendome, but of all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, if the matter be well weighed and rightly and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered.</p>
            <p n="18">18. But touching this point of ſupremacie, you ſeeme at laſt, in words, to appeale to the judgement of the Primitive Church: I would you would doe as you ſay, and ſtand to the judgement of it, in verie deede. For I have proved, (which you have not diſproved, nor ever will bee able to diſprove,) That for the ſpace of eight hundred yeares, and more, after Chriſt, even the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> themſelves, aſwell as other
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2756:45"/> Biſhops were ſubject to the Emperours. And that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours, had alſo authoritie in matters Eccleſiaſticall, aſwell as Civill and temporall, within their Dominions: and nothing doe you, or can you alledge againſt it, but what hath beene many and ſundrie times ſufficiently, &amp; abundantly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, &amp; confuted by the Proteſtants. As for that Catalogue of Emperours, Kings, and Princes, which you affirme to have beene exemplarily puniſhed in this world by violent, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable deathes, for oppugning and ſtriving againſt the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie and ſupremacie of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> you onely ſay, &amp; ſuppoſe it, but doe not prove it. And it is an overbold part in you, to enter into Gods ſecret counſels, and to affirme that to be the cauſe which you know not, nor be able to prove. For there might be, and ſo no doubt there were other juſt cauſes of their puniſhments. As for the oppugning of the Popes ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie that could not be the cauſe of thoſe or of any other pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments: in aſmuch as the groſſe wrongs, and utter unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, hath before plentifully appeared: and that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, nor all his partakers, be able to ſhew, any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion or warrant from God for the approbation of it. Yea, how could the oppugning or contending againſt the Popes Monarchie and ſupremacie, be any cauſe of puniſhment, when in the holy Scriptures themſelves it appeareth, (as in my firſt Booke I have ſhewed at large,) that <hi>Papall Rome</hi> is the <hi>whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and that the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> the head, and ruler of that adulterate, and Popiſh Church, is the verie grand <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> Doe not therefore deceive your ſelfe, nor others any longer, by miſtaking the cauſe, which is, you know, a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie, <hi>à cauſa non, ut cauſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet you further ſay, that I am argued by the wiſeſt, in this Enterprize to have diſcovered in conſideratively, much arrogancie of witt, in not well weighing the mayne importance of this difficultie, farre ſurmounting the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of a Lawyer. But firſt, there is no ſuch difficultie in it,<note place="margin">Reges Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium domina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur.</note> as you ſpeake of: and this I have formerly declared. Secondly, why doth it ſurmount, or exceede a Lawyers talent and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, more in mee, then in you? Wherefore, if I bee, as you ſay I am,) cenſured, or argued, by the wiſeſt, of much arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2756:46"/> becauſe being a Lawyer, I meddle in this matter: Muſt not thoſe wiſeſt, in all juſtice, and equitie condemne you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, of much arrogancie, for the ſame cauſe? For you have hitherto in your writings, affirmed your ſelfe to be a Lawyer: &amp; if all this while you nevertheleſſe be not a Lawyer, you have done your ſelfe a great deale of diſcredite and diſhonour in affirming it: Neyther can any man then tell, how to beleeve you, in any thing you ſpeake, or write: So that herein you gull not mee, but your ſelfe, and others. It would therefore beſt become you, to unmaske your ſelfe, and to diſcover your ſelfe plainely: For you muſt thinke, howſoever you would conceale your ſelfe, that you are ſufficiently knowne, and goe not inviſible. But thirdly, who are thoſe, whom you call and account, the wiſeſt? For there bee ſome that be wiſe in their owne conceite: and ſome that be Antichriſtianly wiſe, and ſome that bee worldly wiſe:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19.</note> whoſe wiſedome is, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth it, <hi>fooliſhneſſe with God. For, hath not God,</hi> (ſaith hee,) <hi>made the wiſedome of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>fooliſhneſſe?</hi> The world accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the wiſedome of God to bee fooliſhneſſe. But, hee ſaith, <hi>that the fooliſhneſſe of God, is wiſer then men: and the weakeneſſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>ſtronger then men.</hi> The wiſeſt men, then, doubtleſſe bee thoſe, that humbly ſubmit all their learning, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to Gods word, and wiſedome, and that bee divinely, and Chriſtianly wiſe: as for the reſt, they muſt, (as the ſame <hi>S. Paul</hi> teaceth them,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor</hi> 3.18.</note>) <hi>become fooles, that they may bee wiſe.</hi> Whatſoever therefore you ſay: I beleeve, that which Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe hath ſpoken, to bee true, and that it will ever bee found verified,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 7.35.</note> 
               <hi>(videlicet,) That wiſedome is iuſtified of all her Children.</hi> But laſtly, what arrogancie eyther of wit, or learning, doe I ſhew, or diſcover, when I neyther brag nor boaſt of eyther: and when I further, franckly and freely confeſſe in all my Bookes, that ſuch matter, as is therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, I have learned of others, and ſo attribute nothing to my ſelfe? The wit, and learning I have, how ſmall, ſlender, or meane ſoever you, or others, eſteeme it, I thanke God for it: and doe humbly pray him, to give mee the Grace, to uſe, and imploy it to his honour, and glorie, and not to mine owne. Yea, how weake or meane ſoever it bee, in reſpect
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2756:46"/> of it ſelfe, yet ſuch is the ſtrength of the cauſe which I defend, and the ſtrength of the Almightie who hath enabled mee in it, and to whom, I give all the thankes, and the glorie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.13.</note> as that it now appeareth, I hope to everie underſtanding, equall, and judicious Perſon, to bee undoubtedly victorious, and triumphant. Hereafter therefore I ſhall not neede to write any more in it, which is now made thus manifeſt, cleere, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, and invincible. So that everie man, that will ſpeake truely, may ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of it, that <hi>Magna est veritas &amp; praevalet.</hi> God open our eyes, (if it bee his will,) and inlighten all our underſtandings, that wee may all ſee and know his truth, acknowledge, reverence, embrace, and profeſſe it, and walke in the wayes of it evermore. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
